TST2-MUC4-0003

SAN SALVADOR, 18 DEC 89 (EL DIARIO DE HOY) -- [TEXT] A TERRORIST ARRESTED BY THE SALVADORAN NATIONAL POLICE, HAS BEEN IDENTIFIED AS RUTH ESPERANZA AGUILAR MARROQUIN, AKA SANDRA. SHE HAS DESCRIBED U.S. CITIZEN JENNIFER CASOLO AS AN ERP [PEOPLE'S REVOLUTIONARY ARMY] MEMBER IN CHARGE OF LOGISTICS.

AS HAS BEEN REPORTED, CASOLO WAS RELEASED BY A MILITARY JUDGE AFTER HE DETERMINED THAT THERE WAS NOT ENOUGH EVIDENCE AGAINST HER. SOME GROUPS, HOWEVER, ASSERT THAT CASOLO WAS RELEASED DUE TO POLITICAL PRESSURE FROM THE UNITED STATES, WHICH THREATENED TO LAUNCH A WORLDWIDE CAMPAIGN TO DISCREDIT EL SALVADOR IF CASOLO WAS NOT RELEASED.

AGUILAR MARROQUIN WAS ARRESTED AT 1500 ON 9 DECEMBER AFTER HAVING PARTICIPATED IN AN ATTACK ON AN URBAN PUBLIC BUS NEAR JUAN PABLO II BOULEVARD.

THE WOMAN FLED AND SOUGHT REFUGE INSIDE THE FACILITIES OF THE SALVADORAN ALBERTO MASFERRER UNIVERSITY, WHERE SHE TOOK A GROUP OF STUDENTS AS HOSTAGES, THREATENING THEM WITH HAND GRENADES. THE POLICE PREVENTED HER FROM DOING ANYTHING AND ARRESTED HER, CONFISCATING ONE .45-CALIBER PISTOL, BULLETS, CARTRIDGES, AND TWO FRAGMENTATION GRENADES.

AGUILAR MARROQUIN SAID THAT SHE JOINED THE ERP LAST MARCH AND THAT SHE WAS PART OF AN URBAN COMMANDO CALLED WORKERS JUSTICE COMMAND. AGUILAR ADDED THAT SHE KNOWS U.S. CITIZEN JENNIFER CASOLO, WHO BELONGS TO THE ERP, AND THAT CASOLO USED TO MEET WITH TERRORIST LEADER FERNANDO, WORKERS JUSTICE COMMAND OPERATIONS CHIEF, NEAR THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY SCHOOL OF DENTISTRY (UES).

AGUILAR ADDED THAT CASOLO WAS IN CHARGE OF ERP LOGISTICS, ESPECIALLY LODGING PEOPLE AND TRANSPORTING ARMS AND WAR EQUIPMENT. THE ERP HAD GIVEN HER TWO MINIBUSES FOR HER TO CARRY OUT HER TASKS.

IN ADDITION, AGUILAR SAID THAT SHE BELIEVES CASOLO HAD A LEADING POSITION WITHIN THE ORGANIZATION, BECAUSE IN ADDITION TO MEETING WITH FERNANDO, SHE ALSO MET WITH AN INDIVIDUAL KNOWN AS MINCHO, WHO IS THE POLITICAL-MILITARY ERP METROPOLITAN CHIEF AND ALSO THE CHIEF OF THE SO-CALLED URBAN COMMANDOS.

THE PRISONER KNEW ABOUT THE EXISTENCE OF THE ARMS IN CASOLO'S HOUSE, BECAUSE ON VARIOUS OCCASIONS AGUILAR'S CHIEF, KNOWN AS MIRIAM, TOLD HER ABOUT IT. OTHER TERRORISTS WENT TO CASOLO'S HOUSE TO GET WEAPONS, AMMUNITION, AND EXPLOSIVES TO CONDUCT THEIR SABOTAGE OPERATIONS AGAINST BUSES, TELEPHONE DISTRIBUTION BOXES, POWER PYLONS, OR TO CONDUCT LARGE OPERATIONS--AS AGUILAR DESCRIBED THEM-- SUCH AS ATTACKS ON MILITARY GARRISONS.

ACCORDING TO THE INFORMATION OBTAINED, THE PRISONER WILL BE SENT TO COURT OVER THE NEXT FEW DAYS.

TST2-MUC4-0004

LA PAZ, 20 DEC 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] A POWERFUL DYNAMITE CHARGE TODAY EXPLODED NEAR THE AMERICAN EMBASSY IN LA PAZ. THE POLICE REPORTED THAT THE EXPLOSION CAUSED CONSIDERABLE DAMAGE TO ALL BUILDINGS ON THE BLOCK.

THE EXPLOSION OCCURRED AT 2130 (0130 GMT) ON THURSDAY [AS RECEIVED]. IT DAMAGED WINDOWS OF THE BUILDINGS ON THE BLOCK.

JOSE PARADA GRANDY, THE BOLIVIAN POLICE CHIEF, TOLD EFE THAT AN UNIDENTIFIED PERSON STEPPED OUT OF A VEHICLE AND PLACED A PACKAGE IN ONE OF THE PLANT POTS ON JUAN DE LA RIVA STREET, A FEW METERS FROM THE U.S. EMBASSY IN DOWNTOWN LA PAZ.

PARADA SAID: "THE VEHICLE LEFT AND IMMEDIATELY THE CHARGE WENT OFF CAUSING CONSIDERABLE DAMAGE."

THE "ZARATE WILLKA ARMED FORCES OF LIBERATION," A GROUP WITH AN INDIAN BAKCGROUND, HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK IN A COMMUNIQUE THAT WAS SENT TO SOME MEDIA.

THE NOTE, SIGNED WITH THE INITIALS OF THE "ZARATE WILLKA" GROUP, STATES: "IN DEFENSE OF THE SOVEREIGNTY OF THE PANAMANIAN PEOPLE. DEATH TO THE INVADER. OUR HATRED IS RELENTLESS; OUR WAR IS TO DEATH."

THE "ZARATE WILLKA" GROUP CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY IN AUGUST 1988 FOR THE ATTACK AGAINST THEN U.S. SECRETARY OF STATE GEORGE SHULTZ AND THE KILLING OF TWO MORMON MISSIONARIES.

TODAY'S BOMB EXPLOSION DAMAGED THE SHELVES OF A BOOK STORE, THE "PEOPLE'S PERUVIAN BANK," THE STATE BANK [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED]; THE MARISCAL BALLIVIAN BUILDING, AND OTHER SHOPS, ALL OF WHICH ARE LOCATED NEAR THE U.S. EMBASSY.

AFTER THE EXPLOSION, A GROUP OF U.S. AGENTS CALLED OFF AN INVESTIGATION AT THE SCENE OF THE INCIDENT BECAUSE SOME PEOPLE SHOUTED AT THEM, "YANKEES, OUT OF PANAMA."

THE U.S. EMBASSY PRESS ATTACHE, BRUCE WARTON, SAID TODAY THAT "IT IS OBVIOUSLY A DESPICABLE ACTION THAT DOES MORE HARM TO BOLIVIANS THAN TO THE U.S. EMBASSY, BECAUSE WE HAVE SUFFERED NO DAMAGES."

TST2-MUC4-0005

SANTIAGO, 20 MAR 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [CHILEAN PRESIDENT AUGUSTO PINOCHET] [TEXT] FELLOW COUNTRYMEN: I AM ADDRESSING YOU AFTER OUR COUNTRY HAS BEGUN TO OVERCOME, WITH EFFORT AND TENACITY, THE FIRST OBSTACLES OF A SERIOUS CRISIS, THE FUTURE IMPLICATIONS AND REPERCUSSIONS OF WHICH WE STILL DO NOT KNOW. I THEREFORE WANTED TO CONVEY A MESSAGE OF HOPE AND ENCOURAGEMENT TO EVERY CHILEAN, TO SHOW THEM MY FEELINGS AT THIS TIME OF DEEP REFLECTION.

FROM THE VERY MOMENT I LEARNED ABOUT THIS TERRORIST ECONOMIC AGGRESSION, I ORDERED THE CREATION OF FOUR MINISTERIAL COMMISSIONS TO TACKLE THE PROBLEM. I ALSO SENT TWO MINISTERS TO THE UNITED STATES TO MEET WITH U.S. GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS. AFTER TIRING SESSIONS OF TALKS, THESE MINISTERS MANAGED TO OVERCOME A SUBSTANTIAL PART OF THE GRAPE PROBLEM. THE PROBLEM AFFECTING OTHER FRUITS REMAINS TO BE SOLVED.

THIS NEW ATTACK AGAINST THE CHILEAN NATION, AN ATTACK THAT DESTINY HAS PLACED IN THE NATION'S PATH OF FREEDOM, PROGRESS, AND WELL-BEING, COMPELS US TO CLOSE RANKS BEHIND THE GOVERNMENT, UNIFIED AND READY TO FIGHT -- WITH COURAGE AND HIGH SPIRIT -- THE PROBLEM THAT FACES US.

ON THIS OCCASION THE COUNTRY HAS SEEN HOW THE COUNTLESS THREATS TO BOYCOTT THE NATIONAL ECONOMY HAVE WORKED. MOST OF THE TIME SUCH THREATS HAVE BEEN PROMOTED BY CERTAIN POLITICIANS, LABOR LEADERS, OR COMMUNIST LABOR UNIONS, BOTH AT HOME AND ABROAD. THEY ARE THE ONES WHO -- DRIVEN BY PERSONAL OR IDEOLOGICAL INTEREST -- HAVE CONTINUALLY JEOPARDIZED THE STABILITY OF WORKERS, OF FAMILIES, AND OF THOSE WHOM THEY DEMAGOGICALLY CALL THEIR FELLOW COUNTRYMEN. THEY DO NOT CARE IF THEY CAUSE UNEMPLOYMENT, POVERTY, AND HUNGER TO 500,000 FELLOW CITIZENS WHO WORK IN THIS AGRICULTURAL ACTIVITY.

HOW SHAMELESSLY THEY MAKE CLAIMS AND DEMANDS, OFFERING THEIR SUPPORT AND THEIR SOLIDARITY WHEN CHILE IS SERIOUSLY THREATENED! YET WHEN THE DANGER IS OVER, THEY CHANGE THEIR ATTITUDE AND AGAIN LEVEL CHARGES AGAINST THE GOVERNMENT AND CRITICIZE ITS ACTIONS. IN DOING THAT THEY FAIL TO RECALL THAT FROM ITS VERY BEGINNING THE CHILEAN NATION HAS BEEN BUILT UPON NON-NEGOTIABLE PRINCIPLES BECAUSE THEY ARE THE ESSENCE OF THE NATIONAL SOUL.

GENTLEMEN: OUR WILL IS BASED ON OUR FEELING OF UNITY IN THE FACE OF ADVERSITY, WHETHER FROM THE ACTION OF NATURE OR FROM THE ACTION OF TREACHEROUS, DISTURBED MINDS THAT RECOGNIZE NO MORAL VALUES, FATHERLAND, OR LAW.

CHILEANS: A FEW DAYS AGO I REPORTED ON THE STEPS FORWARD IN THE INSTITUTIONALIZATION PROCESS AND ON THE PROGRESS THAT OUR COUNTRY HAS MADE IN ALL FIELDS.

THE FACT THAT CYANIDE HAS BEEN INJECTED INTO TWO EXPORTED GRAPES HAS CAUSED INCALCULABLE DAMAGE TO THE ECONOMY; IT HAS ALSO BROUGHT THE SHADOW OF ANGUISH AND UNCERTAINTY TO THOUSANDS OF HOMES OF FELLOW COUNTRYMEN WHOSE JOBS AND, CONSEQUENTLY, THEIR LEGITIMATE RIGHT TO A LIVELIHOOD HAVE BEEN DRAMATICALLY JEOPARDIZED. IT IS UNFORTUNATE THAT SOME OFFICIALS OF IMPORTING COUNTRIES, WITHOUT WEIGHING THE TRUE EFFECTS OF THIS TYPE OF MEASURE, HAVE RESTRICTED THE IMPORT OF CHILEAN FRUITS, THUS PROVOKING FEAR AND DISTRUST ON THE INTERNATIONAL CONSUMER MARKET. GENTLEMEN, WE MUST REVERSE THIS SITUATION.

WE SHOULD ONCE AGAIN ACT IN A UNITED MANNER TO RECOVER INTERNATIONAL CONFIDENCE AND OUR UNDISPUTED LEADERSHIP AS EXPORTERS. I AM SURE THAT WE WILL SUCCEED WITH A NEW JOINT EFFORT. [CONTINUED]

TST2-MUC4-0006

SAN SALVADOR, 22 APR 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] DEAR RADIO AUDIENCE: FIRST OF ALL, I WANT TO THANK YOU FOR ALLOWING ME TO TALK TO YOU TONIGHT ABOUT A VERY IMPORTANT ISSUE FOR THE FUTURE OF OUR COUNTRY. MANY TIMES YOU HAVE HEARD US MENTION THE WORD SOLIDARITY. WE HAVE ALWAYS USED IT AS A WORD THAT MEANS TO THINK ABOUT THOSE WHO SUFFER THE MOST, THOSE WHO HAVE LESS. INDEED, THOSE ARE THE PEOPLE WE MUST HELP, EVEN WITH OUR OWN SACRIFICE, AND MANY TIMES WITH A HUGE SACRIFICE BY ALL OF US. IF LOVE IS THE BOND THAT UNITES FAMILY MEMBERS, SOLIDARITY SHOULD BE THE GREAT PILLAR, THE CEMENT THAT UNITES SALVADORAN SOCIETY, SO THAT, UNITED, WE MAY FULFILL OUR DESIRE FOR PEACE, TRANQUILITY, HAPPINESS, AND WELL-BEING.

HOWEVER, TONIGHT ALLOW ME TO GIVE YOU TWO EXAMPLES OF WHAT WE CONSIDER SHOULD BE THE USE OF THE WORD SOLIDARITY AND WHAT THIS WORD MEANS IN MATTERS THAT ARE COMPLETELY DIFFERENT FROM ONE ANOTHER. A FEW WEEKS AGO THE GOVERNMENT WAS FORCED, DUE TO AN INCREASE IN OIL PRICES, TO RAISE THE PRICE OF OIL BYPRODUCTS SUCH AS GASOLINE, DIESEL, AND ALL FUELS. IN THE PAST, THE GOVERNMENT SUBSIDIZED GASOLINE. PERHAPS THE GOVERNMENT DID THIS TO MAKE PEOPLE BELIEVE THIS WOULD HAVE NOTHING BUT POSITIVE EFFECTS. HOWEVER, LET US ANALYZE FOR A WHILE THE ISSUE OF INCREASES IN THE PRICE OF FUEL. WHEN A GOVERNMENT HAS NO MONEY FOR SUBSIDIZING, THAT MEANS THE COST OF LIVING WILL GO UP. THERE IS NO DOUBT THAT PRICES WILL RISE WHEN A GOVERNMENT SPENDS MORE THAN WHAT IT HAS. HOWEVER, LET US SEE HOW THIS ASPECT, OR RATHER THE PRINCIPLE OF SOLIDARITY, APPLIES TO THE INCREASE IN FUEL PRICES, ESPECIALLY THE PRICE OF GASOLINE.

TEN PERCENT OF ALL FAMILIES IN OUR COUNTRY OWN A VEHICLE. IN GENERAL, THAT 10 PERCENT ARE THOSE WHO HAVE THE MOST; IN OTHER WORDS, THOSE WHO HAVE THE POSSIBILITY OF BUYING A CAR, A VEHICLE. IF WE SUBSIDIZED GASOLINE, WHAT WE WOULD BE DOING IS TAKING MONEY OUT OF A GOVERNMENT THAT, FOR THE TIME BEING, DOES NOT HAVE SUCH FUNDS AVAILABLE. IN ORDER TO GET SUCH FUNDS, THE GOVERNMENT WOULD HAVE TO IMPOSE NEW TAXES WHICH WOULD AFFECT ALL SALVADORANS. THEREFORE, LET US THINK WHETHER OR NOT IT IS FAIR THAT 90 PERCENT OF ALL SALVADORAN FAMILIES, WHO OWN NO VEHICLES, MUST PAY SOME KIND OF TAX IN ORDER TO BENEFIT THE OTHER 10 PERCENT WHO HAVE THE RESOURCES THAT ALLOW THEM TO BUY A VEHICLE.

WE DO NOT WANT TO APPEAR AS DEMAGOGIC OR POPULIST WITH THIS EXAMPLE. WHAT WE WANT TO SAY IS THAT THOSE OF US WHO OWN A VEHICLE, WHO ARE PART OF THE 10 PERCENT LUCKY ENOUGH TO HAVE SOMETHING AND THUS CAN BUY A VEHICLE, MUST BE IN SOLIDARITY WITH THAT 90 PERCENT WHO HAVE LITTLE AND MANY TIMES NOTHING. THEY HAVE NO VEHICLES, AND THEREFORE HAVE NO REASON TO SUFFER SO THE GASOLINE WE BUY BECOMES CHEAPER. MOREOVER, TO SOME EXTENT THE CURRENT PRICE OF GASOLINE MAKES IT POSSIBLE FOR THE DIESEL SUPPLIED TO URBAN AND INTERURBAN BUS COMPANIES TO BE BOUGHT AT A PRICE THAT WILL ALLOW BUS OWNERS TO MAINTAIN THE CURRENT BUS FARES. THIS IS SOLIDARITY, AND EVEN MORE THAN THAT. THOSE OF US WHO HAVE SOMETHING, WHO OWN A VEHICLE, PAY SOMETHING -- THROUGH THE PRICE OF THE GASOLINE WE CONSUME -- SO THAT THOSE WHO OWN NOTHING AND MUST USE THE PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION BUSES CAN DO SO WITH NO PRICE INCREASE.

THE SAME SHOULD BE THE CASE FOR THE COST OF LIQUID GAS AND PROPANE GAS, SO THAT THE PRICES OF FOOD COOKED WITH GAS IN THE MARKETPLACES ARE NOT INCREASED. THIS IS AN EXAMPLE OF HOW THOSE OF US WHO HAVE SOMETHING CAN SHOW OUR SOLIDARITY WITH THOSE WHO HAVE LITTLE OR NOTHING AT ALL.

I WOULD NOW LIKE TO TALK ABOUT AN EXAMPLE OF AN EVEN DEEPER KIND OF SOLIDARITY. I WANT TO TALK ABOUT PEACE. SALVADORAN BROTHERS, THIS IS THE TIME WHEN WE MUST SHOW OUR SOLIDARITY WITH THOSE MOTHERS WHO HAVE LOST THEIR SONS. WE MUST SHOW OUR SOLIDARITY WITH THE INNOCENT CHILDREN WHO COULD KICK A MINE AND END UP WITHOUT AN ARM OR A LEG. WE MUST SHOW OUR SOLIDARITY WITH THOSE WHO, BECAUSE OF VIOLENCE, CANNOT FIND A JOB. THAT IS WHY THIS IS THE TIME FOR ALL OF US TO MAKE AN EFFORT TO ACHIEVE PEACE.

LAST THURSDAY I TOLD YOU I FELT MORE OPTIMISTIC AFTER MEETING WITH THE POLITICAL PARTIES AND LISTENING TO THEIR DECISION TO ACCEPT THE CHALLENGE TO WORK FOR PEACE. THEY ARE DETERMINED TO REACH A CONSENSUS TO FULFILL THE ASPIRATIONS OF ALL SALVADORANS. WE ARE BEGINNING TO SENSE WHAT THE NEAR FUTURE OF EL SALVADOR COULD BE. WE ARE FEELING HAPPY AND OPTIMISTIC. HOWEVER, I REPEAT, THIS IS THE TIME WHEN WE SHOULD ALL CONTRIBUTE TO PEACE.

ANYTHING THAT MAY LEAD TO VIOLENCE, WHETHER IT IS STREET DISTURBANCES OR BOMBS, SHOULD NOT BE PERMITTED, BECAUSE IT IS NO LONGER CONCEIVABLE FOR MOTHERS, CHILDREN, AND FAMILIES TO CONTINUE TO SUFFER IN OUR COUNTRY. THE TIME HAS COME TO SHOW OUR SOLIDARITY, TO SEARCH, NOT ONLY THROUGH WORDS BUT ALSO THROUGH OUR EXAMPLES AND ACTIONS, FOR THE PEACE THAT OUR COUNTRY AND SALVADORANS DESERVE.

THEREFORE, OUR SOLIDARITY SHOULD BE THE FUNDAMENTAL TOOL FOR OUR COUNTRY'S RECONSTRUCTION. IT SHOULD BE THE FUNDAMENTAL TOOL FOR THE PHYSICAL AND SPIRITUAL RECONSTRUCTION OF ALL SALVADORANS. WE WANT ALL SALVADORANS, WITHOUT EXCEPTION, TO SUPPORT THE PEACE EFFORTS, SO THAT THOSE WHO SUFFER SO VERY MUCH FROM VIOLENCE WILL NO LONGER SUFFER.

THIS IS A FUNDAMENTAL STEP FORWARD FOR THE FREEDOM AND DEMOCRACY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. SALVADORAN BROTHERS, LET US SHOW OUR SOLIDARITY IN THIS CRUCIAL TIME IN OUR HISTORY, BECAUSE WE HAVE ALWAYS KNOWN THAT WHEN ALL SALVADORANS ACT POSITIVELY LIKE BROTHERS, WE CAN COME OUT AHEAD. THIS IS ALL FOR TONIGHT. THANK YOU ALL VERY MUCH AND MAY GOD BLESS YOU.

TST2-MUC4-0007

MEDELLIN, 12 APR 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] MEDELLIN MAYOR JUAN GOMEZ MARTINEZ ONCE MORE INSISTED TODAY ON "AN IMMEDIATE DIALOGUE" BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE COCAINE TRAFFICKERS "TO END THE WAR IN WHICH INNOCENT PEOPLE ARE BEING KILLED."

THE MAYOR REITERATED HIS POSITION WHEN HE COMMENTED ON THE ATTACK IN WHICH 20 PERSONS WERE KILLED AND APPROXIMATELY 100 WERE INJURED, WHICH WAS PERPETRATED YESTERDAY BY TERRORISTS ON THE DRUG CARTEL'S PAYROLL NEAR ITAGUI MUNICIPALITY.

THE BLAST FROM THE EXPLOSION HIT A TRUCK FULL OF POLICEMEN, WHO HAD EARLIER CARRIED OUT AN ANTI-MAFIA OPERATION IN A PEASANT VILLAGE, AS WELL AS SEVERAL PUBLIC BUSES, HOUSES, AND BUSINESSES.

A POLICE EXPERT SAID THAT THE CAR BOMB (CONTAINING 300 KG OF DYNAMITE) WAS ACTIVATED BY REMOTE CONTROL AS THE ELITE FORCE PATROL PASSED BY.

ACCORDING TO GOMEZ MARTINEZ, "THESE ACTIONS WILL ONLY CEASE WHEN (PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS') GOVERNMENT PUTS ASIDE SO MUCH PREJUDICE AND AGREES TO THE PEACE TALKS," PROPOSED BY THE SUBVERSIVES.

"THE DIALOGUE WILL TAKE PLACE SONNER OR LATER, AND IT IS BETTER TO START NOW," INSISTED THE MAYOR OF MEDELLIN, A CITY WHERE THE WORLD'S MOST POWERFUL CARTEL HAS ITS BASE OF OPERATIONS.

THE CHIEF OF THE CRIMINAL GANG, PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA, ORDERED THE ASSASSINATION OF MEDELLIN POLICEMEN IN RETALIATION FOR THE GOVERNMENT'S ACTION AGAINST THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS. TWENTY-EIGHT POLICEMEN HAVE BEEN KILLED IN THIS CITY OVER THE LAST TWO WEEKS.

ACCORDING TO SECURITY ORGANIZATIONS, YESTERDAY'S ATTACK "COULD BE ESCOBAR GAVIRIA'S RESPONSE TO THE ARREST OF ADOLFO MESA MENESES," HIS RIGHT-HAND MAN.

MESA MENESES WAS ARRESTED LAST WEEK BY THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY (DAS, SECRET POLICE), AND THE AUTHORITIES HAVE ACCUSED HIM OF ASSASSINATING -- ON ORDERS FROM THE MAFIA LEADER -- LEFTIST PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE BERNARDO JARAMILLO OSSA, AS WELL AS A CHIEF OF POLICE, A MAYOR, AND SEVERAL JOURNALISTS.

MEANWHILE, HUNDREDS OF SOLDIERS, POLICEMEN, AND DETECTIVES ARE CARRYING OUT LARGE-SCALE OPERATIONS IN THE COLOMBIAN COUNTRYSIDE AND BORDER AREAS ON THE SUSPICION THAT ESCOBAR GAVIRIA PLANS TO FLEE THE COUNTRY.

LAST NIGHT, A TELEVISION NEWSCAST SHOWED PHOTOGRAPHS OF THE "DRUG LORD" THAT HAD BEEN "RECENTLY" TAKEN BY SECURITY ORGANIZATIONS AT A COLOMBIAN BEACH ON THE PACIFIC COAST.

A POLICE DEPARTMENT SPOKESMAN CONFIRMED TODAY THAT "WE HAVE RELIABLE INFORMATION ON HIS WHEREABOUTS," ALTHOUGH HE REFRAINED FROM GIVING FURTHER DETAILS. UNOFFICIAL SOURCES SAID THAT ESCOBAR GAVIRIA "IS SOMEWHERE IN WESTERN ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT" -- OF WHICH MEDELLIN IS THE CAPITAL -- WHERE THE SEARCH OPERATIONS ARE CONCENTRATED.

COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES HAVE ALSO ASKED FOR THE COOPERATION OF BRAZIL, ECUADOR, PANAMA, PERU, AND VENEZUELA TO STOP THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS FROM ESCAPING TO THOSE COUNTRIES.

TST2-MUC4-0008

CLANDESTINE, 17 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE HAVE STARTED A NEW DAY, THE SEVENTH, AND THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] IS STILL HOLDING ITS POSITIONS. WE HAVE NOT RETREATED A SINGLE STEP. IF WE MAKE ANY MOVE, IT WILL BE TO ADVANCE TOWARD THE ENEMY BARRACKS, BECAUSE WE WILL SEIZE POWER AND EXPEL THE MILITARY DICTATORSHIP THAT HAS INSTALLED ITSELF IN OUR HOMELAND. THE FMLN MAINTAINS FOR THE 7TH DAY ITS POSITIONS IN THE DEPARTMENTAL CAPITALS. WE CONTINUE TO ADVANCE IN SAN MIGUEL; WE HAVE MADE AN IMPORTANT SEIZURE OF WEAPONS IN SAN MIGUEL.

THE SITUATION COULD NOT BE BETTER IN SAN SALVADOR. LAST NIGHT WE REPORTED THAT THE ARCH OF LIBERTY EXISTS IN THE CAPITAL; IT IS COMPRISED OF NEIGHBORHOODS AND HOUSING PROJECTS -- WHERE THE PROTAGONISTS OF THIS HISTORY ARE THE MASSES, WHICH ARE ORGANIZED FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF TRENCHES AND BARRICADES. THE PEOPLE ARE THE MOST IMPORTANT PROTAGONISTS IN THIS HISTORIC ACTION.

RADIO VENCEREMOS URGES THE PEOPLE TO MULTIPLY THEIR ORGANIZATION IN EACH NEIGHBORHOOD, RESIDENTIAL AREA, AND TOWN. POPULAR COMMITTEES MUST BE ORGANIZED; THE PEOPLE MUST ORGANIZE THEMSELVES; BUT IF THE ENEMY IS NEAR, THIS MUST BE DONE CLANDESTINELY. ALL THE GROUPS IN EACH TOWN, MEANING THE RELIGIOUS GROUPS, STUDENT ORGANIZATIONS, TEACHERS ORGANIZATIONS, AND COOPERATIVES, MUST ALL ORGANIZE, REGARDLESS OF THEIR POLITICAL BELIEFS. OUR UNITY MUST BECOME THE BEST TOOL TO EVICT, ONCE AND FOR ALL, THE MURDEROUS MILITARY DICTATORSHIP WHICH ASSASSINATES PRIESTS AND WHICH BOMBED THE CAPITAL AGAIN EARLY THIS MORNING. IT HAS AGAIN CAUSED MORE DEATHS AND WOUNDED IN SAN SALVADOR.

IT IS IMPORTANT FOR THE PEOPLE TO ORGANIZE COMMITTEES IN EACH NEIGHBORHOOD, RESIDENTIAL AREA, AND TOWN, AND THE WHOLE COMMUNITY MUST PARTICIPATE. IF THE ARMED FORCES ARE NEAR, THEN CLANDESTINE ORGANIZATION MUST BE CONDUCTED IN SMALL TOWNS, VILLAGES, AND NEIGHBORHOODS. THE PEOPLE MUST ORGANIZE THEMSELVE TO CONSPIRE AGAINST DEATH, TO CONSPIRE AGAINST THE ASSASSINS, TO CONSPIRE AGAINST POVERTY, TO CONSPIRE AGAINST HUNGER, AND TO CONSPIRE AGAINST THE BOMBINGS. IT IS NECESSARY TO ORGANIZE THE PEOPLE; IT IS NECESSARY TO ORGANIZE THE ENTIRE COUNTRY. EL SALVADOR MUST BECOME A BODY COMPRISED OF ORGANIZED CELLS -- EVERYWHERE AND IN EVERY POSSIBLE FORM -- REGARDLESS OF THE PEOPLE'S RELIGIOUS BELIEFS OR POLITICAL PARTY.

WE ISSUE AN APPEAL TO THE DECEIVED ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] RANK AND FILE, WHO VOTED BELIEVING THAT THIS GOVERNMENT WOULD REPRESENT A CHANGE FOR THE BETTER. WE ALSO ISSUE AN APPEAL TO ALL THE PATRIOTIC CITIZENS OF THE HOMELAND, URGING THEM TO STOP THE DESTRUCTION OF THE CAPITAL, TO STOP THE DESTRUCTION OF THE COUNTRY. WE URGE THEM TO UNITE AND STOP THE WAR; AND THE END OF THE WAR IS NEAR -- WITH THE PEOPLE'S VICTORY. [CONTINUED]

TST2-MUC4-0009

RIO DE JANEIRO (BRAZIL), NO DATE (O GLOBO) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] LAWYER CARLOS OLDINEY REPORTED THE GANG AND FEDERAL AGENTS VALDEMIR LOPEZ PRAZERES AND LUIS JOSE DA CONCEICAO AND DETECTIVES PAULO MASSANHYO AND CARLOS ANGEL SERRANO CASTILESSO WERE ARRESTED.

CAMBARALAMAIA'S ORGANIZATION IS JUST ONE OF THE MANY GANGS IN THE REGION THAT DEALS WITH BOLIVIAN COCAINE. ANOTHER GANG IS LED BY GERSON PALERMO, OF UMUARAMA, PARANA STATE, WHO CONTROLS THE EXCHANGE OF COCAINE TO PARAGUAY FOR STOLEN BRAZILIAN CARS. PALERMO OWNS FOUR TWIN-ENGINED CESSNA PLANES AND EMPLOYS MORE THAN 200 MEN. HE ALSO EXCHANGE CARS FOR COCAINE IN BOLIVIA. ALTHOUGH SENTENCED BY THE BRAZILIAN COURTS, PALERMO LIVES IN PEDRO JUAN CABALLERO, PARAGUAY, WHERE HE MAINTAINS BUSINESS CONTACTS WITH THE BOLIVIAN COCA PRODUCERS. PALERMO OBTAINS ETHER AND ACETONE, WHICH ARE ESSENTIAL FOR REFINING THE DRUG, FROM ARGENTINA.

THE FEDERAL POLICE BELIEVES THAT THE DRUG MIGHT BE REFINED IN MATO GROSSO DO SUL, NEAR SOME RESIDENCES IN THE DOURADOS AND CAMPO GRANDE SECTORS. PALERMO EXCHANGES THE CHEMICALS FOR TONS OF COCAINE PASTE WHICH, IN THE OPINION OF REGIONAL FEDERAL POLICE DELEGATE FRANCISCO VIANA QUEIROZ, IS ALSO PROCESSED IN PARAGUAY. VIANA QUEIROZ MAINTAINS THAT THE DRUG IS REFINED BY A GROUP OF TRAFFICKERS LED BY ARSENIO BENITEZ GONZALEZ, WHO IS KNOWN AS VILHAR AND WHO LIVES IN ASUNCION. THE FEDERAL POLICE BELIEVE THAT VILHAR -- WHO IS BELIEVED TO BE PALERMO'S PARTNER -- IS THE BRAZILIAN TRAFFICKERS' MAIN COCAINE SUPPLIER.

ACCORDING TO THE POLICE, TWO DRUG ROUTES PASS THROUGH MATO GROSSO DO SUL: THE PONTA PORA ROUTE (WHICH IS USED BY PALERMO), AND THE CORUMBA ROUTE, WHICH PASSES THROUGH THE BOLIVIAN TOWN OF PUERTO SUAREZ. MANY TRAFFICKERS COME TO THIS BOLIVIAN TOWN, MOST OF THEM SMALL SUPPLIERS WHO ONLY WANT TO EXCHANGE COCAINE FOR CARS THAT WERE STOLEN IN BRAZIL. ACCORDING TO THE AUTHORITIES, THE CORUMBA ROUTE IS MORE IMPORTANT BECAUSE IT CHANNELS THE SO-CALLED "MINI-TRAFFIC." THIS INVOLVES HUNDREDS OF PEOPLE WHO, TOGETHER, MAKE UP A SIZABLE QUANTITY OF DRUGS EVERY DAY.

THE CARS ARE THE HARD CURRENCY USED IN THESE TRANSACTIONS. MOST OF THEM ARE TAKEN TO BOLIVIA AFTER HAVING BEEN STOLEN IN SAO PAULO. THEY FOLLOW THE SAME ROUTE AS THE BOLIVIAN COCAINE, THAT IS, VIA PUERTO SUAREZ. THE MOST IMPORTANT PART OF THE TRAFFICKING, HOWEVER, IS CARRIED OUT IN PARAGUAY AND BOLIVIA. GERSON PALERMO IS RESPONSIBLE FOR PART OF IT, WHILE THE REST IS SHARED BY HUNDREDS OF BOLIVIAN TRAFFICKERS. PALERMO OBTAINS ETHER AND ACETONE FROM FORMOSA, ARGENTINA. HE TAKES THESE CHEMICALS ABOARD SMALL PLANES TO THE TOWNS OF PILAR OR ENCARNACION, IN PARAGUAY. FROM THERE, ANOTHER GROUP TAKES THE 200-LITER DRUMS ALONG THE CHACO HIGHWAY TO PUERTO GUARANI, IN BOLIVIA. BOLIVIAN TRAFFICKERS TAKE CARE OF THE REST OF THE JOURNEY TO SANTA CRUZ DE LA SIERRA. IN RETURN, PALERMO RECEIVES COCAINE PASTE WHICH IS SHIPPED TO ASUNCION AND, FROM THERE, TO PEDRO JUAN CABALLERO FOR DISTRIBUTION TO THE PROCESSING UNITS. IT IS BELIEVED THAT THE TRAFFICKERS USE SOME RANCHES NEAR PORTO MURTINHO (MATO GROSSO DE SUL), NEAR THE PARAGUAYAN TOWN OF BAHIA NEGRA, TO PROCESS LARGE QUANTITIES OF COCAINE.

NO COCAINE PASTE IS USUALLY AVAILABLE ALONG THE CORUMBA ROUTE. THE DRUG IS REFINED BECAUSE IT IS RELATIVELY EASY TO FIND ETHER AND ACETONE IN CORUMBA, WHERE THE FEDERAL POLICE HAVE FAILED TO REDUCE THE LARGE DEMAND FOR SUCH CHEMICALS IN RETAIL STORES. DOZENS OF DRUGSTORES SELL THOSE PRODUCTS BY THE LITER, AND THIS IS NOT FORBIDDEN BY LAW.

THE AUTHORITIES ESTIMATE THAT PRODUCTION IN THE PUERTO SUAREZ REGION NEARS 300 KG PER WEEK, WHICH IS TRANSPORTED BY RAILROAD, AIR, AND LAND. IN AN ATTEMPT TO EVADE THE FEDERAL POLICE, TRAFFICKERS HAVE TRIED TO TRANSPORT THE DRUG INSIDE THEIR BODIES, IN WINE DEMIJOHNS, AND EVEN IN CHILDREN'S DIAPERS. THESE TRAFFICKERS GENERALLY TRAVEL BY BUS OR BY TRAIN. OVER THE PAST 6 MONTHS THE POLICE CAUGHT DOZENS OF TRAFFICKERS USING THESE METHODS. NOW, HOWEVER, ONLY WITH THE COMPLICITY OF THE POLICE CAN CARS CARRYING BOLIVIAN COCAINE PRODUCED IN THE PUERTO SUAREZ REGION REACH CAMPO GRANDE.

TST2-MUC4-0010

NO CITY, NO DATE -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PERUVIAN PRESIDENT GARCIA BY AMAT AND AN UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [AMAT] MR. PRESIDENT, WHEN ONE SEES PERU FACING THE DIFFICULTIES IT IS EXPERIENCING NOW, THE SAME AS OUR OWN COUNTRY AND LATIN AMERICA IN GENERAL, ONE ASKS HIMSELF: WOULD A MAN, A NOVELIST LIKE MARIO VARGAS LLOSA, BE THE RIGHT MAN TO LEAD PERU?

[GARCIA] AS PRESIDENT OF ALL PERUVIANS -- AND OF VARGAS LLOSA TO EVEN IF HE DOES NOT LIKE IT -- I CANNOT PASS JUDGMENT, EITHER ETHICALLY OR INTELLECTUALLY, ON A POLITICIAN AND PERUVIAN WHO IS CONTENDING FOR THE PRESIDENCY.

[REPORTER] WHAT ARE YOU GOING TO DO AFTER YOU STEP DOWN FROM THE PRESIDENCY?

[GARCIA] WELL, I AM GOING TO BE FREE.

[AMAT] WHY DO YOU NOT COME TO COLOMBIA AND I AM SURE...

[GARCIA, INTERRUPTING] SURE, I ACCEPT YOUR INVITATION, AND I HOPE SOME COLOMBIANS WILL EXTEND IT. HOWEVER, I WANT TO TELL YOU VERY HONESTLY, THAT I AM PERHAPS BETTER AT SELLING DREAMS, IDEAS, AND DOCTRINES THAN AT ADMINISTERING A SITUATION OF PENURY, LIKE THE ONE OUR COUNTRIES ARE EXPERIENCING, AND MOST PARTICULARLY PERU, WHICH IS ONE OF THE POOREST COUNTRIES IN LATIN AMERICA. IT IS VERY DIFFICULT. FOR INSTANCE, ON A DAY WHEN THE PRICE OF RICE OR CHICKEN GOES UP, THE PEOPLE WILL NOT BELIEVE YOU, EVEN IF YOU TELL THEM THE GREATEST OF TRUTHS. ONE CAN BE PREACHING SOMETHING VERY IMPORTANT, BUT IF IT FAILED TO RAIN AND THE CITY HAD NO WATER NO ONE WILL BELIEVE OF YOU THE GREATEST OF ALL TRUTHS. THEN, WHEN ONE STOPS BEING PRESIDENT AND ADMINISTERING PENURY, ONE CAN DEVOTE ONESELF TO CONVINCING PEOPLE, TO EDUCATING. THAT IS WHAT I SHOULD DO.

[AMAT] NOW, WHY DID YOU MAKE THAT ASIDE, MAKING ME PRESIDENT OF ALL PERUVIANS, EVEN OF VARGAS LLOSA? WHETHER HE LIKES OR NOT IT HURTS HIM.

[GARCIA] BECAUSE I AM SURE THAT SOME PEOPLE WOULD NOT LIKE TO HAVE ME AS PRESIDENT. [LAUGHTER]

[AMAT] EVEN HIM, FOR INSTANCE?

[GARCIA] I DID NOT SAY SO. I DO NOT KNOW. I NEVER FALL TO THE LEVEL OF DEFINING PEOPLE OR POINTING OUT LAST NAMES. I MAKE AN OUTLINE OR DEFINE THEM IN THE NEGATIVE.

[AMAT] MR. PRESIDENT, [WORDS INDISTINCT] THIS DIALOGUE [WORDS INDISTINCT] FOR YOUR GENEROSITY AND KINDNESS. ADDRESSING OUR PEOPLE AND OUR COUNTRY, [WORDS INDISTINCT], HOW WERE THINGS TODAY AT THE SUMMIT?

[GARCIA] VERY WELL. COLOMBIANS, WHO HAVE SEEN THEIR INSTITUTION THREATENED, THEIR PRESS ABUSED, AND MANY POLITICIANS ALSO THREATENED, MUST HAVE CONFIDENCE THAT LATIN AMERICA, TOGETHER WITH THE UNITED STATES, WILL CONFRONT THE PROBLEM OF DRUG TRAFFICKING. THIS IS NOT ONLY A PROBLEM FOR COLOMBIA. IT IS OUR PROBLEM TOO, AND WE WILL TACKLE IT. THE DAY A NEWSPAPER WAS BLOWN UP IN BOGOTA I CAME TO BOGOTA BECAUSE I FELT THAT FREEDOM OF THE PRESS WAS THREATENED ON THE CONTINENT. AFTER ALL, WE ARE LATIN AMERICANS. LET COLOMBIANS HAVE CONFIDENCE.

TST2-MUC4-0011

SAN SALVADOR, 7 FEB 90 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [ALFREDO VILLAREAL] [TEXT] THE CHIEF OF THE ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF [COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE] HAS CATEGORICALLY DENIED THAT THERE ARE ANY RIFTS BETWEEN SALVADORAN ARMY OFFICERS AND U.S. MILITARY ADVISERS, AS ASSERTED BY THE WASHINGTON POST. THE NEWSPAPER STATED THAT THE ALLEGED RIFT BETWEEN THE MILITARY OFFICERS BEGAN ONCE IT WAS DISCOVERED WHO WAS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE DEATH OF SIX JESUIT PRIESTS, IN WHICH ONE COLONEL, TWO LIEUTENANTS, AND SIX SOLDIERS ARE BEING CHARGED.

COLONEL PONCE SAID THAT THE RELATIONS WITH U.S. ADVISERS -- ABOUT 52 IN THE COUNTRY -- ARE VERY CORDIAL.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] OUR RELATIONS WITH THE NORTH AMERICANS ARE NORMAL AS USUAL. THE U.S. ADVISERS HAVE HELPED US VERY MUCH IN THE PROFESSIONALIZATION OF THE ARMED FORCES, AND THEY CONTINUE WORKING WITH US.

[REPORTER] WHERE DO YOU THINK THESE WIRE REPORTS STATING THERE ARE RIFTS BETWEEN SALVADORAN MILITARY OFFICERS AND U.S. ADVISERS HAVE ORGINIATED?

[PONCE] I DO NOT KNOW; I CANNOT UNDERSTAND. THERE ARE ALWAYS THOSE WHO TRY TO BREAK THE STRATEGIC ALLIANCE BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND ARMED FORCES AND THE UNITED STATES. THIS IS A POOR COUNTRY THAT DEPENDS A GREAT DEAL ON U.S. ECONOMIC AND MILITARY AID.

[REPORTER] FOLLOWING THE MURDER OF THE JESUITS, WHAT ARE RELATIONS LIKE BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN MILITARY AND THE GRINGO ADVISERS?

[PONCE] AS USUAL, THESE RELATIONS ARE VERY CORDIAL, AND THEY CONTINUE TO WORK WITH US. AS YOU CAN SEE, TWO ADVISERS ARE HERE WITH ME NOW AT THE TABLE PRESIDING OVER THE EVENT. THE SAME HAS BEEN THE CASE WITH ALL THE UNITS IN THE COUNTRY'S INTERIOR. I FAIL TO SEE ANY DIFFERENCE IN RELATIONS BEFORE AND AFTERWARD. [END RECORDING]

THE MILITARY CHIEF REPEATED THE NEED TO MAINTAIN THE STATE OF EMERGENCY, NOT ONLY DUE TO THE GUERRILLA ATTACKS, BUT ALSO TO KEEP CONTROL OVER THE ORGANIZATION FRONTS JUST PRIOR TO AN EXPECTED WAVE OF PROTESTS ON THE LATEST GOVERNMENT ECONOMY MEASURES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] WE MUST START THINKING WHAT MAY HAPPEN TO DOMESTIC ORDER IN THE FACE OF THE ECONOMIC MEASURES THAT HAVE BEEN ISSUED OR ARE PLANNED. WE MUST THINK WHAT THE REACTION OF THE PEOPLE OR THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] ORGANIZATION FRONTS WILL BE, AS THEY ALWAYS USE ANY EXCUSE TO DISRUPT DOMESTIC ORDER. IT WOULD BE GOOD TO LOOK INTO WHAT IS NEEDED TO MAINTAIN DOMESTIC ORDER IN THE COUNTRY. [END RECORDING]

THE HIGH-RANKING MILITARY OFFICER GAVE THESE STATEMENTS AT THE CEREMONY TO TURN OVER COMMAND OF THE CAPTAIN GENERAL GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY. THE NEW COMMANDER IS COLONEL RICARDO ALFONSO CASANOVA SANDOVAL, WHO REPLACES COLONEL GUILLERMO ALFREDO BENAVIDES MORENO, REMOVED FROM HIS POST AFTER BEING ACCUSED OF ORDERING THE MURDER OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS.

MEANWHILE, COLONEL HECTOR HERIBERTO HERNANDEZ HAS BEEN APPOINTED COMMANDER OF THE 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADE BASED IN USULUTAN, AND IN LA UNION DEPARTMENT THE CHANGE OF COMMAND CEREMONIES OF THE ARMED FORCES MILITARY TRAINING CENTER HAVE TAKEN PLACE, WHERE COLONEL FRANCISCO ARTURO LOPEZ WILL BE IN COMMAND REPLACING COLONEL CARLOS ALFREDO RIVAS, WHO HAS BEEN TRANSFERRED TO THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF.

TST2-MUC4-0013

QUITO, 30 APR 90 (RADIO QUITO) -- [STATEMENT] [COMMUNICATIONS SECRETARY PEDRO SAAD] [TEXT] THIS AFTERNOON, ON THE BERMEJA RIVER, SUCUMBIOS PROVINCE, IN NORTHEASTERN ECUADOR, AT APPROXIMATELY ONE AND A HALF KM FROM THE COLOMBIAN BORDER, A SMALL ECUADORAN FLAGSHIP WORKING WITH THE IMANCO MINING COMPANY, WAS INTERCEPTED BY A COLOMBIAN VESSEL WHICH FIRED AUTOMATIC WEAPONS.

THE FOLLOWING PEOPLE WERE ABOARD THE ECUADORAN FLAGSHIP: U.S. CITIZEN SCOTT HEYNDAL, ECUADOREANS LUIS ANTONIO MENESES BENAVIDES AND EDWIN RODRIGO TENEDA PARRENO, AND COLOMBIAN PILOT JULIO TORRES. MR. TORRES WAS KILLED AND MR. MENESES WAS WOUNDED.

THE ATTACKERS, WHO WORE FIELD UNIFORMS OF THE COLOMBIAN MILITARY, BOARDED THE ECUADORAN VESSEL, AND, AFTER NOTICING THAT MR. MENESES WAS WOUNDED, GAVE HIM 100,000 COLOMBIAN PESOS AND THEN LEFT HIM AND MR. TORRES' BODY. THE ATTACKERS RETURNED TO COLOMBIA TAKING HEYNDAL AND TENEDA WITH THEM. THEY CROSSED THE BORDER AND SAILED UPRIVER FOR ABOUT TWO AND A HALF HOURS ON THE RUMIYACU RIVER.

THE ATTACKERS SPENT THE EVENING AT A CAMP NEAR THE RIVER AND FORCED MR. HEYNDAL TO WRITE LETTERS TO HIS BOSS AT THE MINING PROJECT, MR. JEFF SINO, ALSO A U.S. CITIZEN, AND TO HIS WIFE. THOSE LETTERS WERE GIVEN TO MR. TENEDA, WHO RECEIVED 20,000 COLOMBIAN PESOS. HE WAS THEN ORDERED TO RETURN TO ECUADOR AND GIVEN INSTRUCTIONS FOR DELIVERING THE LETTERS.

TST2-MUC4-0014

CLANDESTINE, 14 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] FIGHTING RAGED ALL DAY LONG IN THE AREA AROUND SAN TERESA HOSPITAL, IN ZACATELUCA, LA PAZ DEPARTMENT. A REPORT SAYS THAT A DMIFA ARMED FORCES ENGINEERS' MILITARY DETACHMENT UNIT WAS AT SANTA TERESA HOSPITAL, AND THAT THE ENTIRE UNIT WAS WIPED OUT. THE SOLDIERS HAD A COMMUNICATIONS RELAY STATION IN THE BUILDING. AS A RESULT OF THE ATTACK, THERE WERE 20 CASUALTIES. AMONG THE CASUALTIES IS A LIEUTENANT WHO WAS THE UNIT CHIEF, AND TWO SERGEANTS. THE COMMUNICATIONS EQUIPMENT WAS TOTALLY DESTROYED.

THE SITUATION IS NOT AS THE FASCIST CRISTIANI REPORTED IT TO BE. HE SAID THERE WAS ONLY ONE SOLDIER AT THE HOSPITAL RECEIVING MEDICAL TREATMENT. THAT IS TOTALLY FALSE. THE BUILDING HOUSED A GARRISON NOT A HOSPITAL, BECAUSE A DMIFA UNIT AND A COMMUNICATIONS RELAY CENTER WERE THERE. IT WAS A GARRISON.

WE ARE GOING TO CORRECT OUR REPORT ON THE RESULTS OF THE ATTACK ON THE DMIFA UNIT: 20 SOLDIERS WERE KILLED AND 10 WERE WOUNDED. IN ALL, THERE WERE 30 CASUALTIES, INCLUDING TWO SERGEANTS AND THE UNIT CHIEF. WE REPEAT: IN AN IMPRESSIVE ATTACK ON A MILITARY POSITION AT SANTA TERESA HOSPITAL--THE BUILDING WAS NO LONGER A HOSPITAL BUT AN ARMY COMMUNICATIONS CENTER--OUR FIGTHTERS ANNIHILATED AND DESTROYED THAT POSITION. THE ARMY SUSTAINED 20 KILLED AND 10 WOUNDED. THE COMMUNICATIONS RELAY STATION WAS TOTALLY DESTROYED.

TST2-MUC4-0016

SAN SALVADOR, 3 MAY 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [CRISTIANI] ALTHOUGH IT ORGANICALLY DEPENDS ON THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH, THE COMMISSION IS AN OFFICIAL JUSTICE ORGANIZATION AND THE JUDGE CAN INSTRUCT IT OR REQUEST THAT IT INVESTIGATE X, Y, OR Z, IN ADDITION TO WHAT IT SUBMITTED WHEN THE CASE WAS PASSED OVER TO THE JUDGE.

[MODERATOR] PABLO GUILLERMO [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] MR. PRESIDENT, THE NEWSPAPER LA JORNADA OF MEXICO STATED YESTERDAY THAT COLONEL ORLANDO ZEPEDA HAD LEFT THE COUNTRY THIS WEEKEND WITH ALL HIS FAMILY AND WITH A CONSIDERABLE AMOUNT OF LUGGAGE, WHICH WOULD INDICATE THAT HE DID NOT GO ON A MERE VACATION. I WOULD LIKE TO KNOW THE OFFICIAL VERSION OF THIS. [LAUGHTER]

[CRISTIANI] YOU SAY HE LEFT WHEN?

[REPORTER] YESTERDAY.

[CRISTIANI] WELL, ONLY IF HE LEFT VERY HURRIEDLY AFTER MIDDAY. I WAS WITH HIM HERE YESTERDAY DISCUSSING OTHER THINGS, AS WELL AS MILITARY MATTERS WITH THE DEFENSE MINISTER AND DEPUTY MINISTERS. HE WAS PRESENT. UNLESS HE MAY HAVE LEFT. I DOUBT IT VERY MUCH, BECAUSE I HAD A MEETING WITH THEM TO SEE THE ORDER OF THE MONTH ON SATURDAY AND HE WAS PRESENT. PARDON ME, THAT WAS TUESDAY WHEN WE HAD THE ORDER FOR THE END OF THE MONTH. I UNDERSTAND HE WAS PRESENT AT THE COMMANDERS MEETING. IF HE LEFT LAST WEEKEND, IT MUST HAVE BEEN FOR THE WEEKEND AND HE RETURNED ON MONDAY.

[MODERATOR] MARIA CORTINA, NOTIMEX.

[REPORTER] MR. PRESIDENT, IN WHAT WAY WOULD A CUT IN MILITARY AID AFFECT THE PEACE PROCESS?

[CRISTIANI] WE ARE CURRENTLY SEEING OPPOSITE SIGNS FROM THE FMLN IN TERMS OF WANTING TO TRULY PUT AN END TO VIOLENCE. A SIGN OF THIS WAS THE NIGHT OF 1 MAY WHEN THE ATTACKS WERE CARRIED OUT. THIS WOULD INDICATE THAT, ALTHOUGH NOT ALL THE FMLN COMMAND, THAT IS THE FIVE GROUPS, SOME GROUPS SEEM TO RESIST A POLITICAL SOLUTION AND FAVOR A MILITARY SOLUTION, AS THEY HAVE INSISTED ON PURSUING FOR 10 YEARS. THOSE GROUPS COULD VIEW A CUT IN MILITARY AID AS A SIGN OF WEAKENING OF THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES, AND THAT CONSEQUENTLY THEY WOULD HAVE A BETTER CHANCE OF BEING SUCCESSFUL FOLLOWING THE MILITARY PATH. THAT COULD INCREASE THE POTENTIAL OF A MILITARY SOLUTION IN THE MINDS OF SOME. THIS COULD REDUCE THE POTENTIAL OF SERIOUSLY CONSIDERING A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT.

[MODERATOR] RAUL MONGE, CADENA RADIO CENTRO.

[REPORTER] MR. PRESIDENT, HOW DO YOU VIEW THE GUERRILLAS' MORALE AT THIS MOMENT?

[CRISTIANI] WELL, I OBVIOUSLY CANNOT BUT BELIEVE THAT THE MORALE OF THE GUERRILLAS AFTER THE OFFENSIVE MUST HAVE DROPPED CONSIDERBLY. THIS IS ESPECIALLY SO SINCE THERE WAS A LARGE SACRIFICE ON THEIR PART IN THE FORM OF CASUALTIES AND THE FACT THAT THE OFFENSIVE DID NOT REPRESENT A SUCCESS, DESPITE THEIR CLAIM THAT IT WAS ONLY A SHOW OF FORCE, WHICH IS A LOT OF MALARKEY. ALL THE PRIOR DOCUMENTS INDICATED THAT THIS WAS A LARGE-SCALE OPERATION TO THE HILT SEEKING TO OVERTHROW THE GOVERNMENT AND TO CROWN A MILITARY VICTORY. WHAT I BELIEVE WAS OF EVEN GREATER IMPACT WAS THAT THEY REALIZED THAT THE PEOPLE OF EL SALVADOR DO NOT SUPPORT THEM AND DO NOT SUPPORT THE PATH OF VIOLENCE. IN THAT SENSE, THEIR HOPES OF A POPULAR INSURRECTION WERE SHATTERED. ON THE CONTRARY, THE PEOPLE DID NOT SUPPORT THE FMLN AND INSTEAD TURNED THEIR BACKS ON THEM AND SHOWED THAT THEY DO NOT SUPPORT VIOLENCE. THIS MUST HAVE CAUSED AN IMPACT ON THE FMLN AND ITS MEMBERS. I RECENTLY READ IN A VENEZUELAN NEWSPAPER STATEMENTS BY A COMMANDER, WHOSE PSEUDONYM IS GUSTAVO, WHO SAID THAT THEY WERE TIRED OF FOLLOWING THE PATH OF VIOLENCE AND THAT A SOLUTION HAD TO BE FOUND. THIS DEMONSTRATES THAT SOME OF THEIR RANKS ARE GETTING TIRED OF THE MILITARY PATH. THESE ARE INDICATIONS OF WHAT COULD BE. WHAT I WANT TO CLEAR UP ONCE AND FOR ALL IS THAT WE DO NOT REACT TO WHETHER OR NOT THE FMLN FEELS STRONG OR FEELS WEAK. WE KNOW THAT 100 TERRORISTS IN A COUNTRY CAN CAUSE DESTRUCTION AND DEATH AND THAT IS WHAT WE ARE TRYING TO AVOID, ALTHOUGH 100 TERRORISTS ARE NOT A FORCE THAT WILL DESTABILIZE A GOVERNMENT. HOWEVER, THE DAMAGE THAT THEY CAUSE IS SUCH THAT WE DO NOT WANT IT TO CONTINUE. [CONTINUED]

TST2-MUC4-0018

CLANDESTINE, 12 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE ARE RECEIVING A REPORT RIGHT NOW ON THE SITUATION IN SAN SALVADOR. THE REPORT SAYS THAT SAN SALVADOR NEIGHBORHOODS AND RESIDENTIAL AREAS ARE STILL UNDER THE CONTROL OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]. ARMED FORCES OFFICIAL SOURCES HAVE ADMITTED THAT SOME AREAS OF SAN SALVADOR ARE CONTROLLED BY THE FMLN. THE REPORT ADDS THAT AS OF 2140 ON 12 NOVEMBER, THERE WAS STILL TENSION IN THE CITY.

SOME SPORADIC SHOOTING WAS STILL HEARD, AND THE SITUATION IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE CAPITAL CITY INDICATED THAT OUR COMRADES ARE MAINTAINING THEIR POSITIONS, THEY ARE CARRYING OUT MILITARY ENGINEERING TASKS, OPENING TRENCHES, AND SETTING UP BARRICADES WITH THE COOPERATION OF THE SAN SALVADOR PEOPLE.

PRESS AGENCY REPORTS NOTE THAT THERE IS GREAT TENSION IN THE CAPITAL CITY, AND APPARENTLY THEY ARE EXPECTING [CHANGES THOUGHT] HERE IS A NEWS AGENCY REPORT WHICH SAYS THAT EARLY THIS MORNING, LESS SHOOTING WAS HEARD BECAUSE APPARENTLY EACH SIDE HAD CONSOLIDATED THEIR POSITION. THAT IS WHAT SOME PRESS AGENCIES ARE REPORTING.

WE HAVE ALSO OBSERVED THAT THE ARMED FORCES HAVE ADMITTED THAT SOME AREAS IN THE CAPITAL CITY ARE CONTROLLED BY THE FMLN. THERE ARE MANY VEHICLES SCATTERED ALL OVER THE STREETS OF SAN SALVADOR. THAT IS THE REPORT WE HAVE RECEIVED FROM SAN SALVADOR, WHERE OUR FIGHTERS IN ZACAMIL AND OTHER NEIGHBORHOODS AND RESIDENTIAL AREAS IN THE CAPITAL CITY ARE NOW RECEIVING THE SUPPORT OF THE PEOPLE WHO ARE FORTIFYING THEMSELVES IN NEIGHBORHOODS.

WE CALL ON THE SAN SALVADORAN YOUTHS TO GO OUT TONIGHT TO COOPERATE WITH THE FMLN FIGHTERS. MAKE THE ASSASSINS OF MSGR ROMERO PAY DEARLY FOR EVERY STEP THEY TAKE AGAINST THE PEOPLE IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS IN SAN SALVADOR CITY. IT HAS BEEN 24, 25, NEARLY 26 HOURS SINCE THE FMLN FIGHTERS ESTABLISHED THEIR POSITIONS IN SAN SALVADOR IN VIEW OF THE REGIME'S INCOMPETENCE. THE REGIME HAS CLEARLY SAID THAT IT IS INCAPABLE OF CONTROLLING THE SITUATION, AS IT HAS HAD TO DECREE A STATE OF SIEGE THAT BEGAN ON THE EVENING OF 12 NOVEMBER IN SAN SALVADOR.

ANOTHER EVIDENCE OF THE GOVERNMENT'S WEAKNESS IS THE GAG PLACED ON THE MEDIA. THE GOVERNMENT HAS NOT ALLOWED THE MEDIA TO BROADCAST ITS NEWSCASTS. WHY DOESN'T THE GOVERNMENT WANT THE PEOPLE TO LISTEN TO NEWSCASTS IN EL SALVADOR? WHAT IS THE CRISTIANI REGIME HIDING? THIS IS A QUESTION THAT THE PEOPLE ARE ASKING; THEY WANT TO KNOW THE ANSWER. THE GOVERNMENT IS AFRAID, IT DOES NOT WANT TO INFORM THE PEOPLE ABOUT THE DEVELOPMENTS OR THE SCOPE OF THE ACTIONS CARRIED OUT BY THE FMLN THROUGHOUT THE NATIONAL TERRITORY.

COMRADE FIGHTERS: WE HAVE ALREADY TOLD YOU; THIS IS IN THE BAG. YOUR COURAGE AND DETERMINATION TO WIN HAS MADE IT POSSIBLE TO CARRY OUT THE FMLN PLAN AS OUR COMMUNIQUE ISSUED BY THE GENERAL COMMAND HAS SAID.

COMRADES: KEEP IT UP, KEEP AN OPEN EYE, KEEP UP THE HIGH MORALE AS YOU HAVE DONE UP TO NOW, SEEK CONTACT WITH THE PEOPLE, RECEIVE THEIR COOPERATION IN THE FORTIFICATIONS THAT ARE BEING MADE THROUGHOUT SAN SALVADOR. LET'S GO TO THE TOP AND THAT'S IT.

TST2-MUC4-0019

SAN SALVADOR, 26 JUN 89 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [INTERVIEW WITH SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY MILTON GRIMALDI] [TEXT] PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI SAID TODAY THAT DESPITE THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT'S [FMLN] TERRORIST ATTACKS AGAINST SALVADORANS, HIS GOVERNMENT IS WILLING TO HOLD TALKS WITH THE REBELS. HE SAID THAT HIS ADMINISTRATION IS CONTINUING ITS EFFORTS TO FORM A COMMISSION FOR A DIALOGUE WITH THE REBELS AND THAT HE IS NOW AWAITING WORD FROM TWO PEOPLE WHOM HE HAS CHOSEN TO SERVE ON THE COMMISSION. THE CATHOLIC CHURCH WILL NOT BE REPRESENTED ON THE COMMISSION BECAUSE THE COMMISSION IS COMPLETELY POLITICAL IN NATURE. PRESIDENT CRISTIANI CONDEMNED THE MURDER OF NATIONAL FIRE DEPARTMENT DIRECTOR COLONEL ROBERTO ARMANDO RIVERA ESCOBAR, WHO WAS KILLED IN A MACHINEGUN ATTACK THIS MORNING. PRESIDENT CRISTIANI ATTRIBUTED RIVERA'S MURDER TO THE FMLN:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] IT IS CLEAR THAT THE FMLN DOES NOT WANT PEACE BUT INSTEAD WANTS TO CONTINUE THE VIOLENCE. THE FMLN COMMITTED THIS CRIME. I BELIEVE THAT A TREACHEROUS CRIME SUCH AS THIS ONE CANNOT BE CALLED ANYTHING BUT A COWARDLY ACT. WE WILL, OF COURSE, INVESTIGATE THE CRIME. I REPEAT, HOWEVER, THAT ALL THE EVIDENCE WE HAVE GATHERED ON THE FMLN'S PLANS INDICATE THAT IT WAS RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS ACTION.

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] WHAT ARE YOU DOING TO PREPARE THE COMMISSION THAT IS TO HOLD TALKS [WORDS INDISTINCT]?

[CRISTIANI] THE TERRORISTS WILL NOT OF COURSE BE SUCCESSFUL WITH ACTIONS OF THIS KIND AND WILL NOT PROVOKE US INTO VIOLENT ACTION. THEY SHOULD UNDERSTAND BY NOW THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS SEARCHING FOR PEACE AND WANTS TO ACHIEVE PEACE WITHIN EL SALVADOR'S LEGAL FRAMEWORK AND BY APPLYING THE LAW. THE FMLN REBELS SHOULD UNDERSTAND THAT THEIR TERRORIST ACTIONS WILL NOT LEAD US TO TAKE RASH ACTIONS; IT IS USELESS FOR THEM TO CONTINUE TO ACT IN THIS WAY.

WE ARE CONTINUING OUR WORK ON SETTING UP THE COMMISSION. TODAY WE WILL SPEAK WITH TWO PEOPLE WHO HAVE STILL NOT TOLD US IF THEY WILL ACCEPT MY INVITATION TO BE COMMISSION MEMBERS. THE NAMES OF THE COMMISSION MEMBERS WILL BE RELEASED TO THE PUBLIC ONCE THE COMMISSION IS FULLY FORMED.

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE CATHOLIC CHURCH'S ROLE IN THIS COMMISSION?

[CRISTIANI] [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE CATHOLIC CHURCH WILL NOT BE REPRESENTED IN THIS COMMISSION BECAUSE IT IS A POLITICAL COMMISSION AND NOT ONE IN WHICH THE CHURCH CAN EFFECTIVELY PARTICIPATE. THE CHURCH HAS ALWAYS WORKED FOR PEACE AND HAS MADE ALL POSSIBLE EFFORTS TO FIND PEACE FOR THE COUNTRY THE CHURCH WILL CONTINUE TO WORK TOWARD THIS GOAL. HOWEVER, I BELIEVE THAT THE CHURCH HAS A DIFFERENT ROLE TO PLAY IN THE SEARCH FOR PEACE, AND THAT ROLE IS NOT SERVING ON THE POLITICAL COMMISSION.

[REPORTER] WHAT WOULD YOU SAY IS THE BIGGEST OBSTACLE YOU HAVE ENCOUNTERED IN THE MONTH THAT YOU HAVE SERVED AS PRESIDENT?

[CRISTIANI] I BELIEVE THAT THE BIGGEST OBSTACLE HAS BEEN OUR INABILITY TO LAUNCH OUR GOVERNMENT PROGRAM, WHICH IS DUE TO THE STATE OF AFFAIRS EXISTING IN THE FORMER ADMINISTRATION WHEN WE TOOK OVER. WE HAVE REPEATEDLY OBSERVED THIS STATE OF AFFAIRS IN THE MAJORITY OF GOVERNMENT [WORD INDISTINCT]. THROUGHOUT GOVERNMENT OFFICES, DISORDER WAS RAMPANT, AND, IN MANY CASES, WE HAVE OBSERVED THAT GOVERNMENT OFFICES WERE MANAGED IRRESPONSIBLY. MOREOVER, THE NATION'S PUBLIC FINANCES HAVE GREATLY DETERIORATED. WE HAVE INHERITED A COUNTRY IN VERY BAD FINANCIAL SHAPE, AND, I BELIEVE, THIS HAS DELAYED THE LAUNCHING OF OUR GOVERNMENT PROGRAM. [END RECORDING]

CRISTIANI, REFERRING TO COSTA RICAN PRESIDENT OSCAR ARIAS' OFFER TO HOLD A DIALOGUE WITH THE REBELS IN COSTA RICAN TERRITORY, SAID THAT THE OFFER WAS A GREAT CONTRIBUTION TOWARD CONVINCING THE FMLN TO STOP MURDERING DEFENSELESS CITIZENS.

TST2-MUC4-0022

BOGOTA, 19 MAY 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] OUT OF THE TEN CANDIDATES RUNNING FOR THE COLOMBIAN PRESIDENCY, THE FOUR WHO HAVE THE BEST CHANCES OF WINNING HAVE INSERTED IN THEIR GOVERNMENT PLATFORMS SOLUTIONS TO THE CRISIS OF VIOLENCE THAT HAS TAKEN HOLD OF THE COUNTRY, CAUSED MAINLY BY THE NARCOTRAFFICKING MAFIAS AND THE GUERRILLA GROUPS.

FOR LIBERAL CESAR GAVIRIA TRUJILLO, "NONVIOLENT SOLUTIONS" MUST BE FOUND THROUGH A CONDITIONED DIALOGUE WITH THE GUERRILLAS AND BY STRENGTHENING JUSTICE TO CONFRONT THE NARCOTRAFFICKERS "BECAUSE EXTRADITION CANNOT BE THE ONLY PATH TO FIGHT THIS CRIME."

GAVIRIA, 43, WHO ACCORDING TO THE POLLS IS THE FAVORITE TO SUCCEED VIRGILIO BARCO AS PRESIDENT AFTER THE 27 MAY ELECTIONS, HAS MADE THE PROBLEMS OF THE GUERRILLAS AND DRUG MAFIAS THE TWO MAIN ISSUES IN HIS GOVERNMENT PLATFORM.

REGARDING THE ARMED REBELS, HE INSISTS THAT NONVIOLENT SOLUTIONS MUST BE FOUND AND PROMISES TO "TAKE INTO CONSIDERATION" THE MERITS OF WHAT HAS BEEN TESTED UP TO NOW.

"THE DIALOGUE WITH THE ARMED REBELS IS A CONCESSION THAT HAS BEEN MADE TO THEM, AND FOR THIS REASON SOCIETY HAS EVERY RIGHT TO ESTABLISH CONDITIONS," GAVIRIA STATED. "THUS," HE ADDED, "THE DIALOGUE WILL PREVENT THE GUERRILLAS FROM HAVING A POLITICAL PROTAGONIST ROLE AND WILL AVERT THE JUSTIFICATION OF VIOLENCE."

SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE RODRIGO LLOREDA CAICEDO, 47, INSISTS THAT "THE SURRENDER OF THE MAFIA LORDS MUST BE ACHIEVED" AND THAT THIS "SHOULD INCLUDE PENALTIES FOR THE CRIMES COMMITTED, ECONOMIC COMPENSATION, AND THE CERTAINTY THAT COLOMBIA WILL NOT CONTINUE TO LEND ITSELF TO PRODUCE AND EXPORT DRUGS."

LLOREDA CAICEDO IS OPPOSED TO THE EXTRADITION OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS TO THE UNITED STATES, AND HE OFFERS TO "STRENGTHEN JUSTICE" AND TO CHANGE PROCEDURES SO AS TO SURROUND JUDGES WITH GUARANTEES, ALL WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF A CONSTITUTIONAL REFORM THROUGH A PLEBISCITE TO CONVOKE A NATIONAL CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY.

FOR THE ARMED REBELS, HE OFFERS "A 12-MONTH TERM FOR THEM TO REJOIN CIVILIAN LIFE" AND THE DRAFTING OF "MECHANISMS" FOR THEIR DISBANDING, SUCH AS THE "NATIONAL CIRCUMSCRIPTION" THAT WILL FACILITATE THEIR PARTICIPATION IN THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIC AND POLITICAL LIFE.

LLOREDA CAICEDO, FOREIGN MINISTER DURING BELISARIO BETANCUR'S ADMINISTRATION AND ONE OF THE PROPONENTS OF THE CONTADORA GROUP TO ATTAIN PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA, SAID THAT AN EFFORT MUST BE MADE TO "RECOVER THE MONOPOLY OF THE PUBLIC FORCE AND CONSOLIDATE ITS SOVEREIGN PRESENCE."

ALVARO GOMEZ HURTADO, 71, A "DISSIDENT" CONSERVATIVE, MAINTAINS THAT WITHOUT THE STRENGTHENING OF MORALS AND THE LAW -- "THE ROOT OF OUR ILLS" -- COEXISTENCE AND PROGRESS WILL NOT BE POSSIBLE. HE PLEDGES TO RESCUE THOSE TWO VALUES.

GOMEZ HURTADO PRESENTED TO COLOMBIAN VOTERS A FIVE-POINT "AGREEMENT ON BASIC ISSUES," INCLUDING LAW AND MORALS, JUSTICE, ECONOMIC PLANNING, AND ECOLOGY, AS HIS GOVERNMENT PLATFORM IF HE IS ELECTED PRESIDENT ON 27 MAY.

ANTONIO NAVARRO WOLFF, THE M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT] PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE, WHO REPLACED THE ASSASSINATED CARLOS PIZARRO, BELIEVES THAT SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC EQUILIBRIUM ARE "BASIC" TO REACHING PEACE.

NAVARRO WOLFF, 41, HAS REITERATED THAT HE DOES NOT AGREE WITH THE EXTRADITION OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS, AND HE ALSO CONDEMNED THE CHAIN OF ATTACKS PERPETRATED BY DRUG TERRORISTS IN THE COUNTRY OVER THE PAST FEW MONTHS.

REGARDING THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS, HOWEVER, HE SAID THAT THEY REQUIRE "MORE SERIOUS TREATMENT." THEREFORE, IT IS BETTER TO HAVE "A POOR DIALOGUE RATHER THAN A GOOD WAR," AND IF THAT DIALOGUE PRODUCES GOOD RESULTS "WE MUST HOLD ON TO IT," HE SAID.

THE FOUR CANDIDATES AGREE ON REFORMING THE CONGRESS OF THE REPUBLIC AND THE CONSTITUTION BY CONVOKING A NATIONAL CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY. THEY ALSO SHARE OPINIONS ON THE COUNTRY'S ECONOMIC OPENING TOWARD INTERNATIONAL MARKETS, ACCESS TO FOREIGN INVESTMENT, AND PROMOTION OF AN "AGRO-INDUSTRIAL REVOLUTION" WHICH WILL GUARANTEE A REDUCTION OR STABILIZATION OF THE RATE OF INFLATION.

TST2-MUC4-0024

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH FMLN COMMANDER GONZALEZ BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] COMMANDER, WHAT CAN THE POPULAR MOVEMENT, THE LABOR UNIONS, AND THE HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS DO IN THE FACE OF A GOVERNMENT AND A MILITARY LEADERSHIP THAT CARRY OUT THIS TYPE OF ATTACK, THIS TYPE OF MASSACRE, IN A LEGAL FRAMEWORK THAT OFFERS NO GUARANTEE TO THE POPULAR MOVEMENT? WHAT CAN THE POPULAR MOVEMENT DO?

[GONZALEZ] I BELIEVE THAT THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT IS CLOSING ALL THE ROADS TO A PEACEFUL SOLUTION OF THIS CONFLICT. THROUGH REPRESSION IT IS CLOSING OFF THE POSSIBILITY OF LABOR UNIONS AND ASSOCIATIONS RESOLVING THEIR PROBLEMS PEACEFULLY. THE GOVERNMENT IS CLOSING OFF THE POSSIBILITY OF NEGOTIATIONS. THE ARMY AND THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT ARE OPPOSED TO TRUE NEGOTIATIONS. THE PEOPLE HAVE NO ALTERNATIVE. IN EL SALVADOR THERE IS A LATENT PATH, THE PATH OF ARMED ACTIONS. AT THIS MOMENT, AS THIS GOVERNMENT INCREASES REPRESSION, ARMED ACTIONS BECOME INCREASINGLY LEGITIMATE, ARMED ACTIONS TO FIND SOLUTIONS TO THE CONFLICT, ARMED ACTIONS TO STOP THE REPRESSION BY THE REGIME.

THE WORKERS AND THEIR ASSOCIATIONS AND LABOR UNIONS ARE ENTITLED TO DEFEND THEMSELVES AND THEIR LABOR BENEFITS. DEFENSE IS LEGITIMATE. IT IS LEGITIMATE FOR THE WORKERS TO DECIDE TO DEFEND THEMSELVES THE ARMED WAY, THROUGH VIOLENCE. IT IS THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT, PONCE, AND THE HIGH COMMAND WHO ARE LEAVING THE WORKERS NO ALTERNATIVE.

[REPORTER] TO CONCLUDE, COMMANDER: IN RECENT HOURS THERE HAVE BEEN ATTACKS IN THE CAPITAL, INCLUDING BOMB ATTACKS ON THE RESIDENCES OF DEMOCRATIC LEADERS SUCH AS RUBEN ZAMORA AND ARONETE DIAZ, AN ATTACK ON THE RESIDENCE OF COLONEL CARRANZA, AND AN ATTACK ON A RELATIVE OF COLONEL LOPEZ HUILA, AMONG OTHERS. THE ARMED FORCES AND THE GOVERNMENT HAVE PUBLICLY SAID THAT THE FMLN IS RESPONSIBLE FOR THESE ATTACKS.

[GONZALEZ] OUR ARMED ACTIONS ARE HIGHLY JUST AND HAVE POLITICAL MOTIVATIONS. OUR OBJECTIVES ARE STRICTLY MILITARY. ALL OUR GUERRILLA UNITS FUNCTION ACCORDING TO THIS PRINCIPLE, BE IT IN THE RURAL AREAS OR IN THE CITIES WHERE OUR URBAN COMMANDOS OPERATE.

THE ATTACK ON THE ARMED FORCES STAFF INSTALLATIONS AND OTHER OPERATIONS AGAINST MILITARY TARGETS ARE OUR RESPONSIBILITY. THE FMLN'S POLICY IS NOT TO ATTACK RELATIVES OF MILITARY MEN OR POLITICIANS. THE HIGH COMMAND HAS BEEN TRYING TO CONFUSE THE PEOPLE HERE AND ABROAD. WHAT IS ITS OBJECTIVE? TO COVER UP ITS REPRESSIVE POLICY. IT IS ESCALATING ITS ACTIONS. IT HAS GONE FROM THE SELECTIVE CAPTURE AND MURDER OF LEADERS TO MASS ARRESTS, AND FROM MASS ARRESTS IT HAS MOVED INTO GENOCIDE AND INDISCRIMINATE ATTACKS.

IT IS CLEAR THAT ITS OBJECTIVE IS THE SOCIAL ORGANIZATIONS. THE GOVERNMENT SAID IT IN SAN JOSE. IT IS EVIDENT THAT THE HIGH COMMAND IS TRYING TO CREATE CONFUSION, BUT THE PEOPLE ABROAD AND WE KNOW THAT OUR ACTIONS ARE AIMED AT MILITARY OBJECTIVES.

TST2-MUC4-0026

BOGOTA, 26 APR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE EXTRADITABLES, THE ARMED BRANCH OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, DENIED TODAY IN A TELEPHONE CALL TO A RADIO STATION BY AN ALLEGED MEMBER, ANY RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE DEATH OF CARLOS PIZARRO, POLITICAL LEADER AND FORMER GUERRILLA COMMANDER.

THE CALLER IDENTIFIED HIMSELF AS JOHN JAIRO ARIAS TASCON. HE CALLED THE CARACOL NETWORK IN MEDELLIN TO DENOUNCE THAT THE CHARGES AGAINST THE MEDELLIN CARTEL ARE PART OF A PLAN TO BLAME THEM FOR ALL VIOLENT ACTIONS IN THE COUNTRY.

THE AUTHORS OF THE ASSASSINATION ARE SECTORS WHO SEEK TO DESTABILIZE THE COUNTRY, ARIAS TASCON ADDED.

PIZARRO, FORMER LEADER OF THE 19 APRIL MOVEMENT (M-19), THE GUERRILLA GROUP THAT LAID DOWN ITS WEAPONS ON 9 MARCH, WAS KILLED BY THE IMPACT OF THREE BULLETS FIRED AT HIM ABOARD A COLOMBIAN AVIANCA FLIGHT THAT WAS EN ROUTE TO THE CITY OF BARRANQUILLA ALONG THE COUNTRY'S ATLANTIC COAST.

AFTER THE CRIME, AT 1100 (1600 GMT), AN INDIVIDUAL WHO IDENTIFIED HIMSELF AS SAPATOCA CALLED CARACOL TO REPORT THAT THE KILLING HAD BEEN ORDERED BY FIDEL CASTANO AND HENRY PEREZ, HEADS OF THE EXTREME RIGHTIST PARAMILITARY MILITIAS.

SAPATOCA ADDED THAT CASTANO AND PEREZ PERPETRATED THE CRIME FOLLOWING ORDERS FROM THE EXTRADITABLES.

CASTANO WAS CONNECTED TO THE DEATH OF BERNARDO JARAMILLO, ALSO A PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE, FOR THE LEFTIST PATRIOTIC UNION (UP), ON 22 MARCH, ALTHOUGH AT THAT TIME IT WAS REPORTED THAT CASTANO HEADED A PARAMILITARY ORGANIZATION THAT DID NOT IMPLICATE THE EXTRADITABLES.

ON THAT OCCASION PABLO ESCOBAR, LEADER OF THE EXTRADITABLES AND THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, DENIED THAT THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS HAD KILLED JARAMILLO.

A CONFIDENTIAL REPORT DRAFTED RECENTLY BY THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY (DAS, COLOMBIAN SECRET POLICE), SAID THAT SOME ARMY AND POLICE MEMBERS COOPERATE WITH CASTANO'S CRIMINAL ORGANIZATION.

NAVARRO WOLFF, NUMBER TWO LEADER OF M-19, TOLD NEWSMEN TODAY AFTER PIZARRO WAS KILLED THAT HIS BURIAL MUST BE ATTENDED BY ALL THE COUNTRY, BECAUSE WE MUST REPUDIATE CRIME SUCH AS THIS.

NAVARRO WOLFF SAID THAT PIZARRO'S DEATH SHOWS THAT THE COUNTRY IS IN TURMOIL AND THAT IT WILL BE VERY DIFFICULT TO REBUILD THE COUNTRY. THERE IS NO SPACE EXCEPT FOR PAIN AND FOR IRE, HE ADDED.

THE BURIAL OF CARLOS MUST BE PEACEFUL, AS WAS M-19'S EXAMPLE OF PEACE GIVEN TO THE COUNTRY, HE ADDED.

IT IS HARD TO EXPLAIN HOW THINGS SUCH AS THIS OCCUR WHEN THE M-19 AND CARLOS PIZARRO WERE SETTING AN EXAMPLE OF PRUDENCE, TOLERANCE, AND UNDERSTANDING, NAVARRO SAID.

PIZARRO, A FORMER GUERRILLA COMMANDER WHO LED HIS ARMED GROUP TOWARD DEMOBILIZATION AFTER 17 MONTHS OF POLITICAL NEGOTIATIONS WITH THE GOVERNMENT OF VIRGILIO BARCO, TOLD NEWSMEN BEFORE BOARDING THE AIRCRAFT: WE ARE DOING WELL. THIS WAS A REFERENCE TO THE M-19 ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN.

PIZARRO STATED IN HIS LAST PUBLIC STATEMENT: I AM CERTAIN THAT WE WILL KNOW HOW TO WAGE OPPOSITION. WE WILL ENGAGE IN A VERY PRETTY DEMOCRATIC PLAY WITH REGARD TO THE NEXT GOVERNMENT. WE WILL PARTICIPATE IN BUILDING NEW COLOMBIAN DEMOCRACY.

THE M-19 PARTICIPATED FOR THE FIRST TIME IN THE 11 MARCH ELECTIONS, BECOMING THE THIRD POLITICAL FORCE IN BOGOTA.

NOTHING HAS BEEN SAID YET CONCERNING THE BURIAL OF PIZARRO, WHO WAS BORN 39 YEARS AGO IN CARTAGENA DE INDIAS AND WHO LEAVES THREE ORPHAN DAUGHTERS, AGED 12, 9, AND 4.

TST2-MUC4-0027

SAN SALVADOR, 6 DEC 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES, BY UNIDENTIFIED SALVADORAN AND INTERNATIONAL REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] COLONEL, WHAT SPECIFIC MEASURES HAVE BEEN TAKEN AGAINST THE MISSILES?

[PONCE] I BELIEVE THAT SPECIFIC MEASURES WE HAVE ADOPTED HAVE GIVEN US GOOD RESULTS. THEY HAVE LAUNCHED FOUR SA-7'S IN THE ZACATECOLUCA AREA; HOWEVER, OUR PILOTS HAVE SKILLFULLY AVOIDED THE ROCKETS OR MISSILES, WHICH DID NOT HIT THEIR AIRCRAFT. WE ARE ADOPTING MEASURES THAT ARE GIVING RESULTS. WE MUST ALSO CLARIFY THAT WE FEEL THAT SINCE THE LIGHT AIRCRAFT TRANSPORTING THESE MISSILES DID NOT HAVE A NORMAL LANDING AND THE MISSILES WERE NOT IN THEIR ORIGINAL PACKAGE, IT IS POSSIBLE THAT THEY SUFFERED SOME FUNCTIONAL DAMAGE WHEN THE PLANE CRASHED SOUTH OF ZACATECOLUCA. THANK GOD, [WORDS INDISTINCT]

[REPORTER] DO YOU THINK THAT THE SUMMIT OF CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS CAN OPEN NEW POSSIBILITIES FOR RESUMING TALKS WITH THE FMLN? DO YOU THINK THAT THIS SUMMIT COULD BRING ABOUT NEW STEPS TOWARD A DIALOGUE?

[PONCE] YES, I THINK THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT SINCE THE BEGINNING OF THE YEAR HAS OPENED THIS POSSIBILITY AND IS WILLING TO TALK ON A PERMANENT BASIS. I THINK THAT AT THIS TIME IT WOULD BE A POSITIVE STEP IN THE POLITICAL FIELD.

HOWEVER, IN THE MILITARY FIELD, WHERE THE FMLN HAS ATTACKED US IN AN IRRATIONAL AND VIOLENT WAY IN THE MAIN CITIES, THE ARMED FORCES IS REPLYING, AND WE WILL CONTINUE TO REPLY. WE WILL COMPLETELY DEFEAT THE FMLN.

BASED ON THE INFORMATION WE HAVE RECEIVED FROM OUR UNITS, WE HAVE INFLICTED 1,902 DEAD, 1,209 WOUNDED, AND 44 TERRORISTS HAVE DESERTED AND TURNED THEMSELVES IN TO THE AUTHORITIES. WE HAVE CONFISCATED A LARGE NUMBER OF WEAPONS. I WILL GIVE YOU THE QUANTITIES: 25 ANTIAIRCRAFT MISSILES -- ONE RED EYE AND 24 SA-7'S -- 915 RIFLES, 12 CARBINES, 11 SHOTGUNS, 156 GRENADE AND ROCKET LAUNCHERS, 49 MORTARS, 45 MACHINEGUNS, 41 SUBMACHINEGUNS, 67 REVOLVERS AND PISTOLS, 23 RADIOS, AND A LARGE AMOUNT OF EXPLOSIVES.

I MUST STRESS THAT THE FMLN HAS GATHERED ALL THESE WEAPONS WITH SUPPPORT FROM ABROAD. IT IS A LARGE ARSENAL.

I MUST ALSO NOTE THAT MANY OF THE WEAPONS WE FOUND HAD BEEN ABANDONED, WHICH MEANS THAT THE FMLN HAS HAD MANY DESERTIONS. WE HAVE ALSO FOUND WEAPONS IN HOUSES, THANKS TO THE COLLABORATION OF THE CIVILIAN POPULATION.

WE HAVE ALSO LEARNED THAT THE FMLN HAS KIDNAPPED A LARGE NUMBER OF YOUTHS HERE IN THE SAN SALVADOR AREA AND MAINLY IN USULUTAN, AS WELL AS IN CHALATENANGO. THIS MEANS THAT THEY ARE TRYING TO FILL IN THE NUMBER OF CASUALTIES THEY HAVE SUFFERED WITH YOUTHS. THIS ALSO MEANS THAT THEIR EFFICIENCY WILL BE VERY LOW.

[REPORTER] I DO NOT KNOW IF YOU HAVE SEEN OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS A LEAFLET ISSUED BY THE AIR FORCE, WHICH WAS DROPPED FROM AIRPLANES AND ALSO DISTRIBUTED ON THE STREETS. THE LEAFLET URGES SALVADORAN PATRIOTS TO DEFEND THEIR HOMELAND, THEIR PROPERTIES, AND LIVES. IT ALSO SAYS THAT IF NECESSARY, TERRORISTS MUST BE KILLED, AS WELL AS THEIR INTERNATIONALIST ALLIES. WHAT IS YOUR OPINION OF THIS LEAFLET? IS IT NOT AN INVITATION TO KILL FOREIGNERS IN THIS COUNTRY?

[PONCE] I DO NOT THINK SO, BECAUSE THE LEAFLETS MENTION INTERNATIONALISTS, WHO ARE FIGHTING ALONG WITH THE FMLN. [CONTINUED]

TST2-MUC4-0031

TEGUCIGALPA, 29 MAY 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS TODAY STATED THAT CIVILIANS AND SOLDIERS WERE KILLED ON SATURDAY DURING AN ARMED CLASH BETWEEN THE HONDURAN AND SALVADORAN ARMIES.

THROUGH A COMMUNIQUE, THE GUERRILLAS EMPHASIZED THE ARMED CLASH TOOK PLACE AFTER HONDURAN ARMY TROOPS ATTACKED IN THE HAMLET OF SAN ANDRES, SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT, IN NORTHERN EL SALVADOR.

MEMBERS OF THE COUNTERINSURGENCY ARCE BATTALION, WHO WERE CONDUCTING AN OPERATION NEAR THE HONDURAN BORDER, RESPONDED, SUPPORTED BY TWO AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS.

THE REPORT BY THE REBELS, BROADCAST FROM SAN SALVADOR BY TEGUCIGALPA RADIO AMERICA, ADDED THAT AN UNNAMED ARCE BATTALION OFFICER WAS KILLED IN THE CLASH.

THE HONDURAN TROOPS THEN RETREATED TO LOS LLANITOS, INTIBUCA DEPARTMENT, IN HONDURAS, WHERE FOUR SALVADORAN HELICOPTERS LANDED, ACCORDING TO THE FMLN.

THE REPORT ADDED THAT AS A HONDURAN HELICOPTER EVACUATED THE WOUNDED, IT WAS ATTACKED AND PURSUED 7 KM INSIDE HONDURAN TERRITORY BY A SALVADORAN AIRCRAFT FIRING ROCKETS AND MACHINEGUNS.

THE HONDURAN SOLDIERS WERE SURROUNDED IN LOS LLANITOS AND TAKEN PRISONER.

THE FMLN STATED THAT SEVERAL HOMES WERE DAMAGED AND THAT ANIMALS WERE KILLED IN THE SURROUNDING HAMLETS AND VILLAGES.

THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLA NOTED THAT IT HAD PREVIOUSLY WARNED THAT THE INVOLVEMENT OF THE HONDURAN ARMY "DUE TO U.S. DISPOSITIONS" IN THE EL SALVADOR WAR, WOULD RESULT IN CLASHES AMONG THE ARMIES OF CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES.

THE FMLN REPORT STATES THAT "IT IS NO SECRET THAT THE OLIGARCHS WHO [WILL ] REACH POWER THROUGH THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) GOVERNMENT ARE THE SAME PEOPLE INVOLVED IN THE 1969 INVASION OF HONDURAS."

THE OFFICERS, WHO AT THAT TIME "WERE DIRECTLY RESPONSIBLE FOR KILLINGS, PILLAGING, AND OUTRAGES AGAINST THE HONDURAN PEOPLE, ARE TODAY MEMBERS OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES LEADERSHIP," THE COMMUNIQUE ADDS.

ACCORDING TO THE FMLN, SATURDAY'S CLASH "WILL SET THE TONE THAT DEFINES THE BORDER CONFLICT FOR A GOVERNMENT OF OLIGARCHS THAT HAS ALWAYS HAD AN EXPANSIONIST ATTITUDE TOWARD HONDURAS."

[THE COMMUNIQUE] ALSO REQUESTS THAT THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES NOT GET INVOLVED IN A WAR FOREIGN TO THEM.

THE HONDURAN MILITARY HAS NEITHER DENIED NOR CONFIRMED THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS REPORTS, AND AN ARMY SPOKESMAN HAS STATED THAT INVESTIGATIONS ARE BEING CONDUCTED.

THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES, HAVE ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS, REPORTED THAT THE GUERRILLAS HAVE "HIDEOUTS" IN SALVADORAN REFUGEE CAMPS, AND CONTINUOUSLY ENTER HONDURAN TERRITORY TO REST OR FOR RESUPPLY OF WEAPONS AND AMMUNITION.

TST2-MUC4-0032

BOGOTA, 22 MAR 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL OSCAR BOTERO RESTREPO DISCLOSED THIS AFTERNOON THAT MEDELLIN CARTEL BOSS PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA ORDERED THE ASSASSINATION OF BERNARDO JARAMILLO OSSA, PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE OF PATRIOTIC UNION, UP.

BOTERO SAID THAT INITIAL INVESTIGATIONS HAVE REVEALED THAT ESCOBAR GAVIRIA PLANNED AND ORDERED THE ATTACK ON JARAMILLO OSSA. GEN. BOTERO TOLD REPORTERS THAT THE MEDELLIN CARTEL CONTRACTED THE SERVICES OF AN ORGANIZATION OF HIRED ASSASSINS AND SENT THEM TO BOGOTA TO ASSASSINATE THE UP LEADER.

HE ADDED THAT ESCOBAR GAVIRIA ORDERED THE DELIVERY OF AN INITIAL SUM OF 300,000 PESOS TO A THIRD PERSON AFTER THE CRIME WAS COMMITTED AT EL DORADO AIRPORT'S PEDESTRIAN OVERPASS IN BOGOTA.

THE DEFENSE MINISTER SAID THAT MINUTES AFTER THE KILLING THE DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY] INTELLIGENCE SERVICE INTERCEPTED AN ESCOBAR GAVIRIA CONVERSATION IN MEDELLIN. HE WAS ORDERING HIS ACCOMPLICES TO PAY 300,000 PESOS TO A THIRD PERSON LINKED TO THE PAID ASSASSIN WHO KILLED THE UP LEADER.

BOTERO ALSO DISCLOSED THAT THE ASSASSIN IS A 16-YEAR-OLD YOUTH WHO CARRIED A FALSE IDENTIFICATION CARD UNDER THE NAME OF JAIRO ALBERTO RESTREPO POSADA.

MEANWHILE, ANONYMOUS CALLS WERE RECEIVED BY VARIOUS BOGOTA MEDIA TODAY. THE CALLERS WERE ATTRIBUTING THE ATTACK ON UP LEADER JARAMILLO OSSA TO A SO-CALLED GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA COMMANDO GROUP. IN THESE CALLS, IT WAS SAID THAT THE MEDELLIN CARTEL DECIDED TO RESUME THE WAR BECAUSE FOR FIVE MONTHS IT OFFERED TO NEGOTIATE WITH THE VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS GOVERNMENT, AND THE ONLY RESPONSE IT RECEIVED WAS TO URGE CARTEL MEMBERS TO TURN THEMSELVES IN TO JUSTICE.

IN ADDITION, THREATS WERE MADE AGAINST OTHER COLOMBIAN POLITICAL FIGURES SUCH AS LIBERAL PARTY CANDIDATE CESAR GAVIRIA TRUJILLO. THE CALLERS SAID THAT THE EXTRADITABLES RELEASED KIDNAPPED PEOPLE, DELIVERED LABORATORIES, AND LARGE QUANTITIES OF DYNAMITE AS PROOF OF THEIR INTENTION TO TALK, BUT THEY NEVER RECEIVED A REPLY FROM THE GOVERNMENT.

THE CALLERS SAID: WE ARE GOING TO TURN OURSELVES IN, BUT WE WILL BE DEAD WHEN WE DO SO. HOWEVER, BEFORE THIS HAPPENS, THEY SAID, THE COUNTRY WILL SEE THE BODIES OF ITS LEADERS, JUST AS IN THE CASE OF JARAMILLO OSSA.

TST2-MUC4-0033

SAN SALVADOR, 28 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] FRANCISCO MERINO, VICE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC AND INTERIOR MINISTER, HAS STRONGLY CONDEMNED THE MURDER OF FORMER SUPREME COURT PRESIDENT FRANCISCO JOSE GUERRERO. MERINO DESCRIBED THE CULPRITS AS MURDEROUS BEASTS.

THE VICE PRESIDENT WENT TO THE MEDICAL-SURGICAL HOSPITAL OF THE SALVADORAN INSTITUTE OF SOCIAL SECURITY, TO WHICH DR GUERRERO WAS TAKEN AFTER THE ATTACK. GUERRERO, WHO WAS AN ADVISER TO THE GOVERNMENTAL COMMISSION FOR SUPPORT TO THE DIALOGUE [COMISION DE APOYO GUBERNAMENTAL DE DIALOGO], WAS SHOT TO DEATH BY TERRORISTS AT THE INTERSECTION OF BOULEVARD DE LOS HEROES AND ALAMEDA JUAN PABLO II.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] WHAT THEY ARE SHOWING IS THAT THEY ARE BENT ON CARRYING OUT TOTALLY DESTRUCTIVE ACTIONS TO LOWER THE CONFIDENCE OF THE POPULATION AND TO PROVOKE GENERAL PANIC. I THINK THAT ALTHOUGH AS A GOVERNMENT WE HAVE ALWAYS MAINTAINED A CONCILIATORY POSITION TO ATTAIN PEACE IN EL SALVADOR, WE MUST ALSO MAKE A FIRMER DECISION TO TAKE STRONGER ACTION. THE PEOPLE WHO COMMIT THESE WANTON ACTIONS ARE DERANGED PEOPLE. THEY DO NOT UNDERSTAND WORDS. THEY DO NOT UNDERSTAND THAT THEY MUST RESPECT A LEGAL SYSTEM, OR A DEMOCRATIC PROCESS OR ONE OF HUMANIZATION. THEY ARE SIMPLY BEASTS AND MURDERERS AND MUST BE TREATED AS SUCH. [END RECORDING]

MERINO SAID THE MURDERERS MUST BE PUNISHED WITH THE FULL WEIGHT OF THE LAWS, AND THAT ONE OF THE TERRORISTS WHO WAS WOUNDED AND CAPTURED AT THE SITE OF THE CRIME IS UNDER INTERROGATION.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] ONE OF THE CRIMINALS WAS WOUNDED. THIS WILL OBVIOUSLY ENABLE US TO OBTAIN SOME CLUES AS TO THE IDENTITY OF THE ACTUAL KILLERS AND OF THE MASTERMINDS OF THIS NEW MURDER, WHICH HAS SHOCKED SALVADORAN SOCIETY.

AS IN PREVIOUS CASES, WE ARE CONDUCTING INVESTIGATIONS IN THIS CASE. HOWEVER, I REPEAT THAT THE TIME HAS COME FOR US TO TAKE A FIRMER STAND, TO DO OUR UTMOST, AND TO REALIZE THAT IF NOTHING HAS HAPPENED TO US THUS FAR, IT DOES NOT MEAN WE WILL NOT FALL VICTIM TO THESE MURDERERS. IT IS BETTER TO TAKE PRECAUTIONS NOW THAN TO HAVE REGRETS LATER. [END RECORDING]

MERINO SAID THAT THIS CAMPAIGN OF VIOLENCE PROMOTED BY THE TERRORIST HORDES HAS NOT ENDED. CLEAR EVIDENCE OF THIS IS THIS BRUTAL AND COWARDLY MURDER, WHICH HAS AGAIN FILLED THE SUFFERING SALVADORAN PEOPLE WITH SORROW.

TST2-MUC4-0034

GUATEMALA CITY, 22 SEP 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] FIVE GUATEMALAN UNIVERSITY LEADERS THREATENED WITH DEATH HAVE SOUGHT REFUGE IN PANAMA, COSTA RICA, AND MEXICO, WHILE UN HUMAN RIGHTS OBSERVER PETER KOOIJMANS IS IN GUATEMALA CONDUCTING AN INVESTIGATION ON THE INCREASING VIOLENCE IN THIS CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRY.

ACCORDING TO MEMBERS OF THE UNIVERSITY STUDENT ASSOCIATION [AEU] OF SAN CARLOS DE GUATEMALA UNIVERSITY, THE STUDENTS LEADERS DECIDED TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY BECAUSE OF THE CONTINUOUS THREATS OF DEATH AND PERSECUTION AND DUE TO THE KIDNAPPING AND ASSASSINATION OF FIVE UNIVERSITY STUDENTS.

THE NAMES OF THE STUDENTS WHO FLED THE COUNTRY ARE BEING KEPT SECRET TO PROTECT THEIR RELATIVES WHO LIVE IN GUATEMALA CITY AND IN THE INTERIOR OF THE COUNTRY, THE SOURCES MAINTAINED.

THREE OF THE STUDENTS TRAVELED TO PANAMA, ONE TO MEXICO, AND ANOTHER TO COSTA RICA.

THIS MONTH, THE CORPSES OF FIVE ASSASSINATED AEU LEADERS WERE FOUND IN THE CAPITAL, SOME WITH SIGNS OF TORTURE. SIX OTHER UNIVERSITY STUDENT LEADERS REMAIN KIDNAPPED.

BELISARIO POLO, STUDENT AFFAIRS DIRECTOR AT THE UNIVERSITY OF PANAMA, TODAY TOLD EFE THAT THE THREE AEU LEADERS ARRIVED IN THE COUNTRY LAST WEEKEND AND ARE LIVING IN PRIVATE HOUSES.

GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS SAID THEY HAVE NO OFFICIAL REPORTS ON THE DEPARTURE OF THE HIGHEST AEU LEADERS.

THE DEPARTURE OF THE FIVE UNIVERSITY STUDENTS LEADERS COINCIDES WITH THE VISIT TO GUATEMALA OF PETER KOOIJMANS, WHO YESTERDAY MET GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO, GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS, AND ARMY OFFICERS TO GATHER INFORMATION.

DURING HIS MEETING WITH GOVERNMENT MINISTER ROBERTO VALLE, KOOIJMANS REQUESTED REPORTS ON THE INVESTIGATIONS THE GOVERNMENT HAS CONDUCTED ON THE CASE OF THE KIDNAPPED STUDENTS, THE GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT OFFICIAL SAID.

THE KIDNAPPING AND ASSASSINATION OF THE FIVE UNIVERSITY STUDENTS AND THE THREATS AGAINST OTHER AEU MEMBERS HAVE BEEN CONDEMNED BY LEADERS FROM UNIVERSITIES IN MEXICO, HONDURAS, PERU, COLOMBIA, COSTA RICA, EL SALVADOR, NICARAGUA, AND PANAMA.

UNIVERSITY STUDENTS LEADERS FROM CANADA, ECUADOR, CHILE, AND THE FRG HAVE EXPRESSED THEIR SOLIDARITY AND DEMANDED THAT THE GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT TO INVESTIGATE THESE ASSASSINATIONAS.

THE AEU REQUESTED THE HIGHER UNIVERSITY COUNCIL TO SUSPEND CLASSES FOR THE CURRENT SEMESTER IN VIEW OF THE WAVE OF VIOLENCE GUATEMALA IS SUFFERING AND IN VIEW OF THE DEATH THREATS AGAINST THE MAIN STUDENT LEADERS. AS A RESPONSE, THE CSU HAS DECIDED TO LET EACH ACADEMIC SECTION DECIDE THE STRATEGY IT WILL IMPLEMENT TO GET PROTECTION FROM THE VIOLENCE. SEVERAL OF THE STATE UNIVERSITY SCHOOLS HAVE MODIFIED THE EVENING SCHEDULE, AND MOST CLASSES HAVE BEEN REDUCED TO 2-HOURS PERIODS SO STUDENTS CAN RETURN HOME EARLY.

SEVERAL LABOR UNION ORGANIZATIONS HAVE CONDEMNED THE KIDNAPPING AND ASSASSINATION ON 15 SEPTEMBER OF EDUARDO ANTONIO LOPEZ PALENCIA, A STUDENT WHOSE CORPSE SHOWED SIGNS OF TORTURE.

TST2-MUC4-0036

CLANDESTINE, 7 FEB 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [STATION COMMENTARY] [TEXT] IT IS IMPOSSIBLE TO HAVE FREE ELECTIONS IN A COUNTRY WHERE REPRESSION PREVAILS. IN AN INDISPUTABLE EFFORT OF CLEAR FLEXIBILITY AND WILLINGNESS FOR PEACE, THE FMLN PRESENTED A PEACE PROPOSAL TO JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE'S GOVERNMENT AND THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND. THAT PROPOSAL IS AIMED AT TURNING ELECTIONS INTO A CONTRIBUTION TO PEACE.

TWO WEEKS HAVE PASSED SINCE WE PRESENTED OUR PROPOSAL, AND NEITHER THE GOVERNMENT NOR THE ARMED FORCES HAVE OFFICIALLY RESPONDED TO THE FMLN INITIATIVE. THAT INITIATIVE HAS HAD THE SUPPORT OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY AND OF OUR COUNTRY'S LARGEST GROUPS.

NEITHER THE GOVERNMENT NOR THE HIGH COMMAND HAVE RESPONDED TO THE PEOPLE'S OUTCRY AND WORLD EXPECTATIONS, WHICH ARE AWAITING A POSITIVE RESPONSE TO OUR PROPOSAL.

ON THE CONTRARY, THE GOVERNMENT, ITS ARMED FORCES, AND THE MEMBERS OF THEIR SQUADS DISGUISED IN CIVILIAN CLOTHES CONTINUE THEIR DIRTY WAR AGAINST THE PEOPLES MOVEMENT AND THEIR WIDESPREAD WAR IN THE COUNTRYSIDE.

THE NATIONAL GUARD [WORD INDISTINCT] MURDERED UNIVERSITY STUDENT MARIO FLORES, WHOSE BODY WAS LEFT ON A HIGHWAY NEAR THE PORT OF ACAJUTLA. MEANWHILE, NATIONAL POLICE MEMBERS WHO WERE DRESSED IN CIVILIAN CLOTHES SEIZED UNIVERSITY STUDENTS HUGO MARTINEZ AND RAUL RAMIREZ, WHO ARE STILL MISSING.

JAIME ESTEVEZ, A MEMBER OF THE BREAD, LAND, WORK, AND FREEDOM MOVEMENT [MPTL] WAS TAKEN TO THE USULUTAN JAIL TO BE MURDERED AND THE CRIME WAS SUPPOSED TO GO UNNOTICED.

MEANWHILE, ACCORDING TO REPORTS FROM MEMBERS OF THE NATIONAL FEDERATION OF AGRICULTURAL AND LIVESTOCK COOPERATIVES, FENACOA, ON 31 JANUARY, OROMONTIQUE BATTALION TROOPS OF THE 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADE COMMANDED BY LIEUTENANT PACHECHO MURDERED PEASANTS VICTOR MANUEL VASQUEZ AND RAFAEL ROMERO. THE TROOPS FAKED A CLASH AT HORCONES DE BERLIN CANTON TO MURDER THOSE PEASANTS.

ON 4 JANUARY, LUCIA AND MARIA ASUNCION ROMERO, AND MINOR PEDRO GONZALEZ ERAZO WERE CAPTURED AT THE AHUACHAPAN BUS STATION BY ARMY TROOPS COMMANDED BY MURDERER COLONEL CANAS.

THE PEASANT COMMUNAL ASSOCIATION, ACC, CONTINUES TO DEMAND THE RELEASE OF PEASANTS BARTOLO RODRIGUEZ, WHO WAS CAPTURED ON 27 JANUARY, AND [NAME INDISTINCT] CAPTURED ON 2 FEBRUARY BY TROOPS OF COLONAL ORLANDO MONTANO OF THE 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADE.

THE NONGOVERNMENTAL SALVADORAN HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION REPORTED THE SEIZURE OF MACLOVIA GONZALEZ, VIRGILIO ORTIZ CRUZ, AND VIRGILIO ORTIZ, WHO WERE CAPTURED ON 4 JANUARY BY MILITARY DETACHMENT NO 4 TROOPS AT EL MAYUELO CANTON, MORAZAN DEPARTMENT. THEIR WHEREABOUTS ARE STILL UNKNOWN.

THE MPTL ALSO REPORTED THAT ROBERTO MENA WAS CAPTURED BY ATONAL BATTALION TROOPS AT 1600 ON 5 FEBRUARY.

THERE CANNOT BE FREE AND CLEAN ELECTIONS IN THIS ATMOSPHERE OF REPRESSION. THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMY HIGH COMMAND CONTINUE TERRIFYING AND KILLING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THE PEOPLES' WILL CANNOT BE EXPRESSED THROUGH THEIR VOTE WITH SUCH AN ATMOSPHERE OF REPRESSION, ESPECIALLY IF THE GROUPS DISPUTING POWER ARE A BUNCH OF MURDERERS AND CORRUPT MEN.

TST2-MUC4-0037

SAN SALVADOR, 17 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WE CANNOT BUT THANK YOU AND RECOGNIZE THE WAY IN WHICH YOU ARE BEARING THE FMLN AGGRESSION.

WE TRULY HAVE A DUTY TOWARD THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND WE WILL GIVE YOU ALL OUR SUPPORT. WE ARE WILLING TO GIVE YOU EVERYTHING THAT WE CAN POSSIBLY GIVE YOU SO THAT [WORD INDISTINCT] CAN LIVE IN PEACE AND TRANQUILLITY.

ECHOING THAT ATTITUDE, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WE MUST ALSO HELP OUR SOLDIERS. WE MUST GIVE THEM ALL THE COOPERATION THEY NEED IN ORDER FOR THE CURRENT SITUATION TO END AS SOON AS POSSIBLE. WE MUST CALL FOR NATIONAL UNITY. WE MUST ALL COOPERATE TO SAVE OUR HOMELAND FROM THE TERRORIST AGGRESSION. WE MUST ALL UNITE TO ACHIEVE PEACE AND TRANQUILLITY AS SOON AS POSSIBLE, ALWAYS TAKING INTO ACCOUNT THE SITUATION OUR COUNTRY IS GOING THROUGH.

WE MUST SUPPORT OUR DEMOCRATIC PROCESS, OUR INSTITUTIONS, AND WE MUST TOTALLY REJECT THE FMLN TERRORIST FORCES. WE MUST FACE THOSE FORCES THROUGH A UNITED FRONT. WE CALL ON ALL OF OUR COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIC AND POLITICAL FORCES TO FORM A UNITED FRONT; TO REJECT VIOLENCE AS A WAY OF SOLVING PROBLEMS IN EL SALVADOR; AND TO UNITE IN OUR ASPIRATION TO LIVE IN A DEMOCRACY AND IN PEACE, TRANQUILLITY, AND RESPECT FOR THE LAWS. BRIEFLY, WE MUST UNITE TO LIVE IN A DE JURE STATE IN WHICH THE PEOPLE CAN LIVE IN HARMONY AND TRANQUILLITY.

IT IS THEREFORE NECESSARY THAT ALL POLITICAL PARTIES JOIN EFFORTS, NOT AROUND A GOVERNMENT OR AN INSTITUTION, BUT FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE TO ACHIEVE THEIR DEAREST GOALS.

WE ARE RECEIVING THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY'S SUPPORT. THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY IS SUPPORTING SALVADORAN DEMOCRACY. WE HAVE RECEIVED ENCOURAGING MESSAGES FROM COUNTRIES SUCH AS GREAT BRITAIN, WHICH HAS VIGOROUSLY CONDEMNED THE FMLN TERRORIST ACTION. WE HAVE RECEIVED A MESSAGE FROM THE EEC, IN WHICH THAT GROUP IS TELLING THE FMLN THAT THE ARMED STRUGGLE IS NOT THE SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEMS AND THAT TO BE ABLE TO SOLVE OUR PROBLEMS, WE MUST FIRST HAVE PEACE AND THEN ACHIEVE THE COUNTRY'S SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT. THOSE GOALS MUST BE ATTAINED THROUGH A PEACE PROCESS. THE GOVERNMENT HAD ALREADY BEGAN THAT PROCESS AND THE FMLN TRIED TO BREAK IT. THE PEACE PROCESS MUST BE BASED ON THE ESQUIPULAS II AGREEMENT AND ESPECIALLY ON THE TELA AGREEMENT.

WE HAVE ALSO WITNESSED HOW DIFFERENT POLITICAL AND IDEOLOGICAL TENDENCIES HAVE BECOME UNIFIED IN OTHER COUNTRIES. [CONTINUED]

TST2-MUC4-0038

SANTIAGO, 14 DEC 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [STATEMENT] [HERNAN BUCHI, IN PROGRESS] [TEXT] UNFORTUNATELY MARRED BY A CARABINERO'S ASSASSINATION, WE HAVE RETURNED TO DEMOCRACY. PATRICIO AYLWIN HAS BEEN ELECTED PRESIDENT OF CHILE. I CONGRATULATE HIM AND HIS FOLLOWERS, AND I WISH HIM SUCCESS IN HIS GOVERNMENT, FOR THE GOOD OF CHILE AND CHILEANS. HIS TRIUMPH IS NOT A DEFEAT FOR OUR IDEAS. MY CAMPAIGN WAS CONSTANTLY FOCUSED ON THE IDEA OF FREEDOM -- BOTH POLITICAL AND ECONOMIC -- PRIVATE PROPERTY, AND THE SOCIAL MARKET ECONOMY. IT HAD TO BE THIS WAY BECAUSE THIS IS THE FUTURE CHILEANS WANT, AND IF OUR IDEAS GAIN GROUND, THAT IS MORE IMPORTANT THAN THE NAME OF THE MAN CHARGED WITH IMPLEMENTING THEM.

BUT THOSE IDEAS MUST BE DISSEMINATED EVEN MORE WITH INCESSANT WORK. IN A DEMOCRACY, THE OPPOSITION ALSO GOVERNS. HISTORY HAS PLACED US IN THE CONSTRUCTIVE OPPOSITION FOR THE NEXT 4 YEARS. WE WILL BE WILLING TO COOPERATE FOR THE GOOD OF THE COUNTRY, BUT WE WILL STAY ALERT TO DEFEND OUR VISION OF THE FUTURE. I AM CONVINCED THAT AN INTELLIGENT OPPOSITION CAN DO MUCH FOR THE COUNTRY, PARTICULARLY IF THAT OPPOSITION IS BACKED BY THE NEARLY 2 MILLION PEOPLE WHO TODAY SUPPORTED MY CANDIDACY.

THE WORK THAT LIES AHEAD WILL TO A LARGE EXTENT BE CARRIED OUT IN CONGRESS. THE INFORMATION NOW AVAILABLE SUGGESTS THAT THE PACT FOR DEMOCRACY AND PROGRESS HAS GAINED A VALUABLE REPRESENTATION IN BOTH HOUSES OF CONGRESS. LET MY CONGRATULATIONS GO TO THE FUTURE DEPUTIES AND SENATORS OF DEMOCRACY AND PROGRESS. I SEIZE THIS OCCASION TO LET THEM KNOW THAT THEY CAN COUNT ON MY SUPPORT.

I AM SATISFIED WITH THE NUMBER OF VOTES I WON, CONSIDERING THE UNFAVORABLE CIRCUMSTANCES. I AM SATISFIED WITH THE ENTHUSIASTIC AND GENEROUS WORK CARRIED OUT BY MY ELECTORAL STAFF AND BY THE POLITICAL PARTIES. I THANK THEM FOR THEIR SUPPORT. I WANT TO ESPECIALLY THANK EACH OF THE MEN AND WOMEN WHO VOTED FOR ME. TO THE MILLIONS OF CHILEAN MEN AND WOMEN WHO IN SUNSHINE OR RAIN THROUGHOUT CHILE FILLED UP STADIUMS, PLAZAS, AND STREETS, CHANTING OUT SLOGANS FOR THE FUTURE; TO THOSE WHO SAW THE STREET WITH THE SYMBOL OF THE STAR OF HOPE; TO THOSE WHO PASTED MY PICTURE ON WALLS, WINDOWS, AND NOTEBOOKS; TO THOSE WHO ENCOURAGED ME IN THIS TIRESOME BUT MOVING CAMPAIGN WITH AN EMBRACE, A HANDSHAKE, OR A SMILE; TO ALL THOSE I WANT TO EXPRESS MY DEEPEST THANKS. I WILL KEEP THEM IN MY HEART FOR THE REST OF MY LIFE.

WHEN WE INITIATED THIS PRESIDENTIAL CAMPAIGN -- AN HONOR THAT YOU KNOW I NEVER SOUGHT -- I TOLD MY FOLLOWERS THAT JUST LIKE CLIMBING A MOUNTAIN, THERE WERE MOMENTS OF ADVANCE, FATIGUE, AND FALLS, BUT I TRUSTED THAT, MUSTERING ALL OUR ENERGY, WE WOULD OUTDO OURSELVES AND REACH THE SUMMIT. I AM SATISFIED BECAUSE I BELIEVE THAT EACH ONE OF US, AS INDIVIDUALS AND AS A POLITICAL FORCE, HAVE OUTDONE OURSELVES AND CLIMBED A LON WAY UP THE MOUNTAIN, BATTLING FOR OUR IDEAS AND FOR VOTES. WE DID NOT REACH THE SUMMIT, TRUE, BUT THIS MUST NOT DISMAY US. TODAY WE ARE CLOSER TO THE SUMMIT THAN WHEN WE STARTED. THANK YOU VERY MUCH, EVERYONE. GOOD NIGHT.

TST2-MUC4-0040

BOGOTA, 17 JAN 90 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [THE EXTRADITABLES] [TEXT] 1. WE HAVE LEARNED ABOUT THE PATRIOTIC INVITATION INCLUDED IN THE DOCUMENT SIGNED BY MONSIGNOR MARIO REVOLLO BRAVO AND BY THE DISTINGUISHED FORMER PRESIDENTS ALFONSO LOPEZ, JULIO CESAR TURBAY, AND MISAEL PASTRANA AS WELL AS BY PATRIOTIC UNION PRESIDENT DIEGO MONTANA CUELLAR.

2. TO RESPOND TO SUCH PROPOSALS, WE REITERATE OUR WELL-KNOWN PEACE COMMITMENTS EXPRESSED IN OUR MOST SINCERE AND FRANK STATEMENTS.

3. WE FULLY SHARE THE CRITERIA EXPRESSED BY THEM REGARDING THE SURVIVAL OF THE STATE AND GOVERNMENT, WHICH WAS DEMOCRATICALLY ELECTED, AGAINST ORGANIZATIONS AND PEOPLE LIKE US, WHO HAVE SHOWN NO REGARD FOR THE LAW BY FIGHTING INSTITUTIONS AND THE LEGALLY ESTABLISHED ORDER.

4. AFTER EVALUATING OUR CONDUCT UNDER THE PREVIOUS CONCEPT, WE ARE ONLY INTERESTED IN PEACE, TRANQUILLITY, AND DEMOCRACY FOR OUR FATHERLAND AND FOR OUR PEOPLE.

5. AS A RESULT, WE ACCEPT THE VICTORY OF THE STATE, THE INSTITUTIONS, AND THE LEGALLY ESTABLISHED GOVERNMENT. WE WILL LAY DOWN OUR WEAPONS AND OTHER MEANS OF STRUGGLE FOR THE SAKE OF THE COUNTRY'S BEST INTERESTS.

6. WE ACCEPT THE LEGAL ORDER THAT IS CURRENTLY IN FORCE WITH THE HOPE THAT THE GOVERNMENT AND SOCIETY WILL RESPECT OUR RIGHTS AND WILL ALLOW US TO RETURN TO OUR FAMILIES AND COMMUNITIES.

7. AS AN ABSOLUTE PROOF OF OUR INTEREST IN ACHIEVING PEACE, WE HAVE DECIDED TO IMMEDIATELY RELEASE MRS PATRICIA ECHAVARRIA AND HER DAUGHTER AS WELL AS OTHER PEOPLE WHO ARE BEING HELD HOSTAGE AS CIRCUMSTANCES PERMIT. WE WOULD LIKE TO ADD THAT WE ARE NOT RESPONSIBLE FOR ALL THE CASES OF KIDNAPPED PEOPLE OF WHICH WE ARE ACCUSED.

8. WE OFFER OUR SERVICES AS MEDIATORS TO ACHIEVE PEACE WITH THE EMERALD TRAFFICKERS, THE SO-CALLED PARAMILITARY GROUPS, AND THE SO-CALLED HIRED ASSASSINS WITH THE ONLY PURPOSE OF ENDING THE VIOLENCE THAT IS HURTING OUR COLOMBIAN FATHERLAND.

9. WE HAVE DECIDED TO SUSPEND THE SHIPMENT OF DRUGS AND TO TURN IN OUR WEAPONS, EXPLOSIVES, LABORATORIES, CLANDESTINE LANDING STRIPS, AND OTHER ELEMENTS THAT ARE RELATED TO OUR ACTIVITIES AS SOON AS WE GET CONSTITUTIONAL AND LEGAL GUARANTEES.

10. THERE WILL BE NO MORE BOMBINGS ANYWHERE ON NATIONAL TERRITORY AND WE HAVE ORDERED THE SUSPENSION OF ALL TYPES OF EXECUTIONS OF POLITICAL LEADERS, GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS, ASSOCIATION LEADERS, JUDICIAL OFFICIALS, JOURNALISTS, POLICEMEN, AND SOLDIERS.

11. THE ESSENTIAL REASON FOR OUR STRUGGLE HAS BEEN AND WILL ALWAYS BE OUR FAMILIES, OUR FREEDOM, OUR PEOPLE, OUR LIVES, AND OUR RIGHTS AS CITIZENS OF THIS FATHERLAND.

THE EXTRADITABLES, 16 JANUARY 1990

TST2-MUC4-0041

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [STATEMENT BY SALVADORAN DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL RAFAEL HUMBERTO LARIOS LOPEZ] [TEXT] BRAVE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, ON THIS OCCASION AND AS DEFENSE AND PUBLIC SECURITY MINISTER, PROFESSIONAL SOLDIER, AND A SALVADORAN CITIZEN, I AM VERY PLEASED TO BE ABLE TO BRING YOU THIS MESSAGE. ABOVE ALL, THIS MESSAGE CONVEYS OUR MOST RESPECTFUL AND THOUGHFUL GREETINGS TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND OUR HOPES THAT, DURING THIS TROUBLED TIME, YOU WILL REMAIN CALM AND HAVE CONFIDENCE AND FAITH IN YOUR ARMED FORCES.

A FEW MOMENTS AGO, YOU HEARD THE VOICE OF THE FIRST SOLDIER OF OUR GLORIOUS ARMED FORCES, THE VOICE OF THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC AND GENERAL COMMANDER OF THE ARMED FORCES. AT THIS TIME, I WISH TO EXPRESS THE FEELINGS OF EACH AND EVERY MEMBER OF THE ARMED FORCES, OF THE INSTITUTION THAT AT THIS MOMENT IS BEING INSTITUTIONALLY CHALLENGED. WE, AS SOLDIERS BORN OF THIS PEOPLE TO SERVE THIS PEOPLE, EXPRESS OUR SOLIDARITY WITH THAT MESSAGE OF CONFIDENCE, SECURITY, AND HOPE SENT BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC.

EVERYONE HAS HEARD ABOUT WHAT HAS HAPPENED IN OUR COUNTRY IN THE PAST 48 HOURS. NO CONSCIENTIOUS CITIZEN, NO REAL SALVADORAN, IS UNAWARE OF THE AGGRESSION TO WHICH WE HAVE ONCE AGAIN BEEN SUBJECTED BY THE F M L N'S [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FORCES] TREACHEROUS TERRORIST FORCES. EVIDENTLY, THIS ACTION, THIS TERRORORIST ACTION, IS ONLY AIMED AT CAUSING PAIN AND SORROW FOR THE PEOPLE AND AT DESTROYING THE REAL FEELINGS, INSPIRATION, AND WILL OF THE PEOPLE. ON THIS OCCASION, THE ARMED FORCES STEP FORWARD TO DEFEND THE PEOPLE, THE PEOPLE WHO ARE DEMANDING THE OBLITERATION OF THESE TERRORIST AND COWARDLY FORCES.

THE ATTITUDE OF OUR COURAGEOUS PEOPLE, THE ATTITUDE OF THE PEOPLE WHO TODAY ARE WRITING ONE OF THE MOST BRILLIANT PAGES IN OUR HISTORY, CREATES AN OPPORTUNITY FOR THE ARMED FORCES, GUARANTOR OF SECURITY, ORDER, AND TRANQUILITY, TO SAY: SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THE ARMED FORCES ARE WITH YOU; THE ARMED FORCES ASSUME THEIR PROFESSIONAL DUTY OF DEFENDING THE MOST SACRED INTERESTS OF OUR HOMELAND, OF OUR COUNTRY, EL SALVADOR.

THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES, AS AN INSTITUTION, HAVE NEVER FORGOTTEN THEIR DUTY AND TODAY REITERATE THEIR ABSOLUTE WILLINGNESS AND DETERMINATION TO MAKE THE BIGGEST SACRIFICE IF THIS BECOMES NECESSARY, SO THAT YOU, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, CAN ASPIRE TO A FUTURE FULL OF HAPPINESS AND WELL-BEING.

WE PRAISE THE DETERMINATION OF THE PEOPLE. WE APPLAUD AND CONGRATULATE THE PEOPLE FOR THEIR DETERMINATION AND THE STOICISM WITH WHICH THEY, THE BRAVE SALVADORAN CITIZENS, HAVE CONFRONTED THESE MOMENTS OF TRAGEDY AND CHALLENGE.

WE SAY: SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THIS INSTITUTION -- YOUR ARMED FORCES -- IS AT YOUR SIDE. THE ARMED FORCES ARE WILLING TO SHED THEIR BLOOD AND GIVE THEIR LIVES PRECISELY SO THAT THE CHILDREN OF OUR PEOPLE, SO THAT THE CHILDREN OF OUR CHILDREN, CAN ASPIRE TO A WORTHY, FREE, JUST, AND INDEPENDENT LIFE.

WE WISH TO CONGRATULATE OUR PEOPLE FOR THEIR ATTITUDE. WE WISH TO CONGRATULATE ALL THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE BECAUSE, WITH THEIR WORDS OF ENCOURAGEMENT SENT TO US THROUGH DIFFERENT MEANS, THE INSTITUTION FEELS STRONGER AND MORE WILLING TO DEFEND THE REAL ASPIRATIONS OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

THIS BRAVE ATTITUDE -- THIS ATTITUDE THAT REFLECTS THE REAL SALVADORANS -- IS, WITHOUT DOUBT, THE STRONGEST RESPONSE AND THE WORST PUNISHMENT THE TERRORIST FORCES COULD RECEIVE. [CONTINUED]

TST2-MUC4-0042

BOGOTA, 15 DEC 89 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] GENERAL CARLOS ARTURO CASADIEGO TORRADO, SECOND IN COMMAND OF THE COLOMBIAN POLICE, HAS REPORTED THE DEATH OF GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA. [POLICE DIRECTOR] GENERAL GOMEZ PADILLA, WHO IS IN CALI, WILL TRAVEL TO BOGOTA AND WILL SOON HOLD A NEWS CONFERENCE TO PROVIDE MORE DETAILS ON THE DEATH OF THIS CRIMINAL.

IN AN INTERVIEW, GEN CASADIEGO TORRADO INFORMED RCN OF THE OPERATION MOUNTED IN THE AREA WHERE THE INCIDENT OCCURRED.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CASADIEGO] WE HAVE BEEN INFORMED BY THOSE OPERATING IN THAT AREA THAT RODRIGUEZ GACHA, HIS SON, AND THE PEOPLE WITH THEM HAVE BEEN KILLED.

THAT IS THE INFORMATION WE HAVE AVAILABLE. WE DO NOT HAVE DETAILS ON THE OPERATION YET. IT WAS THE RESULT OF LONG-TERM INTELLIGENCE WORK CARRIED OUT WITH GREAT PROFESSIONALISM, WHICH GAVE US INFORMATION ON WHERE HE COULD BE FOUND. WE DEPLOYED SPECIAL GROUPS TO CARRY OUT THAT TASK.

[REPORTER] GENERAL, EXACTLY WHERE DID THE OPERATION, IN WHICH RODRIGUEZ GACHA, HIS SON, AND 15 OTHERS WERE KILLED, TAKE PLACE?

[CASADIEGO] IN A RURAL AREA, AS YOU KNOW, IN THE NORTHERN PART OF THE COUNTRY. I DO NOT KNOW THE EXACT LOCATION.

[REPORTER] HAS IT BEEN OFFICIALLY REPORTED THAT RODRIGUEZ GACHA AND HIS SON WERE KILLED? IS THIS AN OFFICIAL REPORT FROM THE NATIONAL POLICE?

[CASADIEGO] THAT IS THE INFORMATION I HAVE. THAT IS THE INFORMATION I HAVE RECEIVED FROM THE SCENE OF THE INCIDENT.

[REPORTER] WHO ARE THE OTHER 15 PEOPLE KILLED?

[CASADIEGO] WE HAVE NOT IDENTIFIED THEM YET. OFFICIALS ARE TRAVELING TO THE SITE TO OFFICIALLY IDENTIFY THE BODIES.

[REPORTER] WERE THEY ASSISTANTS, BODYGUARDS, ESCORTS?

[CASADIEGO] YES, WE ARE SURE OF THAT.

[REPORTER] HAVE WEAPONS OR OTHER ITEMS BEEN CONFISCATED? WE HAVE HEARD THAT IMPORTANT DOCUMENTS WERE FOUND.

[CASADIEGO] YES, WE KNOW THAT WEAPONS WERE FOUND WHICH WERE USED TO PROTECT THIS MAN. HOWEVER, AS I SAID, WE DO NOT HAVE THE DETAILS ON THE INCIDENT YET. WE HAVE BEEN TOLD THAT RODRIGUEZ GACHA AND HIS SON WERE KILLED, AS WELL AS OTHER INDIVIDUALS WHO WERE WITH HIM.

[REPORTER] WHO ELSE IS THERE? IS THERE A COMMISSION OF JUDGES? WE UNDERSTAND THAT A FEW MOMENTS AGO A PLANE DEPARTED WITH REPRESENTATIVES FROM THE CRIMINAL INVESTIGATIVE DIRECTORATE AND THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE.

[CASADIEGO] I DO NOT KNOW IF REPRESENTATIVES FROM THE CRIMINAL INVESTIGATIVE DIRECTORATE HAVE TRAVELED THERE. WE SENT POLICE INSPECTORS, JUDGES, AND WE KNOW THAT THE COMMANDERS OF THE THREE NEIGHBORING DEPARTMENTS WILL ALSO BE THERE.

[REPORTER] HOW WAS THE OPERATION PLANNED, AND HAS THE PRESIDENT BEEN INFORMED?

[CASADIEGO] AS I SAID, THIS OPERATION IS THE RESULT OF ARDUOUS WORK BY THE NATIONAL POLICE. IT WAS A VERY IMPORTANT MISSION. FOR A LONG TIME WE HAVE BEEN CARRYING OUT THESE TYPES OF OPERATIONS. WE ARE STILL DOING THIS TYPE OF WORK AND WILL CONTINUE TO DO SO. [CONTINUED]

TST2-MUC4-0043

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN)] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE FMLN WILL MAINTAIN THESE UNILATERAL ACTIONS DURING A SUFFICIENT AND MODERATE PERIOD OF TIME TO ALLOW THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES TO CARRY OUT THE CORRESPONDING ACTIONS THAT WILL CONTRIBUTE TO CREATING A SERIOUS CLIMATE FOR NEGOTIATIONS. IN THIS SENSE, WE DEMAND THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES TO:

1. IMMEDIATELY CEASE REPRESSION, STOP ASSASSINATIONS, ARRESTS, USE OF TORTURE ON POLITICAL PRISONERS, SECURITY CORPS ACTIONS AGAINST DEMONSTRATIONS, STRIKES, AND OTHER PEOPLE'S ACTIVITIES. WE ALSO DEMAND THE LIFTING OF THE SIEGE AGAINST THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY, LABOR UNION OFFICES, AND OFFICES OF OTHER PEOPLE'S ORGANIZATIONS, AND AN END TO SEARCHES AGAINST THESE ORGANIZATIONS.

2. PERMIT THE IMMEDIATE REPATRIATION OF ALL REFUGEES, WITH NO RESTRICTIONS, TO THE PLACES THEY SELECT. TO LIFT THE SIEGE AND RESTRICTIONS ON THE MOVEMENT OF PEOPLE AT THE ALREADY ESTABLISHED RESETTLEMENTS, AND ON THE CONFLICT AREAS WHERE THE ARMY PREVENTS THE ARRIVAL OF SUPPLIES.

3. CEASE THE ATTACKS ON THE FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION IN THE FORM OF ASSASSINATIONS, INTIMIDATION, AND DISMISSAL OF NEWSMEN, AND PRESSURE ON THE MEDIA IN GENERAL.

4. SUSPEND CONSCRIPTION, WHICH IS CARRIED OUT ONLY AMONG THE LOW INCOME SECTORS OF THE POPULATION.

5. STOP USING LAND MINES AND BOOBY TRAPS, WHICH HAVE CAUSED HUNDREDS OF CASUALTIES ATTRIBUTED TO THE FMLN. STOP BOMBING CIVILIAN TARGETS AND INHABITED AREAS.

THE FMLN, IN TURN, AGREES TO STOP ACTIONS THAT DIRECTLY AFFECT THE GOVERNMENT'S WAR ECONOMY AND IMBALANCE THE ARMY'S DEFENSIVE SYSTEM. THE FMLN AGREES TO STOP USING SUCH WEAPONS AS THE MINES THAT HAVE INFLICTED THOUSANDS OF CASUALTIES ON THE ARMY. SOME OF THESE ACTIONS HAVE AFFECTED THE POPULATION, EITHER DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLY. WE DEMAND THAT THE GOVERNMENT STOP USING REPRESSIVE MEASURES THAT DIRECTLY AFFECT THE POPULATION AND THEIR DEMOCRATIC RIGHTS. WE WILL NOT, HOWEVER, ACCEPT AS A GOVERNMENT GOODWILL GESTURE OUR WAR DISABLED LEAVING THE COUNTRY FOR MEDICAL TREATMENT, IF AND WHEN THIS DEPARTURE TAKES PLACE. WE REGARD THIS AS A BASIC HUMANITARIAN RIGHT SUBJECT TO INTERNATIONAL ACCORDS, SUCH AS THE GENEVA CONVENTION, SIGNED AND RATIFIED BY THE SALVADORAN STATE. THE FULFILLMENT OF THESE ACCORDS HAS BEEN DEMANDED FROM THE GOVERNMENT BY VARIOUS ORGANIZATIONS AND THE LATEST UN HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION RESOLUTION.

AS OF TODAY, WE WILL BE WATCHING THE ACTIONS OF THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES ON THE FIVE POINTS PROPOSED. WE INVITE THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES TO DEMONSTRATE TRUE WILLINGNESS FOR PEACE BY TAKING THE ACTIONS WE HAVE PROPOSED AND INITIATING A SERIOUS NEGOTIATING PROCESS TO END THE WAR.

FMLN GENERAL COMMAND.

EL SALVADOR, 7 SEPTEMBER 1989.

TST2-MUC4-0046

BOGOTA, 27 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [INTERVIEW WITH REPORTER ON THE SCENE BY STUDIO REPORTER] [TEXT] [REPORTER, IN PROGRESS] ... IF THE COLLEAGUES AT THE CENTRAL STUDIO HAVE ANY QUESTIONS FOR THE BOGOTA ELECTRICAL ENERGY INSTITUTE EMPLOYEE WHO WAS AT THE SITE OF THE INCIDENT. WE ARE OBSERVING A TERRIBLE SCENE OF DESOLATION AND DEATH BECAUSE ALL THE PASSANGERS GOING TO CALI, VALLE DEL CAUCA DEPARTMENT, DIED. THERE IS NO SINGLE SURVIVOR ACCORDING TO NATIONAL POLICE REPORTS. THEY ARE AWAITING CRIMINAL INSTRUCTION JUDGES. HOWEVER, THE ELECTRICITY COMPANY WORKER MAY ANSWER QUESTIONS POSED BY STUDIO REPORTERS. LATER ON WE WILL HAVE MORE OFFICIAL INFORMATION.

[STUDIO REPORTER] CAN YOU CONFIRM THE ARRIVAL OF THE POLICE'S BOMB SQUAD? AUTHORITIES FEAR THE CRASH MAY HAVE BEEN CAUSED BY AN EXPLOSION RATHER THAN AN ACCIDENT INSIDE THE AIRPLANE.

[REPORTER] THE F-2 JUDICIAL POLICE AND CRIMINAL STATISTICS EXPERTS ARE HERE. THEY FEEL THAT THE ACCIDENT MAY HAVE BEEN CAUSED BY A TERRORIST ACTION. THE REMARK WAS MADE BASED ON WITNESS ACCOUNTS. THEY NOTED THAT THIS MAY HAVE BEEN A TERRORIST ATTACK BECAUSE AIRPLANES DO NOT HAVE THIS KIND OF ACCIDENT UNLESS THERE IS AN EXPLOSION, SOMETHING THAT HAS VERY SERIOUS CONSEQUENCES. ACCORDING TO REPORTS BY THE NATIONAL POLICE F-2 EXPERTS, THE AIRPLANE BROKE INTO SIX PIECES. IT IS COMPLETELY DESTROYED, WHICH IS WHY THE 106 PASSENGERS ABOARD ARE STREWN ACROSS AN AREA 6-8 KM WIDE.

ACCESS TO THE AIRPLANE'S REMAINS IS DIFFICULT BECAUSE THIS IS A MOUNTAINOUS REGION. THE CASQUITO [WORD INDISTINCT] IS THROUGH THE ROAD THAT GOES FROM BOSA, CUNDINAMARCA DEPARTMENT, TO THE SCHOOL [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED]. AUTHORITIES SAY THAT THIS AREA IS LOCATED VERY CLOSE TO SLUICE NUMBER 3, MUNA 3, WHICH FEEDS WATER TO THE DAM. THE SITUATION IS VERY DIFFICULT AND DRAMATIC. RIGHT NOW, EXPERTS ARE COLLECTING SAMPLES AND TRYING FIND ALL THEY CAN TO LEARN FOR SURE IF THIS WAS A TERRORIST ACTION OR A SERIOUS ACCIDENT CAUSED BY A FLAW IN THE MECHANICAL SYSTEM OF THE HK-1803 AIRPLANE.

TST2-MUC4-0047

BOGOTA, 29 OCT 89 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT HAS EXTRADITED TO THE UNITED STATES FIVE [NUMBER AS RECEIVED] INDIVIDUALS WITHIN THE LAST FEW HOURS, INCLUDING JOSE RAFAEL AVELLO SILVA, ALSO KNOWN AS EL MONO AVELLO. THE AUTHORITIES REPORTED THAT AVELLO IS WANTED BY A U.S. COURT FOR COMMITING MANY CRIMES, INCLUDING CONSPIRACY AND COMPLICITY IN CRIMES AGAINST THE U.S. ECONOMY.

THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS REOPENED THE PROCESS OF EXTRADITION VIA ADMINISTRATIVE CHANNELS AFTER THE LAW ON EXTRADITIONS WAS STRUCK DOWN BY THE SUPREME COURT.

THE AUTHORITIES REPORTED THAT EL MONO AVELLO, WHO IS THE LEADING FIGURE IN THE SO-CALLED MEDELLIN CARTEL, WAS EXTRADITED THIS MORNING AT 0530. HE LEFT ABOARD A U.S. DRUG ENFORCEMENT ADMINISTRATION PLANE.

THE FOLLOWING ARE AWAITING EXTRADITION: GUILLERMO BONO DELGADO; MANUEL JULIAN PALMA; VICTOR EDUARDO VERA MOSQUERA; COMMERCIAL PILOT RICARDO DE LA CUESTA MARQUEZ; ROBERT JAMES SOKOLOWSKY SALAK; NELSON CUEVAS RAMIREZ; AND EVARISTO PORRAS.

THE COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES ALSO REPORTED THAT EMILIO REYNOSA AGUILAR WAS EXPELLED YESTERDAY FROM THE COUNTRY. HE IS WANTED BY THE PERUVIAN COURTS, AND THERE WAS ALSO A REQUEST FOR HIS EXTRADITION. HOWEVER, THE COLOMBIAN AND PERUVIAN GOVERNMENTS AGREED THAT IT WAS BEST TO EXPEL REYNOSA AGUILAR FROM COLOMBIA. HE IS WANTED BY TWO LIMA COURTS FOR HELPING PRISONERS ESCAPE AND FOR OTHER CRIMES.

ON 6 SEPTEMBER, PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS EXTRADITED ECONOMIST EDUARDO MARTINEZ ROMERO TO A COURT IN ATLANTA, GEORGIA. THE U.S. AUTHORITIES CHARGED MARTINEZ ROMERO WITH LAUNDERING APPROXIMATELY $1.2 BILLION FROM THE SALE OF ILLEGAL DRUGS.

LATER, AT 0330 ON 14 SEPTEMBER, THE FOLLOWING WERE EXTRADITED: ANA ELENA BEATRIZ RODRIGUEZ TAMAYO, EDUARDO PELAEZ ROLDAN, AND ITALIAN CITIZEN ROBERTO VICTOR CARLINI AROCA.

THE GOVERNMENT OF VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS DECIDED TO CARRY OUT ADMINISTRATIVE EXTRADITIONS ON 18 AUGUST, FOLLOWING THE ASSASSINATIONS OF COLONEL WALDEMAR FRANKLIN QUINTERO, COMMANDER OF THE ANTIOQUIA POLICE, AND LUIS CARLOS GALAN, A SENATOR AND PRESIDENTIAL HOPEFUL FOR THE LIBERAL PARTY.

TST2-MUC4-0048

SAN SALVADOR, 19 APR 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN PRESIDENT-ELECT ALFREDO CRISTIANI CONDEMNED THE TERRORIST KILLING OF ATTORNEY GENERAL ROBERTO GARCIA ALVARADO AND ACCUSED THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) OF THE CRIME.

LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY PRESIDENT RICARDO VALDIVIESO AND VICE PRESIDENT-ELECT FRANCISCO MERINO ALSO DECLARED THAT THE DEATH OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL WAS CAUSED BY WHAT VALDIVIESO TERMED THE GUERRILLAS' "IRRATIONAL VIOLENCE."

GARCIA ALVARADO, 56, WAS KILLED WHEN A BOMB PLACED BY URBAN GUERRILLAS ON HIS VEHICLE EXPLODED AS IT CAME TO A HALT AT AN INTERSECTION IN DOWNTOWN SAN SALVADOR.

"WE HAVE TO CONDEMN THIS INCIDENT, IT IS A GUERRILLA ACT," ALFREDO CRISTIANI, NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) PRESIDENT-ELECT, WHO WILL REPLACE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRAT JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE ON 1 JUNE, STATED.

CRISTIANI SAID THAT "THESE ARE THE RISKS FACED BY SOMEONE WHO ENFORCES THE LAW." HE NOTED THAT "THE GUERRILLAS' IRRATIONAL ATTITUDE MAKES IT INCREASINGLY DIFFICULT TO BELIEVE THEY WANT PEACE."

ACCORDING TO CRISTIANI, THE ATTACK TOOK PLACE BECAUSE ATTORNEY GENERAL GARCIA ALVARADO WARNED THAT "HE WOULD TAKE MEASURES AGAINST URBAN TERRORISTS."

VICE PRESIDENT-ELECT FRANCISCO MERINO SAID THAT WHEN THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S CAR STOPPED AT A LIGHT ON A STREET IN DOWNTOWN SAN SALVADOR, AN INDIVIDUAL PLACED A BOMB ON THE ROOF OF THE ARMORED VEHICLE.

"THE DRIVER TOLD THE ATTORNEY GENERAL ABOUT THE BOMB. THE VEHICLE SWERVED AND THE BOMB EXPLODED, CAUSING THE TOP OF THE VEHICLE TO COLLAPSE ON THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S HEAD," MERINO STATED.

GUERRILLAS ATTACKED MERINO'S HOME IN SAN SALVADOR 5 DAYS AGO WITH EXPLOSIVES. THERE WERE SEVEN CHILDREN, INCLUDING FOUR OF THE VICE PRESIDENT'S CHILDREN, IN THE HOME AT THE TIME. A 15-YEAR-OLD NIECE OF MERINO'S WAS INJURED.

"THESE INCIDENTS," CRISTIANI SAID, "FRANKLY CAUSE US TO BECOME MORE AWARE OF THE FACT THAT WE MUST NOT PERMIT TERRORIST ACTIONS TO OCCUR IN EL SALVADOR."

THE PRESIDENT-ELECT RULED OUT THE POSSIBILITY THAT THESE ATTACKS "WILL PREVENT THE INAUGURAL CEREMONY FROM TAKING PLACE."

"I AM CERTAIN THAT THE INAUGURATION WILL BE ON 1 JUNE. WE WILL NOT JUMP OVERBOARD OR MAKE A RUN FOR IT. WE KNOW WHAT WE ARE UP AGAINST AND WILL GO ON," HE STATED.

CRISTIANI SAID THE GUERRILLA ATTACKS ARE INTENDED TO PROMPT A GOVERNMENT AND MILITARY REACTION SO THE FMLN CAN "EXPLOIT IT" ABROAD TO "POLITICALLY ISOLATE THE NEW GOVERNMENT."

RICARDO VALDIVIESO, PRESIDENT OF THE LEGISLATIVE ASSSEMBLY AND AN ARENA LEADER, SAID THE FMLN AND ITS "FRONT" GROUPS ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE "IRRATIONAL VIOLENCE THAT KILLED ATTORNEY GENERAL GARCIA."

VALDIVIESO SAID THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY WILL APPROVE DRASTIC LAWS TO "HALT THE WAVE OF VIOLENCE." HE SAID THE ATTORNEY GENERAL "WAS APOLITICAL, WORKED FOR JUSTICE, AND DID NOT DESERVE TO DIE LIKE THAT."

ACCORDING TO THE POLICE AND GARCIA ALVARADO'S DRIVER, WHO ESCAPED UNSCATHED, THE ATTORNEY GENERAL WAS TRAVELING WITH TWO BODYGUARDS. ONE OF THEM WAS INJURED.

THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S BODY WAS DESTROYED BY THE BOMB THAT EXPLODED OVER HIS HEAD.

NO GROUP HAS CLAIMED CREDIT FOR THE ATTACK YET, BUT POLICE SOURCES CLAIM IT "IS CHARACTERISTIC OF THE FMLN URBAN COMMANDOS."

THE SAME SOURCES CONFIRMED THAT GARCIA ALVARADO HAD BEEN THREATENED ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS BY SALVADORAN URBAN GUERRILLAS.

MOMENTS AFTER THE ATTACK, ARMY AND POLICE UNITS CORDONED OFF THE AREA AND BEGAN AN ALL-OUT MILITARY OPERATION TO FIND THOSE RESPONSIBLE.

GARCIA ALVARADO, FATHER OF SIX, WAS APPOINTED ATTORNEY GENERAL ON 23 DECEMBER 1988. HE WAS CONSIDERED TO BE CLOSELY LINKED TO ARENA. ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS, HOWEVER, HE SAID HE DID NOT REPRESENT ANY PARTY AND WAS CARRYING OUT HIS JOB "IMPARTIALLY AND WITH THE INTENTION OF ENFORCING THE COUNTRY'S LAWS."

TST2-MUC4-0052

TEL AVIV (ISRAEL), 27 AUG 89 (IDF RADIO) -- [EXCERPTS] EDUCATION MINISTER YITZHAQ NAVON TODAY DEMANDED IN THE CABINET SESSION THAT THE GOVERNMENT RETURN ALL ISRAELIS WHO ILLEGALLY PROVIDE MILITARY TRAINING ABROAD. THE GOVERNMENT MUST PUT AN END TO THE DISGRACE SOME ISRAELIS CAUSE TO ALL OF US. HERE IS A REPORT BY OUR POLITICAL CORRESPONDENT NATAN GUTMAN:

[BEGIN RECORDING] THE WEEKLY CABINET SESSION DEALT WITH THE COLOMBIA ISSUE ONLY BRIEFLY. DEFENSE MINISTER YITZHAQ RABIN BRIEFLY REFERRED TO THE ISSUE MAINLY BECAUSE HE WAS ASKED BY OTHER MINISTERS TO DO SO. DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER YITZHAQ NAVON SAID THAT THE GOVERNMENT MUST PUT AN END TO THE DISGRACE CAUSED BY SOME ISRAELIS. DEFENSE MINISTER RABIN MERELY STATED THAT THE WHOLE ISSUE OF THE INVOLVEMENT OF ISRAELIS IN COLOMBIA IS UNDER INVESTIGATION. DEFENSE ELEMENTS MADE CLEAR AT THE MEETING THAT SINCE 1986 THERE HAS BEEN A NEED TO ACQUIRE A SPECIFIC PERMIT FOR ANY SECURITY ACTIVITY BY AN ISRAELI BODY ABROAD. IT WAS FURTHER MADE CLEAR THAT THE HOD HAHANIT [SPEARHEAD] COMPANY DID NOT HAVE SUCH A PERMIT, AND HAS BEEN WARNED NOT TO OPERATE IN COLOMBIA.

AT THE CONCLUSION OF THE SESSION, CABINET SECRETARY ELYAQIM RUBINSTEIN SAID THAT THE ISRAELI GOVERNMENT DISASSOCIATES ITSELF FROM ANY SUCH ACTIVITY. IT WAS FURTHER STRESSED THAT ISRAEL CONSIDERS THE STRUGGLE AGAINST THE PLAGUE OF INTERNATIONAL DRUGS A VERY IMPORTANT QUEST.

AS FOR THE SITUATION IN THE TERRITORIES, THE DEFENSE MINISTER EXPLAINED THAT THE FEELING OF A DEADLOCKED POLITICAL PROCESS LEADS TO AN ESCALATION OF THE INTIFADAH [UPRISING]. IT WAS STRESSED THAT THE MASKED MEN CREATE A REAL LEGAL PROBLEM. MINISTER SCIAKI SUGGESTED THAT ORDERS BE ISSUED TO ALLOW SHOOTING AT MASKED MEN IF SUSPICIONS WARRANT. [END RECORDING]

FINANCE MINISTER SHIM'ON PERES' DRAFT LAW ON STREAMLINING BUREAUCRACY WAS APPROVED TODAY IN THE CABINET BY A LARGE MAJORITY OF 14 TO 2. SHARP EXCHANGES BETWEEN THE FINANCE MINISTER AND SOME LIKUD MINISTERS TOOK PLACE. OUR ECONOMIC CORRESPONDENT YARON KULAS REPORTS:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [KULAS] THE DEBATE ON THE DRAFT LAW ON SLASHING BUREAUCRACY REOPENED THE LOUD DISAGREEMENT BETWEEN THE FINANCE MINISTER AND LIKUD MINISTERS MOSHE NISIM, RONI MILO, AND EHUD OLMERT. ONLY TWO MINISTERS OBJECTED TO THE PROPOSAL: 'EZER WEIZMAN, WHO SAID THAT THE TRUE ECONOMIC PROBLEM TODAY IS THE INTIFADAH; AND ECOLOGY AND ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION MINISTER RONI MILO. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

TEN MINISTERS ABSTAINED FROM VOTING. THE PLAN WAS ENDORSED, HOWEVER, BY A LARGE MAJORITY. THE KNESSET WILL CONVENE TO RATIFY THE DRAFT LAW EARLY NEXT WEEK. [END RECORDING]

TST2-MUC4-0054

SAN SALVADOR, 8 JAN 90 -- [TEXT] THE RECTOR OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY [UCA], FATHER MIGUEL FRANCISCO ESTRADA, HAS DESCRIBED THE GOVERNMENT'S REPORT THAT ARMED FORCES ELEMENTS ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE KILLING OF SIX UCA PRIESTS AS MOST IMPORTANT, ALTHOUGH HE ALSO NOTED THAT THE REPORT IS INCOMPLETE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ESTRADA] I BELIEVE IT IS INCOMPLETE BECAUSE WE DO NOT YET KNOW WHO COMMITTED THE CRIMES. WE ONLY KNOW THAT THEY BELONG TO AN INSTITUTION, AND THIS OF COURSE IS ONLY PARTIAL INFORMATION.

[REPORTER] DID YOU KNOW THAT THE GOVERNMENT WAS GOING TO MAKE THIS ANNOUNCEMENT LAST NIGHT, OR WAS IT A SURPRISE?

[ESTRADA] I THINK IT WAS A SURPRISE BECAUSE WE HAD BEEN IN TOUCH WITH THE PRESIDENT AND WITH THE CRIME COMMISSION, WHICH IS THE ONE CARRYING OUT THE INVESTIGATIONS ON ORDERS FROM THE PRESIDENT AND THE GOVERNMENT. THEY PROMISED US THAT IF WE WERE TO COOPERATE BY PROVIDING INFORMATION, THEY WOULD DO EVERYTHING POSSIBLE TO RESOLVE THE PROBLEM AND CARRY OUT THE INVESTIGATIONS.

AT THAT POINT I WAS SKEPTICAL, BECAUSE THE PERSONS WHO HAVE TESTIFIED HAVE ACCUSED THE ARMED FORCES, AND I HAD NEVER SEEN A SALVADORAN PRESIDENT OR THE ARMED FORCES MAKING A SERIOUS EFFORT TO CLEAN UP ITS IMAGE AND CARRY OUT INVESTIGTIONS TO PUT MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES IN PRISON. I WAS SKEPTICAL. I HAD NEVER SEEN THAT HAPPEN, BUT FACTS SHOW THAT I WAS MISTAKEN. [END RECORDING]

FATHER ESTRADA HAS ADMITTED THAT THERE HAS BEEN INTERNATIONAL PRESSURE TO HAVE THIS CASE INVESTIGATED, BUT HE OPTIMISTICALLY BELIEVES THAT THE DECISION TO INVESTIGATE HAS BEEN ADOPTED ALSO FOR THE SAKE OF THE PRESTIGE OF THE ARMED FORCES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ESTRADA] I AM INCLINED TO BELIEVE THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE ACTING NOT ONLY AS A RESULT OF PRESSURE, BUT ALSO BECAUSE THEY COULD BE DENIED MILITARY OR ECONOMIC AID. I BELIEVE THAT A CRIME SUCH AS THE ONE BEING INVESTIGATED GOES AGAINST THE VERY ESSENCE OF THE ARMED FORCES, WHICH EXISTS TO PROTECT THE CITIZENS, NOT TO HARM THEM. [END RECORDING]

FATHER ESTRADA SAID HE TRUSTS IN THE MORAL STRENGTH OF PRESIDENT CRISTIANI TO SEE THIS CASE THROUGH TO THE END. HE CAUTIONED, HOWEVER, THAT SO FAR NOTHING NEW HAS BEEN SAID AND THAT A LISTING OF THE PEOPLE INVOLVED AND A JUST SENTENCE WOULD BE NEWS.

TST2-MUC4-0055

LIMA, 5 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] IN LIMA TODAY, UNOFFICIAL SOURCES REPORTED THAT AT LEAST 2,500 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN DETAINED BY THE PERUVIAN POLICE IN RAIDS CARRIED OUT IN SEARCH OF HECTOR DELGADO PARKER, A LOCAL TELEVISION IMPRESARIO, AND HIS KIDNAPPERS.

THE POLICE RAIDS BEGAN SHORTLY AFTER THE KIDNAPPING OF DELGADO PARKER, A FORMER ADVISER TO PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA AND ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT TELEVISION IMPRESARIO. DELGADO PARKER WAS KIDNAPPED IN DOWNTOWN LIMA WEDNESDAY [4 OCTOBER] BY A COMMANDO OF THE PRO-CHE GUEVARA GROUP TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MRTA).

AS A RESULT OF THE TERRORIST ACTION, DELGADO'S DRIVER WAS KILLED, AND DELGADO'S BODYGUARD WAS SERIOUSLY WOUNDED, WHILE DELGADO HIMSELF WAS VIOLENTLY ABDUCTED BY THE MRTA ACTIVISTS.

ACCORDING TO THE SOURCES, THE RAIDS CARRIED OUT BY THE POLICE, WHO DETAIN PEOPLE WITHOUT IDENTIFICATION PAPERS AND SUSPECTS AFTER CHECKING ON PEDESTRIANS AND VEHICLES, TOOK PLACE ON LIMA'S ACCESS ROADS AS WELL AS IN SOME SUBURBAN AREAS OF THIS CITY AND EVEN IN DOWNTOWN LIMA.

THE PERUVIAN NATIONAL POLICE HAVE REPORTED THAT SOME 2,000 AGENTS OF THE ANTITERRORIST DIRECTORATE (DIRCOTE) AND THE KIDNAPPING DIVISION ARE PARTICIPATING IN THE SEARCH OPERATIONS ORDERED BY PRESIDENT GARCIA.

IN TELEPHONE CALLS TO LIMA MEDIA, THE MRTA HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE KIDPANAPPING OF HECTOR DELGADO PARKER. TELEVISION "CHANNEL 5," OF WHICH THE KIDNAPPED BUSINESSMAN IS PART OWNER, WAS AMONG THE MEDIA MRTA CALLED.

TST2-MUC4-0056

SAN SALVADOR, 19 MAR 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [REPORT] [OSCAR VENANCIO RAMIREZ] [TEXT] DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL EUGENIO VIDES CASANOVA HAS VISITED LA ALAMEDA ROOSEVELT TO OBSERVE THE VOTING PROCESS. HE ALSO SAID AN INVESTIGATION WILL BE CONDUCTED INTO THE MURDERS OF THREE REPORTERS, TWO SALVADORANS AND A NETHERLANDER. THERE WILL ALSO BE AN INVESTIGATION INTO THE WOUNDING OF A SALVADORAN REPORTER AND A CBS REPORTER.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [VIDES] THIS IS THE SAME QUESTION ASKED [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THE ELECTION PROCESS IS PROCEEDING NORMALLY IN ALL MUNICIPALITIES EXCEPT SEVEN. CLASHES WERE REPORTED IN TWO MUNICIPALITIES AND THE ELECTIONS WERE SUSPENDED IN TWO OTHERS. ONE OF THEM IS EL SAUCE, WITH WHICH COMMUNICATIONS HAVE BEEN CUT OFF. THE OTHER IS SANTA ELENA, WHERE A CLASH OCCURRED. I THINK PEOPLE WILL VOTE HERE LATER. NO VOTING IS TAKING PLACE IN FOUR OTHER MUNICIPALITIES.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[VIDES] I HAVE NO OTHER INFORMATION. AT THE TIME I DEPARTED, I SENT FOR REPORTS FROM THE HOSPITAL. I WAS TOLD HE DIED, BUT WE HAVE TO GATHER MORE DATA ON HOW THE INCIDENT HAPPENED.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[VIDES] WE HAVE ALWAYS HELD REPORTERS IN THE HIGHEST REGARD. ALL ARMED FORCES MEMBERS HAVE BEEN INFORMED OF THIS. BUT PROBLEMS ARISE WHEN SOME PEOPLE IGNORE CHECKPOINTS AND THE GUARDS TRY TO STOP THEM. I HEREBY APPEAL TO PEOPLE TO OBEY CHECKPOINTS. WE ARE THE FIRST TO REGRET THESE INCIDENTS. WE HAVE VERY GOOD AND CLOSE RELATIONS WITH THE MEDIA AND KNOW [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] WILL THIS HAVE REPERCUSSIONS?

[VIDES] SERIOUS REPERCUSSIONS WILL CERTAINLY OCCUR, BUT YOU CAN REST ASSURED THAT WHAT HAPPENED WAS UNINTENTIONAL. SOME PEOPLE IGNORED THE ORDER TO STOP. THE PEOPLE SHOULD BE MORE ALERT AND AWARE OF THE SITUATION BECAUSE OF THE REBELS' ATTACKS. [END RECORDING]

TST2-MUC4-0057

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [STATEMENT] [FMLN] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] A. WE HEREBY VOICE OUR WILLINGNESS THAT THERE BE AN IMMEDIATE IN SITU CEASE-FIRE WITH INTERNATIONAL SUPERVISION AND AN OVERALL AND DEFINITIVE SIMULTANEOUS NEGOTIATION LEADING TO A NATIONAL CONSENSUS BASED ON DEMOCRATIZATION, DEMILITARIZATION OF SOCIETY, AND RESPECT FOR THE RIGHTS OF SALVADORANS.

B. IN ORDER TO HOLD GOOD NEGOTIATIONS, WE FEEL IT IS NECESSARY TO ESTABLISH IMMEDIATE GUARANTEES FOR THE RESPECT OF HUMAN RIGHTS, DEMOCRATIC FREEDOMS, AND POLITICAL AND SOCIAL GROUPS THROUGH:

1. LIFTING OF THE STATE OF SIEGE AND REPEAL OF THE LAW ON REFO THE PENAL CODES, ALSO KNOWN AS THE ANTITERRORIST LAW THAT WAS RECENTLY APPROVED BY THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY.

2. RELEASE OF ALL POLITICAL PRISONERS.

3. ALLOWED DEPARTURE OF FMLN WAR DISABLED AND MEDICAL TREATMEN FMLN WOUNDED.

4. IMMEDIATE DISMISSAL OF THE FOLLOWING COMMANDERS AND OFFICER COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE JOINTS CHIEFS OF STAFF, FOR HIS RESPONSIBILITY IN DECISIONS MADE BY THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND TO CARRY OUT INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION AND THE ASSASSINATION OF THE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS; GENERAL RAFAEL BUSTILLOS, GENERAL RAFAEL ANTONIO VILLAMARIONA, AND LIEUTENANT COLONEL JUAN ANTONIO MARTINEZ VARELA, COMMANDER AND EXECUTIVE OFFICERS OF THE AIR FORCE, FOR THEIR DIRECT RESPONSIBILITY IN THE BOMBINGS OF THE CIVILIAN POPULATION; COLONEL ORLANDO ZEPEDA, DEPUTY DEFENSE MINISTER, FOR HAVING SIGNED THE ORDER TO ASSASSINATE THE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS; COLONEL HERIBERTO HERNANDEZ, DIRECTOR OF THE TREASURY POLICE, WHICH IS THE CORPS THAT CARRIED OUT THE MURDERS; AND CAPTAIN ALFONSO CHAVEZ GARCIA, WHO WAS THE DIRECT PERPETRATOR OF THESE MURDERS. ALL OF THESE DISMISSALS ARE NEEDED FOR THE CREDIBILITY AND EFFECTIVENESS OF THE DECISION TO ESTABLISH GUARANTEES FOR THE RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS AND AS A FIRST STEP IN THE PURGE OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES, WHICH IS NECESSARY FOR THE DISMANTLING OF THE BLOODY MILITARY DICTATORSHIP OF THE PAST 60 YEARS.

5. THE IN SITU VERIFICATION OF THE RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS MUST BE CARRIED OUT BY THE INTER-AMERICAN HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION AND THE UN WORK TEAM ON THE FORCED DISAPPEARANCES.

C. WE THINK IT IS INDISPENSABLE TO REORGANIZE THE NEGOTIATING TABLE TO ENSURE THAT OPPOSITION POLITICAL PARTIES AND SOCIAL GROUPS ARE ABLE TO FULLY PARTICIPATE ALONG WITH THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN. THIS WILL ASSURE A NATIONAL CONSENSUS SOLUTION.

MESSRS PRESIDENTS: THE SCOPE OF WAR IN OUR COUNTRY DEMANDS REALISTIC VIEWPOINTS, VIABLE AND URGENT SOLUTIONS. YOU CAN CONTRIBUTE SO THAT THE NEGOTIATIONS WILL PREVAIL OVER WAR AND THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEACE PROCESS WILL YIELD SPECIFIC RESULTS.

WE REITERATE OUR APPRECIATION TO YOUR CONTRIBUTIONS,

THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND, EL SALVADOR, 8 DECEMBER 1989.

TST2-MUC4-0059

BOGOTA, 25 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE POLICE HAVE REPORTED THAT THREE TERRORIST ATTACKS HERE IN BOGOTA AND IN THE CARIBBEAN PORT OF CARTAGENA LEFT TWO DEAD AND THREE INJURED.

THE MOST SERIOUS INCIDENT TOOK PLACE AT THE HISTORICAL BEACH RESORT WHERE A BOMB EXPLODED ON THE 6TH FLOOR OF THE HILTON HOTEL KILLING TWO PEOPLE AND SERIOUSLY INJURING ANOTHER.

ALMOST SIMULTANEOUSLY ANOTHER BOMB EXPLODED IN FRONT OF A BANK IN ANOTHER PART OF CARTAGENA, PARTIALLY DESTROYING THE BUILDING AND INJURING A GUARD AND A PASSERBY.

MEANWHILE, IN BOGOTA, A BOMB EXPLODED AT A BRANCH OF THE CITY'S ELECTRIC ENERGY ENTERPRISE IN THE SUBURB OF QUIRIGUA. THE COMPANY'S OFFICES WERE DESTROYED, AND APPROXIMATELY 50 NEIGHBORING RESIDENCES WERE DAMAGED BY THE BLAST.

ACCORDING TO A GUARD AT THE COMPANY, WHO ESCAPED UNHURT, TWO INDIVIDUALS WHO WERE PASSING BY THE BUILDING PLACED THE EXPLOSIVES AND FLED. THE GUARD SAID HE BARELY HAD TIME TO GET AWAY FROM THE BOMB BEFORE IT WENT OFF.

GUESTS AT THE HOTEL, WHERE PRACTICALLY ALL THE WINDOWS WERE DESTROYED, HAD TO BE EVACUATED TO OTHER LODGINGS.

CARTAGENA HAD UP TO NOW ESCAPED THE WAVE OF DYNAMITE ATTACKS THAT HAVE BEEN TAKING PLACE IN THE COUNTRY'S LARGE CITIES FOR THE PAST SEVERAL WEEKS. AUTHORITIES ATTRIBUTE THE ATTACKS TO DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

TST2-MUC4-0060

SANTIAGO, 28 FEB 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] SOME 9,000 CARABINEROS MEMBERS WILL PARTICIPATE IN A SPECIAL POLICE PLAN BEFORE, DURING, AND AFTER THE OFFICIAL TRANSFER OF POWER CEREMONIES IN OUR COUNTRY. THIS WAS REPORTED BY GENERAL ALFREDO NUNEZ ALLENDE, THE CARABINEROS ORDER AND SECURITY DIRECTOR, WHO ALSO DESCRIBED THE LATEST TERRORIST ATTACKS AS ISOLATED EVENTS WHICH ARE UNDER CONTROL.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [NUNEZ ALLENDE] WE WILL BE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE SECURITY OF THE POPULATION AND OF THE FOREIGN GUESTS IN KEEPING WITH OUR DUTY REQUIREMENTS. AS FOR THE RECENT ATTACKS, I MUST SAY THEY ARE REGRETTABLE AND I WISH THEY HAD NOT TAKEN PLACE, HOWEVER, THIS KIND OF ACTION HAS BEEN TAKEN INTO CONSIDERATION IN ALL OUR PLANS. WE HAVE ADOPTED ALL THE MEASURES WE THINK ARE APPROPRIATE IN CASE THIS KIND OF ACTIVITY TAKES PLACE. WE WILL ALSO TRY TO PREVENT THIS KIND OF ACTION DURING THE PRESIDENTIAL INAUGURATION SO THAT PEOPLE UNDER OUR PROTECTION WILL NOT BE AFFECTED.

[UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] WHY HAS TERRORIST ACTIVITY INCREASED IN THE PAST FEW DAYS?

[NUNEZ ALLENDE] I THINK THAT THIS IS NORMAL WITHIN THE CURRENT PROCESS, IT IS NOT A SPECIFIC FACTOR OR OBJECTIVE. THE ATTACKS ARE IN KEEPING WITH WHAT WE HAVE BEEN OBSERVING IN THE PAST FEW MONTHS. [END RECORDING]

THE CARABINEROS ORDER AND SECURITY CHIEF ALSO REPORTED THAT REINFORCEMENTS WILL BE BROUGHT IN TO SANTIAGO FROM OTHER PARTS OF THE COUNTRY, AND HE ADDED THAT THE DISSOLUTION OF THE NATIONAL INTELLIGENCE CENTER WILL NOT AFFECT THE NORMAL WORK OF THE CARABINEROS. HE ALSO SAID THAT IN FACE OF THE RECENT TERRORIST ATTACKS, THE APPROPRIATE MEASURES HAVE BEEN ADOPTED. AS FAR AS HE KNEW, HE SAID, THE ARMY WILL NOT PARTICIPATE IN ESTABLISHING ORDER AND SECURITY DURING THE TRANSFER OF POWER CEREMONY; THIS WILL BE EXCLUSIVE RESPONSIBILITY OF CHILEAN CARABINEROS.

AS FOR THE RECENT TERRORIST ATTACKS, HE SAID THERE IS NO EVIDENCE THAT THEY ARE PART OF A PLAN, ALTHOUGH HE ADMITTED THAT EXTREMIST ACTIVITY HAS INCREASED LATELY. HOWEVER, SUCH ACTIONS ARE WITHIN WHAT WAS EXPECTED. HE SAID THAT THE SECURITY PERSONNEL THAT WILL BE BROUGHT IN BY THE FOREIGN GUESTS HAVE ALREADY COORDINATED THEIR ACTIONS WITH THOSE OF CARABINEROS.

ON 5 MARCH, THE CARABINEROS WILL ANNOUNCE A DETAILED REPORT ON THE TRANSFER OF POWER CEREMONY AND ON THE MEASURES THAT WILL BE ADOPTED, ESPECIALLY REGARDING THE CIRCULATION OF CARS. THE SECURITY PLAN WILL BE SIMILAR TO THE ONE USED DURING POPE JOHN PAUL II'S VISIT TO CHILE.

TST2-MUC4-0061

BOGOTA, 16 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [TEXT] BOGOTA DID NOT ESCAPE THE TERRORIST ACTIONS OF ORGANIZED CRIMINALS ON FRIDAY NIGHT. TWO NATIONAL POLICE OFFICERS ASSIGNED TO THE DIJIN DIRECTORATE OF JUDIDIAL POLICE AND INVESTIGATIONS INTELLIGENCE CORPS WERE SHOT TO DEATH AS THEY PASSED BY ON A DIJIN MOTORCYCLE IN FRONT OF A HOME IN WESTERN BOGOTA.

THE CRIMINALS INTERCEPTED SERGEANT CARLOS JULIO BONILLA, WHO WAS DRIVING THE MOTORCYCLE, AND CORPORAL LUIS ALBERTO CHAVEZ, AS THEY ENTERED THE HOME. BOTH POLICEMEN DIED INSTANTLY. THE PAID ASSASINS FLED IN A MOTORCYCLE AND IN A VEHICLE THAT AWAITED THEM A FEW METERS AWAY, ACCORDING TO WITNESSES.

AUTHORITIES CARRIED OUT AN INTENSE OPERATION IN THE CITY TO LOCATE THE PERPETRATORS OF THIS LATEST CRIME.

ELSEWHERE, SEVERAL ARMED INDIVIDUALS SHOT REPEATEDLY AT THE NEWSPAPER EL SIGLO'S FACILITIES. THIS IS A NEW ACT OF HARASSMENT AGAINST THE MEDIA. EL SIGLO EDITOR HIPOLITO HINCAPIE WAS INTERVIEWED.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [HINCAPIE] THE INCIDENT TOOK PLACE AT 2120. INDIVIDUALS IN A BLUE RENAULT 12 FIRED SEVERAL TIMES AT THE FACILITIES. THE FACILITIES ARE AS THEY WERE PRIOR TO 2120, AND THE EMPLOYEES ARE WORKING AS USUAL. [END RECORDING]

THE DAMAGE WAS MINOR AND, FORTUNATELY, THERE WERE NO VICTIMS, THANKS TO THE PROMPT REACTION OF THE MARINES GUARDING THE FACILITIES.

TST2-MUC4-0064

BOGOTA, 11 SEP 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN JUSTICE MINISTER MONICA DE GREIFF BRIEFED PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO TODAY ON HER OFFICIAL VISIT TO THE UNITED STATES TO ASK FOR HELP IN THE FIGHT AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING.

THE 32-YEAR-OLD COLOMBIAN MINISTER RETURNED LAST NIGHT ABOARD A COMMERCIAL FLIGHT FROM WASHINGTON, WHERE SHE HAD TRAVELED ON 25 AUGUST WITH HER FAMILY AMID STRONG RUMORS THAT SHE WOULD NOT RETURN TO COLOMBIA AND THAT SHE WOULD RESIGN FROM THE POST SHE HAS HELD SINCE 16 JULY.

JUSTICE MINISTRY SOURCES SAID TODAY THAT DE GREIFF "IS MAINTAINING HER HEAVY AGENDA" AND ADDED THAT "NOTHING HAS BEEN SAID ABOUT HER LEAVING THE COUNTRY SOON."

THE RUMORS ABOUT HER IMMINENT RESIGNATION BECAUSE OF THE THREATS AGAINST HER AND HER FAMILY, INCLUDING HER 3-YEAR-OLD SON, MIGUEL JOSE, HAVE STOPPED WITH HER RETURN TO BOGOTA.

ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL SOURCES, MONICA DE GREIFF'S VISIT TO WASHINGTON WAS TO EXPLAIN "THE DIFFICULT SITUATION IN WHICH THE COLOMBIAN JUDICIAL BRANCH CARRIES OUT ITS DANGEROUS JOB."

PART OF THE $65 MILLION IN AID THE UNITED STATES HAS PROMISED TO COLOMBIA TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING HAS ALREADY ARRIVED IN THE COUNTRY. IT INCLUDES BULLETPROOF VESTS, ARMORED AUTOMOBILES, AND COMMUNICATION EQUIPMENT FOR JUDGES AND OFFICIALS OF THE JUDICIAL BRANCH.

THE COLOMBIAN JUSTICE MINISTER, WHO STUDIED LAW AT BOGOTA'S UNIVERSITY OF EL ROSARIO AND IN THE UNITED STATES, WILL MEET WITH THE PRESS TOMORROW AFTER HAVING PRESENTED HER REPORT ON HER TRIP.

SO FAR THIS YEAR THREE JUDGES WHO WERE IN CHARGE OF CASES AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKERS HAVE BEEN KILLED. IN THIS DECADE, 200 PEOPLE, INCLUDING JUDGES AND ATTORNEYS, HAVE BEEN KILLED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

TST2-MUC4-0068

GUATEMALA CITY, 19 AUG 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] FIRE DEPARTMENT SOURCES REPORTED TODAY THAT GUATEMALAN ARMY TROOPS KILLED NINE PEASANTS BY MISTAKE ON 17 AUGUST. THE SOLDIERS MISTOOK THE PEASANTS, WHO WERE CIVIL SELF-DEFENSE PATROL (PAC) MEMBERS, WITH A REBEL COLUMN.

ACCORDING TO THE SAME SOURCE, MILITARY OFFICIALS HAVE STATED THAT THE INCIDENT, WHERE THREE PEASANTS WERE ALSO WOUNDED, HAD BEEN A "TRAGIC MISTAKE."

THE INCIDENT TOOK PLACE WHEN NORTHEASTERN COBAN BASE TROOPS MISTOOK THE CIVILIAN PATROL FOR A REBEL COLUMN AND ATTACKED IT. THE ATTACK RESULTED IN 9 INDIAN PEASANTS KILLED AND 3 WOUNDED, INCLUDING A 17-YEAR-OLD.

ACCORDING TO THE INFORMATION SUPPLIED BY THE COBAN FIRE DEPARTMENT, THE INCIDENT TOOK PLACE WHEN A PAC PATROL WAS COMBING THE AREA FOR A REBEL COLUMN THAT HAD BEEN SEEN IN "LA PROVIDENCIA" FARMING COMMUNITY AREA.

THE CIVILIAN PATROL WAS RETURNING TO ITS COMMUNITY ON 17 AUGUST, WHEN THE ARMY TROOPS, WHO WERE ALSO SEARCHING FOR THE REBEL COLUMN, FIRED AT THEM BELIEVING THEY WERE PART OF A REBEL GROUP.

THE CIVILIAN PATROL UNIT, APPROXIMATELY 70 PERSONS, DID NOT FIRE BACK AT THE SOLDIERS. ACCORDING TO THE ACCOUNT GIVEN BY ONE OF THE SURVIVORS, THE CIVILIANS SHOUTED AND MADE SIGNS TO THE TROOPS UNTIL, FINALLY, THE SOLDIERS REALIZED THEIR ERROR. THE SOLDIERS, HOWEVER, REALIZED THEIR MISTAKE ONLY AFTER NINE CIVILIANS HAD BEEN KILLED.

GUATEMALAN DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL HECTOR ALEJANDRO GRAMAJO WAS QUERIED ABOUT THE INCIDENT. HE SAID IT WAS CAUSED BY "REGRETTABLE CONFUSION" AND THAT AN ARMY COMMAND STAFF COMMISSION HAD ALREADY BEEN SENT TO INVESTIGATE IT.

GRAMAJO SAID THE COMMISSION IS TO ESTABLISH HOW THE INCIDENT OCCURRED, BUT ADMITTED THAT INITIAL REPORTS INDICATE THAT THERE HAD BEEN CONFUSION BETWEEN ARMY AND PAC UNITS.

THE MILITARY CHIEF SAID: "THE INFORMATION WE HAVE UP TO NOW IS CONFUSING AS BOTH THE ARMY AND PAC HAD MOVED MEN BECAUSE THERE WERE REPORTS THAT A REBEL UNIT WAS IN THE AREA."

TST2-MUC4-0069

BOGOTA, 7 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [REPORT] [MARIBEL OSORIO] [TEXT] MEDELLIN CONTINUES TO LIVE THROUGH A WAVE OF TERROR. FOLLOWING LAST NIGHT'S ATTACK ON A BANK, WHICH CAUSED A LOT OF DAMAGE, A LOAD OF DYNAMITE WAS HURLED AGAINST A POLICE STATION. FORTUNATELY NO ONE WAS HURT. HOWEVER, AT APPROXIMATELY 1700 TODAY A BOMB EXPLODED INSIDE A FAST-FOOD RESTAURANT.

A MEDIUM-SIZED BOMB EXPLODED SHORTLY BEFORE 1700 AT THE PRESTO INSTALLATIONS LOCATED ON [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND PLAYA AVENUE. APPROXIMATELY 35 PEOPLE WERE INSIDE THE RESTAURANT AT THE TIME. A WORKER NOTICED A SUSPICIOUS PACKAGE UNDER A TABLE WHERE MINUTES BEFORE TWO MEN HAD BEEN SEATED. AFTER AN INITIAL MINOR EXPLOSION, THE PACKAGE EXPLODED. THE 35 PEOPLE HAD ALREADY BEEN EVACUATED FROM THE BUILDING, AND ONLY 1 POLICEMAN WAS SLIGHTLY INJURED; HE WAS THROWN TO THE GROUND BY THE SHOCK WAVE. THE AREA WAS IMMEDIATELY CORDONED OFF BY AUTHORITIES WHILE THE OTHER BUSINESSES CLOSED THEIR DOORS. IT IS NOT KNOWN HOW MUCH DAMAGE WAS CAUSED; HOWEVER, MOST OF THE DAMAGE WAS OCCURRED INSIDE THE RESTAURANT. THE MEN WHO LEFT THE BOMB FLED AND THERE ARE NO CLUES AS TO THEIR WHEREABOUTS.

TST2-MUC4-0070

SAN SALVADOR, 5 OCT 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] TODAY, RELIEF ORGANIZATIONS EVACUATED DOZENS OF PEOPLE WHO WERE LOCKED INSIDE "LA CENTROAMERICANA" BUILDING IN SAN SALVADOR WHERE THE COSTA RICAN EMBASSY IS LOCATED. HOWEVER, THE EMBASSY CONTINUES TO BE OCCUPIED BY APPROXIMATELY 50 DEMONSTRATORS.

AMBASSADOR JESUS FERNANDEZ AND ANOTHER TWO DIPLOMATS, AS WELL AS THREE SALVADORAN TELEVISION JOURNALISTS, ARE STILL BEING HELD HOSTAGE.

APPROXIMATELY 50 PEOPLE LEFT THE BUILDING IN WHICH THEY WERE LOCKED FOR 5 HOURS FOLLOWING THE OCCUPATION OF THE EMBASSY BY MEMBERS AND SYMPATHIZERS OF THE MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO FEDERATION OF COMMITTEES OF MOTHERS AND RELATIVES (FECMAFAM) OF POLITICAL PRISONERS AND MURDERED AND MISSING PEOPLE.

THE AMBASSADOR AND OTHER EMBASSY OFFICIALS STILL REMAIN ON THE THIRD FLOOR OF THE BUILDING, WHICH WAS SURROUNDED BY DOZENS OF RIOT POLICEMEN EXPERT IN ANTITERRORIST STRUGGLE, ARMED WITH HIGH-CALIBER RIFLES.

RED CROSS, GREEN CROSS, AND RELIEF COMMAND MEMBERS PARTICIPATED IN THE EVACUATION OF THE OFFICES IN THE BUILDING.

COLONEL ALEJANDRO SANCHEZ, DEPUTY DIRECTOR OF THE SALVADORAN NATIONAL POLICE, SAID THAT "THE PROBLEM COULD BE SOLVED WITHIN THE NEXT 24 HOURS, BUT OFFICIAL SOURCES RULED OUT THE USE OF FORCE.

MAURICIO SANDOVAL, DIRECTOR OF THE PRESIDENCY'S COMMUNICATIONS SECRETARIAT, WENT TO "LA CENTROAMERICANA" BUILDING, LOCATED IN EL SALVADOR'S BUSINESS DISTRICT, TO LEARN ABOUT THE SITUATION AND DESCRIBED THE OCCUPATION AS A "PROPAGANDA ACT" IN VIEW OF THE FACT THAT THE SECOND ROUND OF TALKS BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND THE GUERRILLAS, SCHEDULED FOR 16 AND 17 OCTOBER IN SAN JOSE (COSTA RICA), IS DRAWING CLOSER.

THE FECMAFAM OCCUPIED THE COSTA RICAN EMBASSY TO PROTEST "AN INCREASE IN REPRESSION AGAINST POPULAR ORGANIZATIONS UNLEASHED BY ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S FASCIST GOVERNMENT," FECMAFAM SPOKESMEN SAID.

MOST OF THOSE OCCUPYING THE EMBASSY ARE WOMEN WEARING WHITE SCARFS AND YOUTHS CARRYING WET HANDKERCHIEFS TO AVOID THE EFFECTS OF TEAR GAS.

SANDOVAL DISCLOSED THAT A WORKING COMMISSION HAS BEEN FORMED TO MAINTAIN CONSULTATIONS WITH THE COSTA RICAN GOVERNMENT "AND IS MAKING PERTINENT CONTACTS" TO SEEK A QUICK SOLUTION TO THIS PROBLEM.

THE OFFICIAL STRESSED: "WE WILL NOT BEGIN NEGOTIATIONS" WITH THE EMBASSY OCCUPIERS, WHOM, ACCORDING TO THE AMBASSADOR, ARE ARMED.

THE PRESIDENTIAL SPOKESMAN ALSO REPORTED THAT, IN THE WAKE OF THESE INCIDENTS, FERNANDEZ HAD A SLIGHT CARDIAC PROBLEM, BUT HAS ALREADY GOTTEN OVER IT.

ACCORDING TO THIS OFFICIAL, FERNANDEZ' WIFE SENT HIM MEDICINE AND FOOD.

SANDOVAL ANNOUNCED THAT AN OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUE WILL BE ISSUED WITHIN THE NEXT FEW HOURS.

TST2-MUC4-0072

LIMA, NO DATE (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT GARCIA] [EXCERPTS] [CONTINUED] I BELIEVE THAT THE CLIMATE OF FLEXIBILITY IS EMBRACING THE ENTIRE POLITICAL, MILITARY, AND ECONOMIC WORLD SYSTEM AND THAT THE BANKS WILL HAVE TO BE CONTENT WITH COLLECTING LESS THAN WHAT THEY ORIGINALLY THOUGHT. THERE WAS A TRIUMPHANT PRESENTATION OF AN OFFER TO REDUCE A COUNTRY'S DEBT BY UP TO 20 PERCENT, BUT AS FAR AS WE KNOW THAT OFFER HAS NOT MATERIALIZED. FURTHERMORE, A 20-PERCENT REDUCTION IS NOT SIGNIFICANT, NOT GREAT ENOUGH TO SOLVE THE PROBLEMS OF POVERTY AND THE FINANCIAL OBLIGATIONS OF LATIN AMERICA. THE REDUCTION MUST BE MUCH GREATER. A REDUCTION OF 10 OR 20 PERCENT WILL DO LITTLE; EVERYTHING WILL REMAIN THE SAME. WE BELIEVE -- AND I HAVE BEEN SAYING THIS TO EVERY LATIN AMERICAN PRESIDENT -- THAT ONLY THROUGH OUR ADOPTION OF FIRM AND DIGNIFIED POSITIONS WILL THE ADVERSARY RELENT. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

[GARCIA] LET ME NOW SAY A FEW WORDS ABOUT A DIFFERENT SUBJECT, THE ESTABLISHMENT OF RELATIONS WITH NORTH KOREA. I BELIEVE THE OPPOSITION HAS RAISED A TEMPEST IN A TEACUP; IT HAS RAISED AN ISSUE THAT IS OF NO RELEVANCE TO THE PERUVIAN PEOPLE. FIRST, WE UPHOLD THE CONCEPT OF UNIVERSALITY OF RELATIONS, OF MAINTAINING RELATIONS WITH ALL NATIONS. COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO ESTABLISHED RELATIONS WITH NORTH KOREA A FEW MONTHS AGO; HE DID NOT HAVE TO FACE A SAVAGE OPPOSITION TELLING HIM THAT HE WAS THROWING HIMSELF INTO THE ARMS OF TERRORISM. NOBODY HAS COMPLAINED TO CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ OR TO SALINAS DE GORTARI ABOUT MAINTAINING RELATIONS WITH NORTH KOREA. FOR THAT MATTER, NOBODY HAS OBJECTED IN BOLIVIA, AUSTRIA, OR SWEDEN, BECAUSE IN THOSE COUNTRIES THERE IS NO REACTIONARY RIGHT TO ARGUE THAT TO RECOGNIZE NORTH KOREA IS TO COURT DESTRUCTION.

SECOND, SOMEONE -- AND I DO NOT WANT TO MENTION HIM BY NAME -- HAS SAID THAT RELATIONS HAVE BEEN ESTABLISHED WITH A TERRORIST STATE. THIS IS A TREMENDOUS ERROR, BECAUSE 20,000 RIFLES SOLD TO US BY NORTH KOREA AT $90 APIECE -- $10 LESS THAN ANYWHERE IN THE WORLD -- HAVE MADE IT POSSIBLE TO SAVE AND DEFEND THE LIVES OF TENS OF THOUSANDS OF CIVILIAN GUARDS FROM THE NATIONAL POLICE AND HAVE MADE IT POSSIBLE TO ELIMINATE AND ERADICATE SUBVERSION IN MANY PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

THIRD, INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS ARE NOT DESIGNED TO BE AUCTIONED OFF TO THE HIGHEST BIDDER. IF SO WE WOULD HAVE TO BREAK RELATIONS WITH AUSTRALIA OR WITH FINLAND. ONE MUST MAINTAIN RELATIONS WITH ALL THE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD. UNDER SUCH CRITERIA, SINCE PERU RECOGNIZES THE FRG, IT SHOULD CLOSE ITS EMBASSY IN THE COMMUNIST GDR. THIS MANICHEAN CRITERION, THIS OBTUSE CRITERION, THIS OUTMODED CRITERION IS NO LONGER VALID; THE BERLIN WALL HAS BEEN RAZED. HOW CAN ONE SAY THAT THIS COUNTRY SHOULD BE RECOGNIZED AND ANOTHER SHOULDN'T? PERU WILL NOT ACCEPT ANY IMPERIALIST VETO ON ITS WORLD RELATIONS. WE HAVE HAD ENOUGH OF THE 1960'S AND 1970'S WHEN PASSPORTS SAID WE COULD NOT TRAVEL TO THE SOVIET UNION OR CUBA. PERUVIANS HAVE THE RIGHT TO TRAVEL WHEREVER THEY WISH, LIKE THEY WISH, AND WHEN THEY WISH. THIS IS FREEDOM, AND IT CANNOT BE CURTAILED BY THE ESTABLISHMENT OF OFF-LIMITS AREAS AROUND THE GLOBE.

FINALLY, SEVERAL OF THE GENTLEMEN WHO NOW OPPOSE THE ESTABLISHMENT OF RELATIONS WITH NORTH KOREA HAVE BEEN HONORED, ILLUSTRIOUS GUESTS OF THE NORTH KOREAN GOVERNMENT. THE OTHER DAY I HEARD SOME PEOPLE SPEAKING VEHEMENTLY ON THIS TOPIC, WHILE SOME OTHER PEOPLE NEARBY HAD BEEN HONORED GUESTS THERE. JOURNALISTS CAN SEEK OUT AND DETERMINE HOW MANY OF THOSE WHO NOW OPPOSE THESE RELATIONS HAVE BEEN HONORED GUESTS IN NORTH KOREA FOR WEEKS. NOW, FOR POLITICAL REASONS, THEY ARE OPPOSED TO THE ESTABLISHMENT OF RELATIONS WITH NORTH KOREA. [END RECORDING]

TST2-MUC4-0074

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [REPORT] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE MAIN REASON FOR COMING UP WITH THIS VERSION WAS TO [WORDS INDISTINCT] MASTERMINDS OF THE CRIME [WORDS INDISTINCT] TO FIND OUT WHO THE PERPETRATORS WERE. WITH THIS VERSION, CRISTIANI AND THE HIGH COMMAND ARE TRYING TO COME UP WITH EXTENUATING CIRCUMSTANCES FOR THE TRIAL AND TO PLACE THE RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ASSASSINATION OF THE JESUITS ON MID-LEVEL MILITARY OFFICERS. THE COLONELS WHO WERE INVOLVED IN THE CRIME COULD BE SET FREE AND THEIR RESPONSIBILITY WOULD ONLY BE RELATED TO THE FACT THAT THE CRIME WAS COMMITTED WITHIN AN AREA UNDER THEIR COMMAND.

THIS VERSION OF THE CRIME IS AIMED AT LEAVING THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND FREE FROM ANY RESPONSIBILITY AND TO ONLY SLIGHTLY TOUCH THE MEMBERS OF LA TANDONA, ESPECIALLY COL ORLANDO CEPEDA, WHO WAS THE ONE WHO SIGNED THE ORDER TO ASSASSINATE THE JESUITS, AND COL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHIEF OF STAFF. COL GUILLERMO BENAVIDES, WHO IS A MEMBER OF LITTLE IMPORTANCE WITHIN LA TANDONA, WAS INDIRECTLY INVOLVED IN THE CRIME.

HOWEVER, THE [WORD INDISTINCT] IS SELF-EVIDENT. THE DECISION TO CARRY OUT AN OPERATION TO KILL POPULAR AND RELIGIOUS DEMOCRATIC LEADERS WAS MADE BY THE GENERAL STAFF OF THE ARMED FORCES [WORDS INDISTINCT] 4 DAYS AFTER THE FMLN OFFENSIVE BEGAN. THIS OPERATION WAS PART OF A COMPLETE COUNTEROFFENSIVE PLAN OF THE ARMED FORCES, WHICH INCLUDED THE MASSIVE USE OF ALL THE FIREPOWER OF THE AIR FORCE AGAINST POOR NEIGHBORHOODS AND THE KILLING OF DEMOCRATIC PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT AND CHURCH LEADERS.

ALFREDO CRISTIANI, WHO WAS TAKEN TO THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE GENERAL STAFF FOR SECURITY REASONS AND ASSUMED CONTROL OF THE DEFENSE PLAN, WAS FULLY AWARE OF THE GENOCIDE PLAN. U.S. OFFICERS AND ADVISERS WERE ALSO AT THE GENERAL STAFF HEADQUARTERS AT THE TIME TO DISCUSS AND APPROVE THIS GENOCIDE PLAN.

THE PLAN WAS IMPLEMENTED ON THE EVENING OF 16 NOVEMBER. ALL LABOR UNION OFFICES IN SAN SALVADOR WERE LOOTED. THE OFFICES OF HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS, POLITICAL PARTIES, AND RELIGIOUS CENTERS WERE ALSO LOOTED.

THE PLAN WAS IMPLEMENTED AT THE INSTALLATIONS OF THE UCA. THE DAYS THAT FOLLOWED SAW A CONTINUATION OF THE ARRESTS, PERSECUTIONS, AND ASSASSINATIONS. THE OFFICES OF ALL THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] WERE ATTACKED. ITS LEADERS WERE FORCED TO SEEK REFUGE OR TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY TO ESCAPE THIS MANHUNT. THIS IS A POLICY FOR WHICH THE HIGH COMMAND AND ALFREDO CRISTIANI ARE DIRECTLY RESPONSIBLE. [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE U.S. AMBASSADOR AND U.S. EMBASSY PERSONNEL ARE FULLY AWARE OF THIS.

THE NEED TO COME UP WITH THIS VERSION COMES FROM THE PRECARIOUS PREDICAMENT THAT THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES HAVE FOUND THEMSELVES IN IN VIEW OF THE DEBATES TAKING PLACE IN THE U.S. CONGRESS TO DECIDE THE FATE OF AID TO EL SALVADOR, WHICH IS LINKED TO THE RESULTS OF THE INVESTIGATION OF THE ASSASSINATION OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS ON 16 NOVEMBER.

TST2-MUC4-0076

BOGOTA, 3 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] OFFICIAL SOURCES ANNOUNCED THAT A U.S. STATE DEPARTMENT HERCULES C-123 CARGO PLANE WAS PARTIALLY DESTROYED EARLY THIS MORNING WHEN AN INCENDIARY BOMB EXPLODED AT THE MONTERIA AIRPORT. MONTERIA IS THE CAPITAL OF CORDOBA DEPARTMENT AND IT IS LOCATED 490 KM NORTH OF BOGOTA.

A SPOKESMAN FOR THE MONTERIA POLICE ADVISED AFP VIA TELEPHONE THAT THE FRONT PART OF THE PLANE, AS WELL AS THE COCKPIT, WERE BURNED WHEN A BOMB, PLANTED BY UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS, EXPLODED. NO VICTIMS WERE REPORTED.

THE U.S. EMBASSY IN BOGOTA CONFIRMED THAT THE PLANE WAS "SERIOUSLY DAMAGED" BY THE FLAMES; HOWEVER, THE EMBASSY DID NOT SPECIFY THE ORIGIN OF THE FIRE. ACCORDING TO EMBASSY SPOKESMAN PETER SAMSON, THE PLANE IS THE PROPERTY OF THE U.S. STATE DEPARTMENT'S INTERNATIONAL NARCOTICS MATTERS (INM).

THE PLANE, WHICH WAS RETURNING TO THE UNITED STATES AFTER FULFILLING A MISSION IN PERU, HAD BEEN PARKED AT THE MONTERIA AIRPORT FOR THE PAST 2 WEEKS. THE PLANE WAS FORCED TO LAND IN MONTERIA AFTER ONE OF ITS ENGINES FAILED, THE EMBASSY SPOKESMAN ADDED.

ACCORDING TO THE MONTERIA POLICE, THE FIRE BROKE OUT AFTER AN EXPLOSION WAS HEARD. THE FIREMEN INTERVENED QUICKLY TO PREVENT THE FIRE FROM SPREADING AND COMPLETELY DESTROYING THE PLANE.

THE FIRE BROKE OUT AT 0430 (0930 GMT), A FEW HOURS BEFORE TWO C-130 PLANES--U.S. MILITARY CARGO PLANES--ARRIVED AT BOGOTA AIR FORCE BASE WITH MILITARY MATERIEL SENT TO HELP FIGHT THE BATTLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING LAUNCHED BY THE COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES.

TST2-MUC4-0078

CLANDESTINE, 28 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION: A REPORT FROM SAN SALVADOR STATES THAT FIGHTING CONTINUES IN THE NORTHERN SECTOR OF THE CITY. OUR FORCES ARE FINDING LITTLE RESISTANCE FROM THE SO-CALLED TROOPS BROUGHT FROM THE INTERIOR OF THE COUNTRY. THE REPORT STATES THAT DURING TODAY'S CLASHES IN CIUDAD DELGADO, LOS ALPES, GUADALUPE, AND SAN PATRICIO NEIGHBORHOODS, THE TREASURY POLICE SUFFERED THREE CASUALTIES. WE INFLICTED TWO CASUALTIES ON THE TREASURY POLICE IN LOS ALPES NEIGHBORHOOD, AND THE 6TH MILITARY DETACHMENT SUFFERED ONE CASUALTY DURING A CLASH IN SAN PATRICIO NEIGHBORHOOD. IT HAS ALSO BEEN REPORTED THAT FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] FORCES HAVE SET UP BARRICADES ON THE NORTHERN TRUNK ROAD AND POWER LINES HAVE BEEN SABOTAGED. AS A RESULT OF THIS SABOTAGE, AN AREA OF SAN SALVADOR DOES NOT HAVE POWER. WE HAVE ALSO LEARNED THAT TWO TRANSFORMERS WERE DESTROYED ON KM 10 OF THE NORTHERN TRUNK ROAD, WHERE BARRICADES WERE ALSO SET UP. THE REPORT ADDS THAT THE ENEMY SHOWED UP 90 MINUTES AFTER THE BARRICADES HAD BEEN SET UP AND HEAVY FIGHTING RESULTED. THE ENEMY TROOPS SUFFERED FOUR CASUALTIES; OUR FORCES HAVE REPORTED THAT THEY HAVE NOT ENCOUNTERED PROBLEMS ON THE NORTHERN TRUNK ROAD. AT THIS HOUR, 1613 [2213 GMT], THE REBEL PRESENCE IN INCREASING ON THE NORTHERN TRUNK ROAD.

ATTENTION: DURING YESTERDAY'S ATTACK, WITH PEOPLE'S ARTILLERY ON 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS, WE INFLICTED EIGHT CASUALTIES. THESE EIGHT CASUALTIES HAVE BEEN CONFIRMED.

AT NOON TODAY, CLASHES WITH 1ST MILITARY DETACHMENT TROOPS WAS REPORTED IN LA CRUZ HILL, SAN MIGUEL DE MERCEDES JURISDICTION. WE REPEAT: TODAY AT NOON, FIGHTING WAS REPORTED IN LA CRUZ HILL, SAN MIGUEL DE MERCEDES, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT.

THIS HAS BEEN THE LATEST REPORT WE HAVE RECEIVED. THERE IS FIGHTING IN CIUDAD DELGADO, LOS ALPES, GUADALUPE, SAN PATRICIO, AND OUR GUERRILLA COLUMNS ARE SPREADING THROUGHOUT THE NORTHERN PART OF THE CITY. IT IS NOW 1615 [2215 GMT] AND THE HIGH COMMAND HAS NOT REACTED. THIS GIVES US AN IDEA OF HOW LOW MORALE IS AMONG THE SOLDIERS IN SAN SALVADOR. THIS NEW BLOW AGAINST THE ENEMY FORCES IN SAN SALVADOR HAS CAUSED THE MORALE OF THE ENEMY FORCES TO DROP EVEN FURTHER.

ATTENTION: WE HAVE JUST LEARNED THAT THERE HAS BEEN A REBEL AMBUSH IN THE NORTHERN SECTOR OF SAN SALVADOR. THE REPORT ADDS THAT AT 0630 [1230 GMT] TODAY, REBEL FORCES AMBUSHED A VEHICLE TRANSPORTING NATIONAL GUARDSMEN. THE AMBUSH OCCURRED ON KM 9.5 ON THE NORTHERN TRUNK ROAD. THE GUARDSMEN WERE HEADING INTO AN AREA WHERE THE FMLN REBELS HAVE SET UP BARRICADES. A POWERFUL GUAZAPA-TYPE MINE AND RIFLES WERE USED IN THE AMBUSH. AT LEAST 10 CASUALTIES, INCLUDING A NATIONAL GUARD OFFICER, WERE INFLICTED. WE REPEAT: A NATIONAL GUARD OFFICER IS INCLUDED AMONG THE CASUALTIES WE INFLICTED DURING THIS AMBUSH CARRIED OUT ON KM 9.5 ON THE NORTHERN TRUNK ROAD.

LIKEWISE, WE HAVE LEARNED THAT FIGHTING CONTINUES IN MEJICANOS, AYUTUXTEPEQUE, CIUDAD DELGADO, AND SOYAPANGO. HEAVY FIGHTING IS ALSO BEING REPORTED IN APOPA AND MARIONA. REBEL FORCES ARE SPREADING OUT THROUGHOUT THE NORTHERN AREA OF SAN SALVADOR AND THEY ARE FINDING LITTLE RESISTANCE. AT 1616 [2216 GMT], THIS HAS BEEN THE REPORT RECEIVED AT RADIO VENCEREMOS. WE ARE RECEIVING REPORTS FROM OUR LIBERATED TERRORITORIES, FROM CHALATE [CHALATENANGO], MORAZAN, SAN MIGUEL. GREETINGS TO OUR FORCES IN SAN SALVADOR; ONWARDS FIGHTING COMRADES; OUR PEOPLE ARE SUPPORTING YOU IN SAN SALVADOR.

TST2-MUC4-0080

SAN SALVADOR, 11 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION PLEASE, LISTENERS OF YSKL. WE CONTINUE REPORTING ON THE RECENT INCIDENTS IN THE CAPITAL. ACCORDING TO REPORTS WE HAVE RECEIVED, THE PRESIDENCIAL RESIDENCE LOCATED IN THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD WAS TARGET OF AN ATTACK TONIGHT.

WE HAVE ALSO LEARNED THAT TWO VEHICLES OF THE SALVADORAN RED CROSS HAVE ALSO BEEN ATTACKED. ONE OF THEM WAS TOTALLY DESTROYED BY FIRE IN THE MEJICANOS SECTOR, AND AN AMBULANCE WAS ATTACKED NEAR THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY.

WE HAVE ALSO RECEIVED REPORTS FROM THE NORTHERN NATIONAL GUARD SECTOR IN THE SAN JOAQUIN NEIGHBORHOOD AND SURROUNDING AREAS, FROM WHERE THE ATTACKS AGAINST THE NATIONAL GUARD HEADQUARTERS ARE BEING LAUNCHED. HERE IS FRANCISCO BENITEZ WITH AN IMPORTANT LAST MINUTE REPORT. GO AHEAD, FRANCISCO:

[BEGIN RELAY] GOOD EVENING YSKL LISTENERS. WE HAVE CONFIRMED THAT CLASHES CONTINUE AT THIS TIME OF THE NIGHT NEAR THE UNIVERSITY OF EL SALVADOR BETWEEN URBAN COMMANDOES OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN) AND MEMBERS OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE WHO ARE IN AREA SURROUNDING THE UNIVERSITY OF EL SALVADOR, SPECIFICALLY IN FRONT OF THE INSTITUTE OF URBAN HOUSING, IVU, OFFICES.

THIS IS A DARK SECTOR. ALL CIVILIANS, PEDESTRIANS, AND DRIVERS ARE ASKED TO AVOID THIS SECTOR BECAUSE HEAVY SHOOTING CONTINUES IN THE AREA BETWEEN REBELS AND MEMBERS OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE. WE HAVE CONFIRMED THAT THERE IS A HEAVY EXCHANGE OF FIRE IN THIS SECTOR. WE HAVE BEEN TOLD THAT PEDESTRIANS AND DRIVERS SHOULD BE WARNED TO AVOID THIS AREA, AS THERE IS HEAVY SHOOTING NEAR THE UNIVERSITY OF EL SALVADOR. WE HAVE CONFIRMED THIS. WE CAN HEAR SHOOTING EVERYWHERE IN THIS SECTOR, PARTICULARLY IN FRONT OF THE IVU OFFICES.

MEMBERS OF THE CIVIL DEFENSE IN MEJICANOS HAVE JUST CONFIRMED THAT THEY ARE ALSO FIGHTING IN MEJICANOS AT THIS TIME OF THE NIGHT.

STAY TUNED, AS WE WILL CONTINUE REPORTING.

TST2-MUC4-0081

BOGOTA, 27 AUG 89 (REUTER) -- [TEXT] THE RESPECTED EL ESPECTADOR NEWSPAPER HAS REPORTED THAT COLOMBIAN JUSTICE MINISTER MONICA DE GREIFF, A KEY OFFICIAL IN THE WAR ON DRUG TRAFFICKING, HAS RESIGNED.

MEANWHILE, MEDELLIN METROPOLITAN POLICE ANNOUNCED THAT, EARLY THIS MORNING, UNIDENTIFIED PERSONS PLACED 11 BOMBS IN VARIOUS GOVERNMENT BANK BRANCHES. SEVEN OF THESE BOMBS EXPLODED, CAUSING DAMAGE, BUT THERE WERE NO VICTIMS.

JUSTICE MINISTER MONICA DE GREIFF, 32, WENT TO THE UNITED STATES ON 25 AUGUST TO SUBMIT A SPECIFIC PLAN ON THE USE OF A $2-MILLION U.S. GRANT TO PROVIDE SECURITY TO COLOMBIAN JUDGES.

EL ESPECTADOR SAID THAT "RUMORS OF A POSSIBLE CABINET RESHUFFLE GREW, AND IT WAS FULLY CONFIRMED THAT JUSTICE MINISTER MONICA DE GREIFF HAD RESIGNED AND WILL STAY FOR AN INDEFINITE PERIOD IN THE UNITED STATES."

A JUSTICE MINISTRY SPOKESMAN DECLINED TO COMMENT ON THE NEWSPAPER REPORT, BUT A POLITICAL SOURCE OF THE RULING PARTY TOLD REUTER HE HAD HEARD THE MINISTER WAS GOING TO RESIGN.

ANOTHER SOURCE SAID GREIFF WILL STAY IN THE UNITED STATES FOR 12 DAYS AND THAT SHE WILL TENDER HER RESIGNATION UPON HER RETURN.

GREIFF, WHO WAS APPOINTED ON 16 JULY, WAS ASKED BEFORE LEAVING THE COUNTRY IF SHE WAS A WARTIME OR PEACETIME MINISTER. SHE REPLIED: "I AM A PEACETIME MINISTER."

LOCAL NEWS MEDIA AND POLITICAL SECTORS INTERPRETED THIS COMMENT AS AN ADVANCED NOTICE OF HER RESIGNATION.

TST2-MUC4-0082

CARACAS (VENEZUELA), 18 MAY 90 (VENEZOLANA DE TELEVISION CANAL 8) -- [TEXT] GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO HAS PRESENTED TO THE VENEZUELAN GOVERNMENT A PROPOSAL TO RESTRUCTURE THE SAN JOSE AGREEMENT. THE PROPOSAL COVERS THE SUPPLY OF OIL AND THE SALE OF FINISHED PRODUCTS. ANOTHER POINT INCLUDED IS THE REFINANCING OF THE GUATEMALAN DEBT WITH VENEZUELA, WHICH TOTALS $200 MILLION.

THE GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT'S ACTIVITIES BEGAN TODAY AT MIRAFLORES PALACE WHEN, PRIOR TO THE SIGNING OF THE TWO AGREEMENTS, THE VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT HELD A PRIVATE MEETING WITH HIS GUATEMALAN COUNTERPART. THE PRESIDENTS THEN HELD A FORMAL WORK SESSION WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF TWO COMMISSIONS AT THE MINISTERIAL LEVEL. GUATEMALA, LIKE OTHER COUNTRIES THAT BENEFIT FROM THE SAN JOSE AGREEMENT, ARE FACING THE PROBLEM OF NOT BEING ABLE TO HONOR ALL COMMITMENTS ON DEBTS AS THEY MATURE. THE RESTRUCTURING OF THE SAN JOSE AGREEMENT WAS ONE OF THE POINTS DISCUSSED BY PRESIDENT CEREZO DURING A NEWS CONFERENCE TODAY AT THE AYACUCHO ROOM OF THE PRESIDENTIAL PALACE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CEREZO] WE HAVE PROPOSED A 20-YEAR TERM TO RESTRUCTURE THE DEBT, WITH A SIX-YEAR GRACE PERIOD, AT FOUR PERCENT INTEREST. OBVIOUSLY, THIS HAS NOT BEEN THE USUAL PROCEDURE AT THE VENEZUELAN INVESTMENT FUND NOR IS THIS INCLUDED IN THE SAN JOSE AGREEMENT. FOR THESE REASONS, BECAUSE THIS PROPOSAL DOES NOT FIT VENEZUELAN LAW, WE NEED TO DISCUSS AND ADJUST THE TERMS TO THE LAW AND THE SAN JOSE AGREEMENT. HOWEVER, THERE IS WILLINGNESS TO DISCUSS THE TERMS. WE WILL OBVIOUSLY HAVE TO MAKE THE SAME PROPOSAL TO THE MEXICAN GOVERNMENT, FROM WHOM WE EXPECT THE SAME ATTITUDE AND UNDERSTANDING, AND WE ARE CERTAIN WE WILL HAVE IT. [END RECORDING]

WITHIN THE FORMAL CEREZO VISIT, TWO IMPORTANT AGREEMENTS BETWEEN VENEZUELA AND GUATEMALA WERE SIGNED TODAY. ONE OF THEM IS A COOPERATION AND FRIENDSHIP AGREEMENT. ANOTHER IS A SCIENTIFIC AND TECHNOLOGICAL COOPERATION AGREEMENT IN ENERGY AND MINING MATTERS, WHICH WILL STRENGTHEN BILATERAL RELATIONS. AS ENERGY AND MINES MINISTER CELESTINO ARMAS SAID UPON SIGNING THE AGREEMENTS, THIS WILL PERMIT CARRYING OUT JOINT OIL EXPLORATION OPERATIONS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ARMAS] FOR EXAMPLE, IN THE AREA OF OIL EXPLORATION, THERE ARE VERY INTERESTING PROSPECTS IN GUATEMALA THAT COULD RESULT IN GREAT INTEREST FOR GUATEMALA AND FOR VENEZUELA. WITH REGARD TO MINING, WE HAVE BEEN DISCUSSING THE POSSIBILITY OF MAKING SOME PROGRESS IN THE MINING SECTOR IN GUATEMALA AND THE POSSIBILITY OF HELPING GUATEMALA DISCOVER MINERAL DEPOSITS THAT COULD BE VERY ATTRACTIVE FOR OUR ECONOMIES. [END RECORDING]

FOLLOWING THE NEWS CONFERENCE HELD AT THE MIRAFLORES PALACE, GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO WENT TO THE CELA [ECONOMIC COMISSION FOR LATIN AMERICA]. THE CEREZO AGENDA INCLUDED A DINNER HE WILL HOST TONIGHT FOR HIS COUNTERPART CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ.

TST2-MUC4-0084

BEIJING (PRC), 16 FEB 90 (SHIJIE ZHISHI) -- [ARTICLE] [SHEN AN] [TEXT] AT THE END OF 1989 AND AT THE BEGINNING OF 1990, THE UNITED STATES CONDUCTED TWO MAJOR MILITARY OPERATIONS IN LATIN AMERICA, TO THE UNANIMOUS CONDEMNATION OF THE NATIONS OF LATIN AMERICA AND OTHER PARTS OF THE WORLD. HOWEVER, THE FIGHTERS FOR "FREEDOM," "DEMOCRACY," AND "HUMAN RIGHTS" IN WESTERN NATIONS HAVE KEPT QUIET OUT OF FEAR OF THE NAKED AGGRESSION AND THE WAY OF THE TYRANT.

ON 20 DECEMBER 1989, SEVERAL TENS OF THOUSANDS OF U.S. TROOPS, EQUIPPED WITH THE MOST UP-TO-DATE WEAPONS, BRAZENLY INTRUDED INTO PANAMA, TOPPLING THE NORIEGA GOVERNMENT AND FORCING MANUEL ANTONIO NORIEGA TO BE TRIED IN THE UNITED STATES. THIS U.S. ACT WAS BY NO MEANS LESS THAN THE SOVIET ACT OF INVADING CZECHOSLOVAKIA AND KIDNAPPING ITS LEADERS AT THAT TIME. THE NEW PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT ESTIMATED THAT THE U.S. INVASION HAD RESULTED IN THE DEATHS OF AT LEAST 600 PANAMANIAN SOLDIERS AND CIVILIANS AND MADE SEVERAL TENS OF THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE HOMELESS. MORE THAN 5,000 MILITARY AND ADMINISTRATIVE PERSONNEL OF THE FORMER GOVERNMENT WERE ARRESTED BY U.S. TROOPS, AND PANAMA SUFFERED ECONOMIC LOSSES OF $10 BILLION. THE UNITED STATES OPENLY MANIPULATED THE WORK OF ESTABLISHING A NEW PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT, NATIONAL DEFENSE ARMY, POLICE FORCE, AND OTHER STATE APPARATUSES, SO MUCH SO THAT IT RUSHED IN AND RAIDED [AS PUBLISHED] THE EMBASSIES OF OTHER COUNTRIES IN PANAMA OR DIPLOMATIC APARTMENTS, AND DETAINED THE DIPLOMATIC OFFICIALS OF OTHER COUNTRIES. UNDER THE POWERFUL PRESSURE OF WORLD OPINION, SOME OF THE U.S. TROOPS HAVE WITHDRAWN FROM PANAMA, BUT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT STILL REFUSES TO PULL OUT ALL ITS TROOPS.

JUST AFTER ITS INTRUSION INTO PANAMA, THE U.S. GOVERNMENT IMMEDIATELY ANNOUNCED, AS SCHEDULED, THE DISPATCH OF A STRONG FLEET OF WARSHIPS INTO THE CARIBBEAN, CLOSE TO THE COAST OF COLOMBIA, FOR WHAT WAS CALLED AN ANTIDRUG MANEUVER, INTERCEPTING PLANES AND VESSELS FOR TRAFFICKING IN DRUGS. ON 5 JANUARY THIS YEAR, THE UNITED STATES, IGNORING THE STRONG OPPOSITION OF LATIN AMERICAN NATIONS, ORDERED A FLEET OF FOUR WARSHIPS, INCLUDING THE AIRCRAFT CARRIER "KENNEDY" AND NUCLEAR-PROPELLED CRUISER "VIRGINIA," TO SAIL TOWARD THE CARIBBEAN TO "COMBAT DRUG SMUGGLING." SUCH A HIGH-HANDED WAY OF IGNORING THE SOVEREIGNTY AND WILL OF LATIN AMERICAN NATIONS AND FORCING THE DEPLOYMENT OF TROOPS IN FRONT OF THE GATES OF OTHER COUNTRIES EVOKED FIERCE REACTIONS IN COLOMBIA AND OTHER LATIN AMERICAN NATIONS. JARAMILLO OSSA, A PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE FROM THE COLOMBIAN PATRIOTIC UNION, NOTED THAT THE UNITED STATES "VERY NEARLY" INVADED COLOMBIA. THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT ALSO WARNED THE U.S. GOVERNMENT: WITHOUT THE AUTHORIZATION OF THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT BARCO, NO U.S WARSHIPS ARE ALLOWED TO DRAW NEAR [AS PUBLISHED] THE WATERS OF COLOMBIA. IT ALSO ORDERED ITS NAVAL AND AIR FORCES TO INTENSIFY THEIR SEA PATROLS TO SAFEGUARD THE COUNTRY'S SOVEREIGNTY. AT THE SAME TIME, THE GOVERNMENTS OF COLOMBIA, VENEZUELA, AND SOME OTHER NATIONS REFUSED TO JOIN THE PROPOSED U.S. "DRUG-FIGHTING DRILL" IN THE CARIBBEAN. FACED WITH SUCH A SITUATION, THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION HAD TO ORDER THE "DRUG-FIGHTING FLEET" TO RETURN TO BASE AND CANCEL THE "DRILL."

ON THE AFOREMENTIONED ACTS OF THE UNITED STATES, LEADERS OF SOME LATIN AMERICAN NATIONS COMMENTED: WHILE RELAXING THE TENSION WITH THE SOVIET UNION, THE UNITED STATES HAS RESERVED THE "RIGHT" TO INTERFERE BY FORCE IN LATIN AMERICA AND OTHER SMALL AND WEAK COUNTRIES. THE PUBLIC MEDIA OF SOME NATIONS SOLEMNLY POINTED OUT: SUCH MOVES OF U.S. AGGRESSION ARE THE CONTINUATION OF THE CONSISTENT U.S. POLICY OF INTERFERING IN THE AFFAIRS OF LATIN AMERICA AND ALSO THE EXTENSION OF WHAT IS CALLED THE REAGAN DOCTRINE, WHICH STARTED IN THE EARLY 1980'S.

IN U.S. RELATIONS WITH LATIN AMERICA THROUGHOUT THE DECADE OF THE 1980'S, THERE WAS A PROBLEM AFFECTING THE SITUATION AS A WHOLE, NAMELY, THE ISSUE OF CENTRAL AMERICA, WHICH HAD ALL ALONG BEEN LISTED IN THE CATEGORY OF EAST-WEST CONFRONTATION BY THE UNITED STATES. THE REAGAN ADMINISTRATION EVEN GAVE TOP PRIORITY TO MEETING THE CRISIS IN CENTRAL AMERICA IN ITS FOREIGN POLICY.

IN 1981, WHEN REAGAN ENTERED THE WHITE HOUSE, THE SITUATION IN CENTRAL AMERICA STOOD AS FOLLOWS: THE SANDINISTA REVOLUTION HAD WON VICTORY IN NICARAGUA, THE GUERRILLA WAR IN EL SALVADOR WAS ESCALATING, AND A TURBULENT SITUATION HAD STARTED TO EMERGE IN OTHER CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES. THE HUMAN RIGHTS DIPLOMACY PURSUED BY THE CARTER ADMINISTRATION RESULTED IN THE DETERIORATION OF U.S. RELATIONS WITH A CERTAIN NUMBER OF LATIN AMERICAN NATIONS RULED BY JUNTAS. IN 1977 THE CARTER ADMINISTRATION SIGNED THE PANAMA CANAL TREATY WITH THE PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT, AGREEING TO RETURN TO PANAMA SOVEREIGNTY OVER THE CANAL AND THE CANAL ZONE. BEFORE THE VICTORY OF THE NICARAGUA REVOLUTION, IN 1979 THE CARTER ADMINISTRATION ABANDONED ITS SUPPORT FOR THE TYRANNICAL SOMOSA REGIME AND ESTABLISHED NORMAL RELATIONS WITH THE SANDINISTA REGIME. [SENTENCE AS PUBLISHED] [CONTINUED]

TST2-MUC4-0085

SAN SALVADOR, 13 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [NATIONAL INFORMATION CENTER, SIN] [TEXT] THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF EL SALVADOR REPORTS TO THE INTERNATIONAL AND NATIONAL COMMUNITY THAT THE TERRORIST OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FML]. AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE HAS BEEN COUNTERED BY THE ARMED FORCES IN COMPLIANCE WITH ITS CONSTITUTIONAL RESPONSIBILITY TO PROTECT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S LIVES AND POSSESSIONS. THE SITUATION IS UNDER THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES' CONTROL.

THE FLMN, WITH A TOTAL DISREGARD FOR HUMAN RIGHTS, HAS UNLEASHED AN INDISCRIMINATE ATTACK ON VARIOUS PLACES IN SAN SALVADOR AND ON THE CAPITALS OF FOUR DEPARTMENTS BY FIRING VERY POWERFUL WEAPONS AND KILLING MANY CIVILIANS.

THE GOVERNMENT HEREBY REPORTS THESE TERRORIST ACTIONS BECAUSE THE FMLN ATTACKS ON MILITARY OBJECTIVES HAVE SERIOUSLY ENDANGERED THE LIVES OF THOUSANDS AND THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS.

THIS FMLN ATTACK IS TOTALLY UNJUSTIFIED BECAUSE THE DIALOGUE PROCESS IS CURRENTLY UNDERWAY AND THE GOVERNMENT HAS ATTENDED THEM WITH TOTAL POLITICAL HONESTY, TRYING TO FIND MECHANISMS AND RATIONAL SOLUTIONS TO THE CONFLICT. THE FMLN NOT ONLY HAS VIOLATED THE AGREEMENTS IT SIGNED IN MEXICO CITY, BUT ALSO IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA. IT HAS ALSO BRAZENLY MOCKED THE FEELINGS AND THE DESIRE FOR PEACE WANTED BY THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

THE FMLN TERRORIST ACTIONS HAVE FORCED THE GOVERNMENT TO MAKE USE OF ITS LEGITIMATE RIGHT TO DEFEND SOCIETY BY USING THE ARMED FORCES WHICH HAS BEEN FULLY SUPPORTED BY THE PEOPLE. SALVADORAN PEOPLE DO NOT WANT TO LOSE THEIR LIBERTY AND FALL INTO THE HANDS OF TOTALITARIAN MARXIST-LENINIST SYSTEMS SUCH AS THE ONE THE FMLN WANTS TO IMPOSE RUTHLESSLY. REPRESENTATIVES FROM VARIOUS COUNTRIES WHO HAVE OBSERVED THE DEVELOPMENT OF THESE INCIDENTS CAN FULLY CONFIRM THE FACTS. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, IN ADDITION TO BEING VICTIMS OF THE FMLN AGGRESSION, FEEL OUTRAGED BECAUSE THE FMLN STILL HAS THE GALL TO SAY THAT IT IS SPEAKING IN DEFENSE OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WHO, IN THESE SAD TIMES, FEEL OUTRAGED BY THE TERRORIST GROUP'S IRRATIONAL ATTACK.

THE GOVERMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF EL SALVADOR REQUESTS THAT THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY CONDEMN THIS BRUTAL VIOLATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS PERPETRATED BY THE FMLN. IT ALSO ASKS THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY TO CONDEMN THE HIDEOUS CRIMES THE FMLN TROOPS ARE PERPETRATING AGAINST CIVILIANS -- WHO FLATLY REFUSE TO HELP THEM -- AND WHO HAVE REJECTED THEM [3 SECOND BREAK IN TRANSMISSION]. THE GOVERNMENT ALSO REQUESTS THAT THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY STRONGLY CONDEMN NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT ORTEGA BECAUSE HE SUPPLIED THE WEAPONS THAT THE TERRORISTS ARE USING TO MASSACRE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

TST2-MUC4-0087

HAMBURG (FRG), 16 DEC 89 (DIE WELT) -- [INTERVIEW WITH CHILEAN PRESIDENT PATRICIO AYLWIN BY WERNER THOMAS] [TEXT] DIE WELT: YOUR THOUGHTS ARE FOCUSED ON CHILE, BUT LET US BRIEFLY LOOK AT EUROPE NEVERTHELESS. THE DEMOCRATIC REVOLUTION IN EAST EUROPE HAS ALSO BEEN A SENSATION TO CHILE. WHAT HOPES DO YOU PLACE IN THESE GIGANTIC RADICAL CHANGES?

AYLWIN: I THINK THAT THE CHANGES IN EAST EUROPE ARE OF VERY GREAT IMPORTANCE FOR MANKIND. THEY GIVE US SATISFACTION AND HOPE. THE OPENING OF THE BERLIN WALL SYMBOLIZES THE BEGINNING OF A NEW ERA IN RELATIONS BETWEEN EAST AND WEST AS WELL AS THE DESIRE OF THE GERMANS TO ACHIEVE UNITY AGAIN. WE WOULD LIKE TO SEE THIS SITUATION LEAD TO A REDUCTION IN MILITARY SPENDING AND TO CLOSER RELATIONS BETWEEN THE PEOPLES.

DIE WELT: WHAT EFFECTS DO YOU SEE FOR A THIRD WORLD COUNTRY SUCH AS CHILE?

AYLWIN: I SEE TWO EFFECTS. FIRST, A SYMBOLIC EFFECT. CHILE IS TRADITIONALLY A DEMOCRATIC COUNTRY. NOW THE LONG PERIOD OF A DICTATORIAL REGIME IS ENDING, HOWEVER. THIS EXPLOSION OF FREEDOM COINCIDES WITH THE RESTORATION OF DEMOCRACY IN CHILE. THAT IS A STIMULATING FEELING. WE ARE EMBARKING ON THE ROAD OF HUMANITY. SECOND, THERE IS A LOT OF TALK ABOUT THE DANGER OF COMMUNISM IN OUR COUNTRY; PEOPLE SAY THAT COMMUNISM COULD JEOPARDIZE OUR DEMOCRATIC FUTURE. I THINK THAT THE EVENTS IN EAST EUROPE AND THE SOVIET UNION DEMONSTRATE THAT COMMUNISM IS NO LONGER A DANGER FOR THE WORLD. NOR FOR CHILE.

DIE WELT: CHILE HAS THE BEST ORGANIZED COMMUNIST PARTY IN LATIN AMERICA. HAS THIS PARTY CHANGED? WHAT WAS ITS REACTION?

AYLWIN: LITTLE IS KNOWN ABOUT THE SITUATION OF SUCH A MONOLITHIC AND COHERENT PARTY. IT WAS ILLEGAL AND WORKED UNDERGROUND FOR A LONG TIME. HOWEVER, I DO NOT BELIEVE THAT ANY COMMUNIST PARTY CAN IGNORE THE EVENTS IN THAT PART OF THE WORLD WHICH HAS SO FAR BEEN DOMINATED BY COMMUNIST PARTIES. THE CHILEAN COMMUNIST PARTY LEADERS HAVE ADMITTED THAT THIS IS A UNIVERSAL PROCESS.

DIE WELT: WHAT RELATIONSHIP DO YOU HAVE WITH VOLODIA TEITELBOIM, THE GENERAL SECRETARY OF THE COMMUNIST PARTY? DO YOU SPEAK WITH HIM? DO YOU SEE HIM SOMETIMES?

AYLWIN: WE HAVE KNOWN EACH OTHER FROM THE TIME WHEN WE WERE BOTH SENATORS, MEANING PRIOR TO 1973. WE WERE POLITICAL OPPONENTS, BUT WE OFTEN TALKED WITH EACH OTHER. SINCE THEN, WE HAVE MET ONLY ONCE, AT A POLITICAL FUNCTION. MY RIVALS IN THIS ELECTION CAMPAIGN HAVE OFTEN MISREPRESENTED OUR RELATIONSHIP, AND HAVE DESCRIBED ME AS TEITELBOIM'S SECRET ALLY. HOWEVER, I THINK THAT PEOPLE OF DIFFERENT PERSUASIONS CAN TALK WITH EACH OTHER AND CAN REACH AGREEMENT. THAT HAS BEEN DONE IN CHILE WITH SOME SUCCESS.

DIE WELT: THE COMMUNIST PARTY BACKED YOUR CANDIDACY. WILL IT BE REPRESENTED IN THE NEW GOVERNMENT?

AYLWIN: NOT AT ALL.

DIE WELT: BUT THE FUTURE GOVERNMENT WILL BE A LEFT-CENTER GOVERNMENT AND WILL REFLECT THE COMPOSITION OF THE OPPOSITION TODAY.

AYLWIN: YES, CHILE WILL HAVE A LEFT-CENTER GOVERNMENT. THE VARIOUS SOCIALIST CURRENTS WILL BE REPRESENTED. HOWEVER, THE STRONGEST MOVEMENT IS THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY WHICH IS IN THE CENTER.

DIE WELT: DO YOU THINK THAT FOLLOWING THESE ELECTIONS, THE PANORAMA OF THE OPPOSITION WILL CHANGE?

AYLWIN: I HAVE NO DOUBT ABOUT THAT. THERE HAVE BEEN FOUR FAMILIES IN THE PAST -- THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC FAMILY, THE SOCIAL DEMOCRATICALLY-ORIENTED FAMILY OF THE OLD RADICAL PARTY, THE SOCIALIST FAMILY, AND THE FAMILY OF THE RIGHT CENTER. THEY ALL WANT TO SURVIVE.

DIE WELT: MANY PEOPLE SAY THAT THE SOCIALIST RICARDO LAGOS IS THE STRONGEST FIGURE OF THE OPPOSITION ALLIANCE. WHAT ROLE WILL HE PLAY IN THE FUTURE?

AYLWIN: HE WILL CONCENTRATE ON PARLIAMENTARY WORK AS A SENATOR. AS IS THE CASE IN EVERY PARLIAMENTARY DEMOCRACY, HE CANNOT BE A MEMBER OF THE GOVERNMENT AS A REPRESENTATIVE OF CONGRESS. [CONTINUED]

TST2-MUC4-0089

BOGOTA, 30 MAR 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO TODAY MET WITH 8 OF THE 13 MEMBERS OF THE 19 APRIL MOVEMENT (M-19) "TEAM OF SPOKESMEN" AT THE NARINO PALACE. BARCO AND THE M-19 MEMBERS TALKED ABOUT THE PEACE PROCESS STARTED BY THE GOVERNMENT AND THE GUERRILLAS.

A PRESIDENTIAL PALACE SOURCE TOLD EFE THAT THE GUERRILLA REPRESENTATIVES DISCUSSED WITH PRESIDENT BARCO SOME OF THE ISSUES TO BE DEBATED AT THE "WORKING ROUNDTABLES." THE "WORKING ROUNDTABLES" COMPRISE DELEGATES OF THE GUERRILLAS, THE GOVERNMENT, AND THE POLITICAL PARTIES REPRESENTED IN THE COLOMBIAN CONGRESS, WHO WILL EXCHANGE VIEWS ON THE CHANGES THE COUNTRY NEEDS.

THE M-19 DELEGATES ARRIVED AT THE NARINO PALACE, LOCATED IN DOWNTOWN BOGOTA, UNDER STRICT SECURITY MEASURES AT 1800 LOCAL TIME (2300 GMT).

MEANWHILE, AT THE PEACE VILLAGE IN THE MOUNTAINS OF CAUCA DEPARTMENT, 350 KM SOUTHWEST OF BOGOTA, M-19 COMMANDER CARLOS PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ RELEASED A COMMUNIQUE IN WHICH HE ACCUSED THE COLOMBIAN ARMY OF ATTACKING AN M-19 GROUP ON 26 MARCH. ACCORDING TO PIZARRO, THE ATTACK WAS STAGED BY THE MILITARY TO "CREATE OBSTACLES FOR THE PEACE PROCESS." HE ADDED THAT COMMANDER MARCO CHALITA, COMMANDER OF THE M-19'S "SOUTHERN FRONT," WAS SLIGHTLY INJURED IN THE FIGHTING.

ON 26 MARCH, 9TH BRIGADE TROOPS CLASHED WITH THE "AMANDA RINCON" GROUP, LED BY CHALITA, IN A RURAL AREA OF PITALITO MUNICIPALITY, HUILA DEPARTMENT. DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL MANUEL JAIME GUERRERO PAZ DESCRIBED THE CLASH AS "AN UNFORTUNATE INCIDENT."

PIZARRO SAID IN A COMMUNIQUE ISSUED AT THE PEACE VILLAGE TODAY THAT THE TROOPS ATTACKED THE REBELS AND THAT "TWO OF OUR COMRADES WERE KILLED AND THREE OTHERS WOUNDED."

THE M-19 COMMANDER SAID "HE SHARED THE DEFENSE MINISTER'S VIEWPOINT," AND HE SAID "OBSTACLES STILL MUST BE OVERCOME" TO ACHIEVE A NATIONAL RECONCILIATION.

THE M-19 BEGAN TALKS WITH THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT IN JANUARY. FOLLOWING A SERIES OF MEETINGS WITH PRESIDENT BARCO'S ENVOYS, THEY AGREED ON THE CREATION OF "ROUNDTABLES." LAST WEEK, THE M-19 AND GOVERNMENT MINISTER RAUL OREJUELA MET AT THE PEACE VILLAGE, WHERE THE GUERRILLAS PRESENTED THE NAMES OF THE DELEGATES THAT WOULD PARTICIPATE AT THE "ROUNDTABLES," WHICH ARE SCHEDULED TO BEGIN DELIBERATIONS ON 3 APRIL.

TST2-MUC4-0090

TEGUCIGALPA, 29 APR 88 (VOZ DE HONDURAS NETWORK) -- [INTERVIEW WITH PRESIDENT JOSE AZCONA HOYO BY FRANCISCO VALERIANO GIRON] [TEXT] [BEGIN RECORDING] [GIRON] IS THERE ANY UNREST BECAUSE OF SOME OF THE LAWS PASSED BY CONGRESS?

[AZCONA] NO, THERE IS NO UNREST BECAUSE OF LAWS PASSED BY CONGRESS. SOME MEASURES THAT HAVE AFFECTED INCOME HAVE BEEN ADOPTED, BUT WE WILL MAKE PROGRESS ANYHOW.

[GIRON] WILL YOU ASK THAT SOME OF THESE LAWS BE RECONSIDERED?

[AZCONA] NO, I AM NOT GOING TO DO THAT. THERE IS, HOWEVER, THE LAW ON COFFEE TAXES WHICH COULD BE DISCUSSED WITH PRODUCERS BECAUSE THE LAW-DECREE ON COFFEE IS VERY DRASTIC. HOWEVER, THE COUNTRY IS MAKING PROGRESS, AND ECONOMIC ACTIVITIES IN VARIOUS SECTORS--COMMERCE, CONSTRUCTION, AND MANUFACTURING--ARE ON THE INCREASE. SOME SECTORS HAVE SOME PROBLEMS, BUT I BELIEVE WE ARE GOING TO RESOLVE THOSE PROBLEMS.

[GIRON] DO YOU HAVE ECONOMIC ADVISERS, MR PRESIDENT?

[AZCONA] ANY PERSON CONSULTED IS AN ECONOMIC ADVISER. THE MAIN ECONOMIC ADVISERS, HOWEVER, ARE THOSE IN THE GOVERNMENT.

[GIRON] IT IS BEING SAID THAT POLITICALLY SPEAKING YOU HAVE BEEN LEFT ON YOUR OWN. IS THIS HOW YOU SEE IT ALSO?

[AZCONA] NO WAY. HOW COULD I BE ALONE? ON THE CONTRARY, WE ARE DOING WELL. I BELIEVE WE ARE GOING TO RECEIVE MORE SUPPORT. I DO NOT SEE WHY I COULD BE LEFT ALONE. THERE IS THE GOVERNMENT AND THE EXPERTS. WE ARE ESTABLISHING RELATIONS WITH THE PARTY, WITH THE MOST IMPORTANT PEOPLE OF THE PARTY.

[GIRON] ARE EMPLOYEES GOING TO BE PRESSURED?

[AZCONA] I DO NOT BELIEVE THEY ARE GOING TO BE FORCED TO DO ANYTHING BECAUSE NO LAW SAYS THAT THE EMPLOYEES OF A GOVERNMENT MUST SUPPORT ANY PARTICULAR PARTY. HOWEVER, I BELIEVE THAT IF THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH WORKS IN UNISON, AS IT HAS BEEN DOING, THEN ALL MEMBERS OF THE LIBERAL PARTY WILL BE HAPPY TO MAKE CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE PARTY TO GUARANTEE A NEW VICTORY.

[GIRON] WOULD YOU SUPPORT REFORMS TO THE ELECTORAL LAW?

[AZCONA] WE DISCUSSED THAT ISSUE TODAY. APPARENTLY THE NATIONAL CONVENTION, WHICH IS THE PARTY'S TOP AUTHORITY, HAS APPROVED SOME REFORMS.

[GIRON] DO YOU AGREE WITH INTERNAL ELECTIONS TAKING PLACE SIMULTANEOUSLY [AS HEARD]?

[AZCONA] I BELIEVE IT WOULD BE BENEFICIAL IF THEY TAKE PLACE IN ONE SINGLE DAY, BUT WE DID NOT DISCUSS THAT TODAY, AND I DO NOT WANT TO DISCUSS DETAILS ABOUT THAT.

[GIRON] DO YOU BELIEVE THAT EITHER YOUR GOVERNMENT OR YOURSELF COULD HAVE BEEN POLITICALLY HARMED BY THE LATEST CRISIS ENDURED BY THE COUNTRY?

[AZCONA] I DO NOT THINK SO. I THINK THAT WHAT HAPPENED WILL BENEFIT THE COUNTRY. ACTS OF VIOLENCE ARE REGRETTABLE, BUT THOSE THAT HAVE TAKEN PLACE HAVE SHOWN THAT WE IN HONDURAS ARE NOT IMMUNE TO VIOLENCE. THE SAME DAY INCIDENTS WERE TAKING PLACE HERE, 13 PERSONS DIED IN SAN SALVADOR AS A RESULT OF A BOMB EXPLOSION. THE LOSS OF LIVES IS UNFORTUNATE AND VIOLENCE AGAINST A BUILDING AND FACILITIES NEXT TO THE U.S. EMBASSY IS REGRETTABLE BECAUSE THIS DOES NOT HELP THE COUNTRY.

[GIRON] HAVE YOU TALKED WITH U.S. GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS ABOUT AN INDEMNITY? IT IS BEING SAID THAT DAMAGE AMOUNTS TO $6 MILLION.

[AZCONA] NO, WE HAVE NOTHING ABOUT $6 MILLION. WHAT WE HAVE RECEIVED IS A NOTE FROM THE U.S. AMBASSADOR THE DAY AFTER THE INCIDENTS. THEY ARE ENTITLED TO FILE A PROTEST. THE NOTE SAYS THAT LATER THERE WILL BE A [WORDS INDISTINCT].

HONDURAS SIGNED THE GENEVA CONVENTION ON THE RESPONSIBILITY OF GOVERNMENTS WHEN ACTIONS ARE CARRIED OUT AGAINST DIPLOMATIC INSTALLATIONS.

[GIRON] THE FORCING OF RADIO STATIONS TO JOIN A RADIO NETWORK AND THE IMPOSING OF A STATE OF EMERGENCY HAVE BEEN THE SOURCE OF MUCH CRITICISM AGAINST YOUR GOVERNMENT.

[AZCONA] I HAVE HEARD SOME CRITICISM BECAUSE OF THE NETWORK. PERHAPS WE HAD IT FOR A FEW HOURS TOO MANY. REGARDING THE STATE OF EMERGENCY, HOWEVER, THE PEOPLE HAVE RESPONDED POSITIVELY BECAUSE ONE MORE CASUALTY WOULD HAVE HAD NEGATIVE EFFECTS. THE STATE OF EMERGENCY MADE IT POSSIBLE FOR PEOPLE TO COOL DOWN, AND THOSE ON THE STREETS RETURNED TO THEIR HOMES. I FEEL IT WAS BENEFICIAL. THE DECLARATION OF EMERGENCY DECREE WAS BASED ON THE CONSTITUTION AND ON PRESIDENTIAL AUTHORITY. CONGRESS WAS INFORMED ABOUT THIS.

I BELIEVE THIS WAS A POSITIVE MEASURE, AND THIS IS HOW THE PEOPLE HAVE VIEWED IT, POSITIVELY.

[GIRON] DO YOU BELIEVE THE SITUATION HAS BEEN OVERCOME?

[AZCONA] WE DO NOT KNOW IF THE SITUATION IS OVER. I THINK SO. I BELIEVE THAT WHAT HAPPENED IS THAT TEMPERS GOT HOT FOR A MOMENT, AND THAT SOME SECTORS, WHICH I DO NOT WANT TO NAME BECAUSE THEY HAVE BEEN IDENTIFIED BY THE PEOPLE, TOOK ADVANTAGE OF THIS. PERHAPS SOME PEOPLE TRIED TO MAKE POLITICAL GAINS AND THE SITUATION GOT OUT OF HAND.

I BELIEVE, HOWEVER, THAT EVERYTHING IS MORE OR LESS QUIET. THE GOVERNMENT IS TALKING WITH THE VARIOUS SECTORS. THERE IS A SMALL STRIKE BY A SMALL GROUP OF HEALTH WORKERS. CHECKS WITH SALARY INCREASES COVERING A 4-MONTH PERIOD WILL BE PAID TODAY. SOME READJUSTMENTS WILL BE MADE TO FAVOR SOME EMPLOYEES WHO HAVE NOT RECEIVED THE INCREASES WE HAD PROMISED.

WE WANT TO APPEAL TO HEALTH SECTOR LABOR UNIONS TO SET ASIDE ANY CONFRONTATIONAL ATTITUDE BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT IS MEETING AND WILL MEET ALL ITS COMMITMENTS.

[GIRON] WHAT CAN YOU TELL US ABOUT THE LATEST INCIDENTS WITH NICARAGUA?

[AZCONA] THESE ARE NOT THE FIRST INCIDENTS. I BELIEVE INCIDENTS WILL CONTINUE HAPPENING. HOWEVER, THE GOVERNMENT IS PREPARED TO ENFORCE RESPECT FOR THE COUNTRY'S SOVEREIGNTY. [END RECORDING]

TST2-MUC4-0091

CLANDESTINE, 14 NOV 89 (CADENA REVOLUCIONARIA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION; PAY CLOSE ATTENTION. WE HAVE RECEIVED THE FOLLOWING REPORT FROM ZACATECOLUCA, LA PAZ DEPARTMENT:

WE DENOUNCE -- OUR COMRADES HAVE DENOUNCED -- THE ROLE PLAYED BY THE GREEN CROSS, WHICH HAS BEEN DISLODGING THE POPULATION IN THE FOLLOWING NEIGHBORHOODS: 27 DE SEPTIEMBRE, CHINCHONTEPEC, AND SANTA LUCIA, LOCATED IN NORTHERN ZACATECOLUCA.

THE GREEN CROSS IS SERVING AS AN INSTRUMENT FOR DMIFA [ARMED FORCES ENGINEERS' MILITARY DETACHMENT] TO DISLODGE THE POPULATION. SOME DMIFA AGENTS ARE WEARING GREEN CROSS UNIFORMS TO DO THAT JOB. THEY GO FROM HOUSE TO HOUSE, IDENTIFYING THEMSELVES WITH GREEN CROSS DOCUMENTS. THEY ARE ASKING FAMILIES ONE BY ONE TO MOVE OUT, TELLING THEM THAT THOSE AREAS WILL BE BOMBED.

WE URGE ORGANIZATIONS SUCH AS THE RED CROSS, THE GREEN CROSS, AND RESCUE TEAMS NOT TO PERMIT THE USE OF INSIGNIAS, UNIFORMS, AND VEHICLES OF HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS BY ARMY TROOPS.

THE DISLODGING OF PEOPLE IN SAN SALVADOR AND NOW IN THE 27 DE SEPTIEMBRE NEIGHBORHOOD IN ZACATECOLUCA IS BEING DONE IN ORDER TO PROCEED WITH THE BOMBING OF THESE DENSELY POPULATED CIVILIAN NEIGHBORHOODS.

TST2-MUC4-0092

SAN SALVADOR, 19 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [STATEMENT] [GENERAL RAFAEL HUMBERTO LARIOS, SALVADORAN DEFENSE AND PUBLIC SECURITY MINISTER] [TEXT] DEAR SALVADORAN PEOPLE, OUR REPUBLIC, OUR SOCIETY, AND OUR PEOPLE BECAME THE VICTIMS OF A MURDEROUS AND TERRORIST AGGRESSION 8 DAYS AGO. THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT CARRIED OUT AN INCURSION IN OUR COUNTRY AND VENTED ALL ITS FURY AND ALL ITS TERROR AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THIS VIOLENT, IRRATIONAL, ILLOGICAL, AND SENSELESS ACTION BEGAN 8 DAYS AGO AGAINST PEACE-LOVING PEOPLE WHO WANT TO WORK, CHOOSE THEIR OWN DESTINY, AND SEEK THEIR WELFARE.

ON THIS OCCASION I AM DEEPLY MOVED BY THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S ATTITUDE, AND, IN MY ROLE AS DEFENSE AND PUBLIC SECURITY MINISTER, I HEARTILY CONGRATULATE THEM. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S ATTITUDE HAS REFLECTED THEIR STOICISM, STRONG WILL, AND INDOMITABLE SPIRIT, HOPE, AND FAITH IN GOD AND THE ARMED FORCES.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, YOUR ATTITUDE IN RECENT DAYS HAS BEEN DIGNIFIED AND IT HAS SET AN EXAMPLE. IT IS WORTHY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WHO HAVE ALWAYS PROVED THEIR FAITH AND WILLINGNESS TO DEFEND A JUST AND NOBLE CAUSE, THE HOMELAND'S CAUSE. THIS IS PRECISELY WHAT HAS GIVEN THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE THE WILL TO LIVE, LOVE, AND ACHIEVE PEACE.

YOUR ATTITUDE ENCOURAGES US, PLACES US UNDER AN OBLIGATION, AND URGES US -- AS AN INSTITUTION AT THE SERVICE OF THE PEOPLE -- TO CONTINUE THE STRUGGLE TO THE END, SO THAT WE MAY ERADICATE FOREVER THE TERROR, VIOLENCE, AND DISRESPECT THAT THE TERRORIST FORCES HAVE TRIED TO IMPOSE ON OUR HARD-WORKING AND INNOCENT PEOPLE.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, YOUR ATTITUDE IS EXEMPLARY, AND WE, THE PROFESSIONAL SOLDIERS, ARE PREPARED -- LIKE WE HAVE ALWAYS BEEN -- TO SUPPORT AND DEFEND UNDER ANY CIRCUMSTANCES AND IN ANY EVENT THE SECURITY, ORDER, TRANQUILLITY, WORK, AND PEACE THAT ALL THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE HAVE A RIGHT TO ENJOY.

ONWARD, SALVADORAN PEOPLE. AS AN INSTITUTION WE NEED YOUR SUPPORT. YOUR SUPPORT IS IMPORTANT AND YOUR UNDERSTANDING IS NECESSARY. YOU MUST BELIEVE IN AND TRUST THE ARMED FORCES, BECAUSE WE, WHO ARE ALSO PEOPLE LIKE YOU, UNDERSTAND THE LEGITIMATE DEMAND AND DESIRE FOR PEACE, FAITH, AND HOPE WHICH PREVAIL IN THE HEARTS AND MINDS OF ALL SALVADORAN CITIZENS -- AND WE ARE PLEASED AND SATISFIED TO DEFEND THEM.

THE ARMED FORCES ARE AN INSTITUTION WHICH HAS THE RESPONSIBILITY OF GUARANTEEING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S WELFARE, AND THEY ARE HIGHLY ENCOURAGED, DEEPLY PLEASED, AND DETERMINED TO CONTINUE THEIR WORK. THEY WILL DEFEND THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND GUARANTEE THEM A FUTURE WITH DIGNITY, PEACE, WELFARE, AND SECURITY. [CONTINUED]

TST2-MUC4-0094

BOGOTA, 20 APR 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO] [TEXT] FURTHERMORE, WE HAVE HAD TO STRUGGLE AGAINST MANY OF OUR FELLOW COUNTRYMEN'S SKEPTICISM AND PESSIMISM. THE FIRST THING THE GOVERNMENT DID WAS TO CONSOLIDATE ITS BASES TO WAGE A STRUGGLE AGAINST THOSE TERRORIST GROUPS WITH WHATEVER FIRMNESS AND PERSEVERANCE WAS CALLED FOR.

WE STRENGTHENED INVESTIGATION ORGANIZATIONS, WE CREATED SPECIAL PUBLIC COURTS. WE MODIFIED PENAL LAWS AND PROCEDURES. WE INTRODUCED NEW MEASURES TO ENCOURAGE CITIZEN PARTICIPATION AND TO PROTECT CITIZENS. WE FORMED NEW COMPONENTS TO BOLSTER OUR PUBLIC FORCES. OUR EFFORTS TOOK QUITE A BIT OF TIME. ONE CANNOT PROVIDE AN OVERNIGHT SOLUTION FOR THESE COMPLEX PROBLEMS WITH WHICH YOU ARE ALL VERY FAMILIAR.

ONCE THE INSTITUTIONS IN CHARGE OF MAINTAINING PUBLIC ORDER AND SECURITY WERE STRENGTHENED, WE CONCENTRATED OUR AVAILABLE RESOURCES ON SOLVING THE CRIMES COMMITTED BY THOSE TERRORIST GROUPS. THE RESULTS HAVE BEEN INCREASINGLY POSITIVE, BOTH IN THE FIGHT AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING -- WHICH IS THE CENTRAL FOCUS OF MANY OF THESE TERRORIST GROUPS -- AND IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST GANGS OF HIRED ASSASSINS AND PRIVATE JUSTICE ORGANIZATIONS, ALSO KNOWN AS DEATH SQUADS.

NEVER BEFORE HAD WE ACHIEVED SUCH POSITIVE RESULTS. I AM SURE THAT EVEN THOUGH WE WILL FACE DIFFICULTIES AND OBSTACLES, WE WILL CONTINUE TO WIN THIS BATTLE AGAINST TERRORISM. TO DATE, WE HAVE DISBANDED 23 GANGS OF HIRED ASSASSINS OPERATING IN ENVIGADO IN ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT, HUICAN IN BOYACA DEPARTMENT, PUERTO LOPEZ AND SAN MARTIN IN META DEPARTMENT, LA ROCHELA IN SANTANDER DEPARTMENT, AND LLANOS DEL YARI IN CAQUETA DEPARTMENT. THESE GANGS OF HIRED ASSASSINS HAD PARTICIPATED IN MOST OF THE MURDERS OF THE COUNTRY'S LEFTIST LEADERS. [CONTINUED]

TST2-MUC4-0095

GUATEMALA CITY, 18 MAY 90 (EL GRAFICO) -- [TEXT] GENERAL HECTOR GRAMAJO MORALES HAS REPORTED THAT LAST NIGHT'S TERRORIST ACTS WERE PROBABLY INTENDED TO DAMAGE GUATEMALAN AIR FORCE INSTALLATIONS, BUT ONE OF THE EXPLOSIVE DEVICES WENT OFF PREMATURELY.

HE ADDED THAT ONE OF THE EXPLOSIVE DEVICES HIT A WALL OF THE AIR FORCE INSTALLATIONS AND THE SHOCK WAVE FROM THE EXPLOSION DAMAGED SOME BUILDINGS.

ACCORDING TO PRELIMINARY CONCLUSIONS, THE ATTACK WAS PROBABLY A PROPAGANDA PLOY BECAUSE THE DEVICES WERE RUDIMENTARY AND SIMILAR TO FIRECRACKERS.

THE TERRORIST ACTIONS SEEM TO BE MOTIVATED BY THE FACT THAT THE IRREGULAR GROUPS ARE SHRINKING CONSIDERABLY. EVIDENCE OF THIS IS THE FACT THAT A SUBVERSIVE WHO SURRENDERED ON THE SOUTHERN COAST WAS CARRYING SOME IMPORTANT DOCUMENTS IN WHICH THE GUERRILLAS ADMITTED THAT THEY HAD MADE A BIG EFFORT TO SHOW THEIR PRESENCE, BUT THAT NOTHING SUBSTANTIAL RESULTED AND THEY SUFFERED MANY CASUALTIES INSTEAD, GRAMAJO SAID.

WHEN QUESTIONED ABOUT THE POSSIBLE IMPACT OF THESE TERRORIST ACTIONS ON THE TALKS BEING HELD IN OSLO, NORWAY, GRAMAJO SAID THAT THOSE WHO ARE TAKING PART IN THE TALKS DO NOT MAINTAIN CONTACT WITH THE GROUPS THAT CARRY OUT THE TERRORIST ACTIONS.

AMONG THOSE GROUPS, THERE IS ONE FACTION THAT IS CALLED THE INTERNATIONAL MILITANT GROUP. THIS FACTION IS COMPRISED OF PERSONS WHO LOVE ADVENTURE; THESE PEOPLE TAKE ADVANTAGE OF SUBVERSIVE GROUPS TO ENGAGE IN SOME OF THESE ACTIVITIES.

TST2-MUC4-0096

LIMA, 21 MAR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE PERUVIAN NAVY TODAY FORMALLY DENIED THAT ITS INTELLIGENCE SERVICES HAD UNCOVERED A PLOT TO ASSASSINATE WRITER MARIO VARGAS LLOSA, WHO IS CONSIDERED TO BE THE FAVORITE CANDIDATE TO WIN THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION THAT WILL BE HELD ON 8 APRIL.

CITING AN ALLEGED NAVY INTELLIGENCE REPORT, A TELEVISION STATION CARRIED A REPORT -- WHICH WAS LATER PICKED UP BY A NEWSPAPER -- TACITLY SUGGESTING THAT THE COMMUNIST TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MRTA) AND PROMINENT PEOPLE IN THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT, INCLUDING PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA, WERE INVOLVED IN THE ALLEGED PLOT.

THE NAVY HAS ISSUED AN OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUE IN WHICH IT DENIES THE ALLEGED SOURCE OF THE DOCUMENT AND STATES THAT THE ALLEGATIONS, CONSIDERING THE RANK OF THE PERSONALITIES MENTIONED, COULD BE A MATTER AFFECTING NATIONAL SECURITY.

THE REPORT ON THE PLOT WAS INITIALLY CARRIED BY CHANNEL FOUR DURING A POLITICAL PROGRAM. IT WAS LATER PICKED UP BY THE CENTER-RIGHT WING NEWSPAPER EXPRESO, ONE OF THE LEADING NEWSPAPERS IN THE COUNTRY.

ALVARO VARGAS LLOSA, A SON AND SPOKESMAN FOR THE PERUVIAN WRITER, STATED THAT "WE GIVE GREAT CREDENCE TO THE DOCUMENT SHOWN ON TELEVISION BUT THE AUTHORITIES SEEM TO HAVE IGNORED IT. IT CONCERNS MY FATHER AND IT SHOULD BE TAKEN SERIOUSLY."

ACCORDING TO THE DOCUMENT, THE AUTHENTICITY OF WHICH HAS BEEN OFFICIALLY DENIED BY THE NAVY, AN MRTA HIT SQUAD WOULD MURDER THE NOVELIST AND PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE OF THE DEMOCRATIC FRONT (FREDEMO) AND OTHER PERSONALITIES OF THE CENTER-RIGHT WING COALITION.

THE REPORT ADDS THAT THE PLOT MAY HAVE BEEN CONCOCTED EARLY IN DECEMBER LAST YEAR AT A MEETING REPORTEDLY ATTENDED BY PRESIDENT GARCIA, INTERIOR MINISTER AGUSTIN MANTILLA, TWO SENIOR LEADERS OF THE RULING AMERICAN POPULAR REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE (APRA), AND BY AN UNIDENTIFIED MRTA MEMBER.

TST2-MUC4-0098

SAN JOSE (COSTA RICA), 27 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE GUATEMALAN ASSOCIATION OF UNIVERSITY STUDENTS (AEU), WHOSE TOP LEADERS WERE KIDNAPPED, MURDERED, OR HAD TO GO INTO HIDING DURING THE LAST FEW WEEKS, TODAY DEMANDED THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY'S SOLIDARITY TO CONTAIN THE WAVE OF VIOLENCE THAT HAS SHAKEN THE COUNTRY OVER THE LAST 2 MONTHS.

TWO MEMBERS OF THE AEU COORDINATING BOARD, WHO LAST WEEK WENT INTO EXILE, SAID THAT IT IS URGENT THAT A PERMAMENT UN RAPPORTEUR BE SENT TO GUATEMALA TO CERTIFY THE CONTINUAL AND INCREASING HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS IN THE COUNTRY.

THE UNIVERSITY STUDENTS ALSO CALLED FOR GOVERNMENTS AND INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS TO SEND DELEGATIONS TO GUATEMALA AS SOON AS POSSIBLE, "TO PRESSURE THE VINICIO CEREZO GOVERNMENT TO STOP THE CAMPAIGN OF TERROR AND THE BLOODBATH BEING PREPARED BY THE ARMY TO CONTAIN THE STUDENT AND PEOPLES' MOVEMENTS."

THE AEU REPRESENTATIVES SAID THEY HAD EVIDENCE THAT THE RECENT KIDNAPPING OF 12 STUDENT LEADERS, OUT OF WHICH 5 WERE LATER FOUND MURDERED WITH BRUTAL SIGNS OF TORTURE, "WAS DIRECTLY PLANNED AND CARRIED OUT BY THE GUATEMALAN ARMY.

THESE SAME STUDENTS BELIEVE THAT VINICIO CEREZO'S CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT "KNOWS WHO IS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE CAMPAIGN OF TERROR, AND IT WILL NOT TAKE ACTION BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT IS AN ACCOMPLICE OF THE MILITARY."

THE AEU LEADERS, WHO DID NOT DARE GIVE THEIR NAMES BECAUSE THEIR FAMILIES "COULD SUFFER WORSE CONSEQUENCES IN GUATEMALA," INSISTED THAT "THE ONLY THING REMAINING FOR GUATEMALANS TO FACE THE TERROR AND VIOLENCE IS INTERNATIONAL SOLIDARITY."

"THE SITUATION IS TERRIBLE. THE HUMAN RIGHTS PROSECUTOR HIMSELF TOLD US THAT HE COULD DO NOTHING TO CONTAIN THIS WAVE OF REPRESSION AND ADVISED US THAT WE BETTER SEEK INTERNATIONAL PRESSURE," ONE OF THE EXILED AEU LEADERS SAID.

ACCORDING TO THEM, THE WAVE OF REPRESSION OVER THE LAST FEW WEEKS AGAINST GUATEMALAN UNIVERSITY STUDENTS "IS THE WORST SINCE 1978," WHEN NUMEROUS UNIVERSITY LEADERS WERE MURDERED, INCLUDING AEU SECRETARY GENERAL OLIVERIO CASTANEDA, KILLED AT POINT-BLANK RANGE WHILE HEADING A DEMONSTRATION IN THE MIDDLE OF THE CAPITAL.

CASTANEDA'S MURDER FORCED THE AEU TO ELIMINATE THE POST OF SECRETARY GENERAL AND MODIFY ITS STRATEGIES SO ITS TOP LEADERS WOULD NOT BECOME EASY TARGETS OF REPRESSION. HOWEVER, IN LIGHT OF THE LATEST EVENTS, THESE CHANGES SEEM TO HAVE HAD LITTLE EFFECT.

"BECAUSE NOW THEY CANNOT IDENTIFY ANY PARTICULAR LEADER TO KILL, LIKE THEY DID WITH OLIVERIO, THIS TIME THEY HAVE ATTACKED US ALL," ONE OF THE BANISHED LEADERS , WHO ARRIVED IN COSTA RICA LAST WEEKEND, SAID.

SINCE 21 AUGUST, WHEN THE CAMPAIGN OF STUDENT KIDNAPPINGS AND MURDERS BEGAN, OF THE 16 MEMBERS OF THE AEU EXECUTIVE COORDINATING BOARD, THREE WERE MURDERED, SEVEN ARE STILL MISSING, FOUR HAD TO GO INTO HIDING, AND TWO WENT INTO EXILE.

"I WAS TOLD THROUGH A FRIEND: YOUR TURN IS ON 4 SEPTEMBER. I THEN HAD TO HIDE UNTIL I WAS ABLE TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY," ONE OF THE EXILED TOLD AFP WITH ANGUISH.

"WE REALLY DID NOT EXPECT THIS. WE THOUGHT WE WERE GOING TO BE POLITICALLY NEUTRALIZED, BUT NEVER THOUGHT THEY WOULD ORDER US KIDNAPPED AND MURDERED," ANOTHER OF THE STUDENTS ADMITTED.

FOR BOTH LEADERS "THE ARMY'S REPRESSIVE CAMPAIGN AGAINST THE AEU SEEKS TO SCARE THE POPULATION AND STOP THE PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT THAT BECAME MOTIVATED FOLLOWING THE LAST TEACHERS' STRIKE ALL OVER THE COUNTRY."

HOWEVER, THEY CONCLUDED, "THE ARMY WILL NEVER BE ABLE TO END THE AEU BECAUSE TO DO SO THE ARMY WOULD HAVE TO KIDNAP, MURDER, OR SEND INTO EXILE THE 60,000 SAN CARLOS UNIVERSITY STUDENTS, THE LARGEST AND OLDEST UNIVERSITY IN CENTRAL AMERICA."

TST2-MUC4-0099

BOGOTA, 7 JUL 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN OFFICIALS REPORT THAT GUERRILLAS PRESUMED TO BE MEMBERS OF THE PRO-CASTRO ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION (ELN) TODAY ONCE AGAIN DYNAMITED THE CANO LIMON-COVENAS OIL PIPELINE, COLOMBIA'S MAJOR OIL PIPELINE.

AN ECOPETROL [COLOMBIAN PETROLEUM ENTERPRISE] SPOKESMAN SAID THAT THE EXPLOSION TOOK PLACE AT KM - 102 OF THE PIPE NEAR BENADIA IN ARAUCA INTENDANCY, IN THE EASTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY.

THIS ATTACK TAKES PLACE 25 DAYS AFTER A PREVIOUS GUERRILLA ACTION, WHICH INTERRUPTED THE PUMPING OF CRUDE THROUGH THE 780 - KM LONG PIPELINE. ON 16 JUNE, THE ELN DESTROYED THE CANO LIMON-COVENAS OIL TERMINAL ON COLOMBIA'S ATLANTIC COAST, IN WHAT IS CONSIDERED THE MOST SERIOUS ATTACK AGAINST COLOMBIA'S PETROLEUM INDUSTRY IN ITS HISTORY. SINCE THAT TIME, COLOMBIA HAS BEEN FORCED TO SUSPEND AN AVERAGE OF 180,000 OF THE 220,000 DAILY BARRELS OF CRUDE PIPED THROUGH THE COUNTRY'S LEADING PIPELINE.

TODAY'S ATTACK IS THE 25TH DURING 1989, AND THE THIRD THIS WEEK, THE ECOPETROL SPOKESMAN REVEALED. THE ELN'S ATTACKS HAVE REDUCED THE NATION'S HYDROCARBON PRODUCTION THIS YEAR BY 20 PERCENT, WITH LOSSES EXCEEDING $180 MILLION. THE ELN HAS DYNAMITED THE CANO LIMON-COVENAS PIPELINE 125 TIMES SINCE JANUARY 1988, CAUSING LOSSES OF MORE THAN $450 MILLION AS A RESULT OF OIL SPILLS, HALTED PRODUCTION, THE SUSPENSION OF EXPORTS, AND ECOLOGICAL DAMAGE, THE ECOPETROL SPOKESMAN ADDED.

DURING THE 25 YEARS OF ITS ARMED STRUGGLE, THE ELN -- LED BY FORMER SPANISH PRIEST MANUEL PEREZ -- HAS INTENSIFIED ITS ATTACKS AGAINST THE PETROLEUM INFRASTRUCTURE, ARGUING THAT IT PERPETRATES THESE ACTIONS "TO PREVENT THE EXPLOITATION OF COLOMBIA'S NATURAL RESOURCES."